













    
        
    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    







    

    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"  xml:lang="en-us"  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            

            
                
            

            
                <link href="https://hockenworks.com/tags/vr/" rel="self" type="text/html"/>
            
        
            

            

            
                <link href="https://hockenworks.com/tags/vr/rss.xml" rel="alternate" type="application/rss+xml"/>
            
        

        

        

        <description>Recent content</description>

        
            <language>en-us</language>
        

        
            <lastBuildDate>2025-06-23 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</lastBuildDate>
        

        <link>https://hockenworks.com/tags/vr/</link>

        

        <title>VR · Tags · hockenworks</title>

        

        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>&ldquo;The Flapper&rdquo; is a project that spawned out of a simple VR movement mechanic test that I had in my head for a while, which turned out to be surprisingly fun! The idea is to flap your arms to fly - wrapped up as a multiplayer battle to really get people moving.</p>
<p>In order to start working on this game, because there was so much standard VR code that I had to write for <a href="/treekeepers-vr">Treekeepers</a>, I decided to make a sort of engine out of the Treekeepers codebase and work off of that rather than start from scratch. That let me tie in some of the nice associated graphics, music and sound effects I had made, and a bunch of other helper functions and tools I use for things like the camera following around the character, how I deal with collisions, a bunch of netcode, etc.</p>
<p>You can see my more detailed post about that engine here: <a href="/treekeepers-engine">Treekeepers Engine</a></p>
<h2 id="core-mechanic--gameplay">Core Mechanic &amp; Gameplay</h2>
<p>Most of the start of this game was just tuning the movement mechanic, which borrowed from some physics realities and some elements I made up to make flapping feel good. But, the essential idea was that each arm generates unique thrust in the direction it moves with an exponential applied to its speed. It&rsquo;s hard to describe any native VR mechanic with words and videos only, but to me and the folks I demoed it to, it felt &ldquo;right&rdquo; for how flying should work if you did it by flapping your arms - and that feeling is based in the physical reality of wing-powered flight. I had a ton of fun just jetting around the obstacle courses I made for myself.</p>
<p>My idea for this other than just the mechanic was to make a sort of gorilla tag-esque multiplayer game where players would fly around and try to pop each other&rsquo;s balloons in an NES balloon fight {link} style. Ideally something like 15 to 20 people would be in a lobby flying around and trying to pop each other.</p>
<p>Like gorilla tag I didn&rsquo;t want anyone to have to &ldquo;sit out&rdquo; of the game, so it&rsquo;s essentially a deathmatch where the player who pops the most balloons wins, and is also visible who&rsquo;s winning, because they also gain the balloons that they pop. In some playtests players would have 20 or 30 balloons on their heads. This was my clever idea of adding a built-in rubber-band effect to the gameplay as well, since having more balloons over your head made you a bigger target to pop. The gameplay worked well - but I never quite got the game to a place with netcode and networking engine where multiplayer felt seamless enough.</p>
<p>Here’s a video of one of the later states of the game, where I have it fully networked and am testing with friends, though it still has a few bugs here:</p>

    <div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
      <iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" loading="eager" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Vxn8rDOZ7dU?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video"></iframe>
    </div>

<h2 id="today">Today</h2>
<p>I stopped working on this project after about 3 months. It turned out that flying alone with this mechanic was very compelling (and also a great workout!) but the networking engine I had used for Treekeepers, Photon, was not up to the task for how low latency a competitive game needed to be. Treekeepers was four-player co-op so Photon was just fine.</p>
<p>In the future I might pick this one back up (or maybe have an AI agent pick it up for me depending on how that goes) using <a href="https://spacetimedb.com/">space-time DB</a> which looks like a great solution for this type of game that doesn&rsquo;t require a whole ton of cloud programming and setup</p>
<p>I haven&rsquo;t made a build of this game public yet due to its unfinished and multiplayer nature - it&rsquo;s not set up with a usable server other than for testing. If I receive interest in playing it from enough people, I&rsquo;ll go back in and package up the single player parts as a tech demo and put a download here.</p>
<p>I learned a lot from this project, both in terms of game code organization and game mechanic design, and I still think it&rsquo;s a great concept. I hope this movement mechanic becomes the basis for a full game in the future and with any luck with the direction software development AI is going I might get that opportunity sooner vs later. About 3 weeks from now, I will be releasing an article on the modern state of AI software development, including a deep dive on some of the latest tools for web and game development, so stay tuned!</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:hockenworks.com,2025-06-23:/the-flapper/</guid>

                
                    <link>https://hockenworks.com/the-flapper/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>The Flapper - A Physical VR Multiplayer Game</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I made my latest Unity project into a multi-application &ldquo;engine&rdquo;. I am now building and releasing two applications from one project. Let me show you how it works.</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="Switching apps in the treekeepers engine"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/treekeepers-app-switcher-1.gif"   style="height: auto; max-width: 720px; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">Switching apps in the treekeepers engine</span>
    
</div>

<p>I did this because I had a lot of assets and code in Treekeepers that would directly translate to a new project I was prototyping. I considered other approaches - git submodules, unity packages, just cloning my old project. After a cost-benefit writeup I decided on this.</p>
<p>Now when I change variables, I edit a class called “Application Definition” for each application, which look like this:</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="An applictaion definition in the editor"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/treekeepers-app-switcher-2.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 400px; width: 100%"   >


    
</div>

<p>My plan is to use this new &ldquo;Engine project&rdquo; to not only update multiple games with common assets and code easily, but also as an instant starting point for any new networked VR/AR prototype.</p>
<p>As I go, any code I refactor to be generic across all projects goes in an Engine folder. Same for prefabs, materials, etc.</p>
<p>This way, if this gets cumbersome in the future, I can make a git submodule out of everything in &ldquo;Engine&rdquo; and import that into a new project.</p>
<p>Here are the scripts. The first runs via the Editor UI and takes variables for anything that needs to be different by project. The second file has the application definition classes you saw in the image above.</p>
<p><a href="https://gist.github.com/hockenmaier/14d50ff0bb90aece1cc6de1b9fc5419d">https://gist.github.com/hockenmaier/14d50ff0bb90aece1cc6de1b9fc5419d</a></p>
<script src="https://gist.github.com/hockenmaier/14d50ff0bb90aece1cc6de1b9fc5419d.js"></script>

<p>The files are free to use. Check them out if you&rsquo;re in a similar situation, but be warned there are still some hard-coded things and references you’ll need to change.</p>
<p>Has anyone taken this approach before? Curious on other&rsquo;s take or approaches to similar problems!</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:hockenworks.com,2023-03-17:/treekeepers-engine/</guid>

                
                    <link>https://hockenworks.com/treekeepers-engine/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Fri, 17 Mar 2023 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Treekeepers Engine</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    





    







    



    























<img  alt="The Treekeepers Puddle Jumper"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/treekeepers_moonlight.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">The Treekeepers Puddle Jumper</span>
    
</div>

<p>Treekeepers VR is a networked VR game where up to 4 players can cooperate to navigate an oversized world and save a giant tree.</p>
<p>Treekeepers is in production on both Quest (standalone VR) and Steam (PC VR) with full cross-play functionality. See the <a href="https://togetheragainstudios.com/treekeepersvr/">Treekeepers VR Website</a> for links to all storefronts and more detail about the game.</p>
<h2 id="heading"></h2>
<h2 id="development">Development</h2>
<p>I began working on Treekeepers in June 2021, and my primary goal was to go significantly deeper into Unity and make a fully networked game. Very few co-op games existed in VR at the time (the area is still lacking), and my intention was to answer this need and create a game that 4 players could cooperate in within a static frame of reference (players move within a ship, and the ship moves through the world) while having to solve coordination challenges together.</p>
<p>I initially designed the project for SteamVR only using the SteamVR SDK but quickly realized that a VR game released only on PC would miss the majority of the userbase, as the (then Oculus) Quest 2 was quickly dominating the market. Treekeepers was a good fit for a mobile platform with its simple low-poly cel-shaded design, so I pivoted to using OpenXR about two months into the project to support VR interactions on both PC and mobile (Android) devices like the Quest 2.</p>
<p>By summer 2022, I had a releasable product, albeit only with one “world” available. I decided to push the game to early access to gather rapid feedback from real players, and after getting approved for both storefronts, Treekeepers released to early access on September 30, 2022.</p>]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:hockenworks.com,2022-10-01:/treekeepers-vr/</guid>

                
                    <link>https://hockenworks.com/treekeepers-vr/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Treekeepers VR</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>Editor&rsquo;s note from 2025:</p>
<p>This article was written as part of the launch of <a href="/treekeepers-vr">Treekeepers VR</a> and the sole proprietorship Together Again Studios, and represents some of my core beliefs of the value of VR and where it&rsquo;s taking us socially. Though I&rsquo;m no longer actively working on Treekeepers, I do hold that VR and AR are truly the &ldquo;endgame&rdquo; of interface and one that could save us from some of the social attitudes caused by social media of today. Enjoy!</p>
</blockquote>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="proofreader GPT"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/together-again-studios.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 400px; width: 100%"   >


    
</div>

<p>With Together Again Studios and Treekeepers VR, we&rsquo;re setting out to solve an insidious problem we see all around us:</p>
<p><strong>Social Media Is Anti-Social</strong></p>
<p>Though Facebook, Instagram, Twitter, and Tiktok all let us share more with each other than ever before, what we are sharing is surprisingly hostile and dismissive of opinions other than our own.</p>
<p>Though Zoom, Hangouts and Teams let us finally see each other from a distance, we still can&rsquo;t speak naturally. We depend on tools like &ldquo;mute&rdquo;. We create meeting upon meeting with different sets of the same group of people. And we don&rsquo;t form the depth of relationships we could in-person.</p>
<p>We as humans are all-too-capable of forming us-versus-them &ldquo;tribes&rdquo; and dehumanizing those who appear too different, and this problem is becoming ever more apparent behind the curtain of the graphical user interface.</p>
<p><strong>Virtual and augmented reality are a way out</strong></p>
<p>In 2016, thanks to pioneers like Palmer Luckey, Michael Abrash, and John Carmack, we suddenly gained access to a technology that removes the curtain and forces us to see eachother. And in 2020, an event that has permanently limited our in-person interaction arose and gave new meaning to this technology.</p>
<p>In VR/AR, voices are no longer text on a screen, taken out of context by our social media bubbles. They&rsquo;re voices again.</p>
<p>In VR/AR, people are no longer user profiles with one image and a tag-line. They&rsquo;re really people, with bodies, faces, and hands that can point and gesture.</p>
<p>In VR/AR, messages are not just &ldquo;public&rdquo;, or &ldquo;direct&rdquo;. Conversations are dynamic, with people physically approaching one another to talk, with people moving in and out of physical groups, and with people attending public conversations together again while still able to have &ldquo;sidebar&rdquo; conversations.</p>
<p>All these abilities we used to have in-person, we have gained again in virtual reality.</p>
<p>Soon, we&rsquo;ll go even further with this technology. We&rsquo;ll be able to make real eye contact with eachother in VR. We&rsquo;ll use AR to invite distant friends and family over to our homes.</p>
<p>And at Together Again, we plan on using these new tools to let people like eachother again.</p>
<p><strong>Treekeepers: Only Possible in VR</strong></p>
<p>Why is Treekeepers a VR Game?</p>
<p><strong>Multiplayer of this depth only works in VR</strong></p>
<p>The challenges in Treekeepers VR hinge on player coordination and quick group decisions - Which weapon should we upgrade? Who&rsquo;s doing which job? Where are we going?</p>
<p>In VR, you gain the ability to gesture and point to enemies and obstacles naturally.</p>
<p>No more &ldquo;Who is the green player?&rdquo; - spend zero mental energy figuring out who you are talking to. Just turn towards them and speak.</p>
<p><strong>Scale is the most fun when you&rsquo;re in the world</strong></p>
<p>We&rsquo;re going to be exploring oversized objects around a gigantic tree. Only VR can get the full benefit of this experience.</p>
<p><strong>VR can be uncomfortable</strong></p>
<p>BUT, experiencing it via a static vehicle which acts as a persistent frame of reference reduces motion sickness.</p>
<p>No need to rotate - gameplay is based on the hot air balloon always facing one direction, and players navigating within it.</p>
<hr>
<p>Check out Treekeepers VR <a href="/treekeepers-vr">here</a></p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:hockenworks.com,2022-08-01:/social-media-is-antisocial/</guid>

                
                    <link>https://hockenworks.com/social-media-is-antisocial/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Social Media Is Anti-Social</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>The &ldquo;Human Joystick&rdquo; is an experimental VR movement system in which the player moves through the virtual environment by changing their physical location within their VR &ldquo;playspace&rdquo;.</p>

    <div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
      <iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" loading="eager" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/q_1itpdiPb4?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video"></iframe>
    </div>

<p>A demo of the human joystick movement system, showing how the system can work on flat surfaces or terrain.</p>
<p>This was my first barebones VR project. Though I knew Unity going in, VR and 3D games in general have a lot of unique aspects that I wanted to learn about while trying to solve an actual problem, rather than following tutorials or demos online.</p>
<p>VR has some adoption problems in its current state. We all know of some of the main problems- the clunky headset, the nausea issues, and of course the pricetag. But one major problem that you don&rsquo;t really notice until you get into it, is the lack of a good solution for virtual movement.</p>
<p>I had been wondering about &ldquo;the human joystick&rdquo; as a potential a solution to this particular problem ever since getting into consumer VR in 2016.</p>
<p>In most modern VR systems, the player can move physically around the room if they choose. Some applications and games depend on this - they put you in a small space and rely on your physical movement in order to reach different areas and interact with things. But games that provide a more traditional sense of scale and allow players to move through large worlds cannot rely on physical motion, because their users are constrained by physical space. Because of this, you see all kinds of &ldquo;artificial&rdquo; locomotion systems in order to let people move around - some just like traditional 2D games that let users &ldquo;slide&rdquo; their playspaces around the world using a joystick, and others that adopt teleportation mechanics. Neither feel very natural as compared to actually walking, and some can be downright sickening.</p>
<p>My goal with this project was to solve this problem with a mixture of physical and artificial movement.</p>
<p>It works like this: When the player is standing near the center of their playspace, physical VR movement applies. The player can move around and interact with things with their actual bodies. But once the player moves further from the center, the plaspace starts to move with them in the same direction as the vector from the center of the player&rsquo;s space to their current position. This allows for some of the benefits that physical movement experiences have, while allowing the players to more naturally move through an infinite amount of space.</p>
<p>I experimented with several speeds, both static and scaling with the distance between the center and the player. I also experimented with the size of the physical movement &ldquo;deadzone&rdquo; and with vertical and constrained movement across hills, valleys, and buildings.</p>
<hr>
<table>
  <thead>
      <tr>
          <th style="text-align: center">


















<div class="paige-image">
    





























    



    

    
        

        

        
    
        

        

        
    
        

        
            

    



    







    





    



    























<img   class="img-fluid "  crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/human_joystick_centered.jpg"   style="display:block; height: auto; margin:0 auto; width: 60%"   >


</div>
</th>
          <th style="text-align: left"><em>View from the player&rsquo;s perspective looking at the guides at his feet. With the white dot in the red deadzone, the player isn&rsquo;t moving.</em></th>
      </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
      <tr>
          <td style="text-align: center">


















<div class="paige-image">
    





























    



    

    
        

        

        
    
        

        

        
    
        

        
            

    



    







    





    



    























<img   class="img-fluid "  crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/human_joystick_moving.jpg"   style="display:block; height: auto; margin:0 auto; width: 60%"   >


</div>
</td>
          <td style="text-align: left"><strong><em>When the white dot is in the green area, the player moves in that direction. Here I am moving forward and left at about half of max speed.</em></strong></td>
      </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<hr>
<p>Eventually I found some good default values and the system worked, but there were some unforeseen problems: First, it was more difficult to center yourself within the playspace without looking at the visible guides I put at the player&rsquo;s feet than I expected. Second and more importantly, when you were already moving in one direction, it was not as simple as I thought to start moving in another direction accurately without fully returning to center, which was an immersion breaker.</p>
<p>Ultimately I put the project up for others to view but have not expanded it into a full experience or released it on any marketplaces. Feel free to download the Unity project and try it on your own VR setup if you&rsquo;re curious.</p>]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:hockenworks.com,2020-01-01:/human-joystick/</guid>

                
                    <link>https://hockenworks.com/human-joystick/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Human Joystick VR</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
