













    
        
    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    







    

    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"  xml:lang="en-us"  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            

            
                
            

            
                <link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/writing/" rel="self" type="text/html"/>
            
        
            

            

            
                <link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/writing/rss.xml" rel="alternate" type="application/rss+xml"/>
            
        

        

        

        <description>Recent content</description>

        
            <language>en-us</language>
        

        
            <lastBuildDate>2024-04-30 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</lastBuildDate>
        

        <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/writing/</link>

        

        <title>Writing · Categories · Home</title>

        

        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<div style="display: flex; align-items: center; justify-content: center; gap: 10px; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    







    



    






















<img  alt="Alt text"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/brian_portrait.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 200px"   >


    
        <span style="font-style: italic;">←me</span>
    
</div>

<p>I build things! I love making games and things with VR and AI.</p>
<p>I’ve been at one company for a long time and have built a lot there, led some large teams, and released several things on my own too, in a bunch of software domains. I started on back-office stuff like billing systems, TV scheduling systems, IP rights management systems, file ingest systems for News, and several games and tools outside of work.</p>
<p>Most recently I&rsquo;m making some pretty awesome stuff in agentic AI for the mundane work that the people at my company have to do!</p>
<p>My bias is to build rather than talk. I&rsquo;m the one pushing to just try to build the thing, to scrap it early if needed, and to take risks releasing early. We always know more, and usually throw away our plans, when we start to build.</p>
<p>I post here mostly about things I&rsquo;m making and occasional essays.</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2024-04-30:/about-me/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/about-me/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Hi, I’m Brian</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I came across this tweet today that was surprisingly contentious. Maybe not so surprising given the state of Twitter, but still:</p>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/AdamRackis/status/1762321041899012307">https://twitter.com/AdamRackis/status/1762321041899012307</a></p>
<p>On the face of it, “people get twisted in their relationship with work” seems like a reasonable take. Stop complaining—you are making 16x the median salary in this country. Just do the boring job with the toxic team.</p>
<p>Let’s stop and think about this for a second. The original poster (OP from now on) is making $800K annually due to the appreciation of Spotify stock. An obscene amount of money? Maybe, maybe not. I do not have the typical hang-ups about the wealthy or ultra-wealthy. I don’t see this world as a zero-sum game, and I think the richest people out there have usually done some amazing things, especially in countries like the US where most wealth is not old wealth.</p>
<p>But there is a difference between founding a company you’re passionate about, which goes on to become incredibly valuable, and working for someone else doing a job you think is boring in order to join the 1%. In this article, I’m talking about the latter.</p>
<p>I propose this core question for this type of person: Is this large income worth doing a job you find boring, or working with people you feel are toxic? I would say no. Absolutely not. OP is clearly regretting how he’s spending his time at work. He should look for something to do that he values, even if it pays a quarter as much as he gets now. Or less!</p>
<h2 id="the-hedonic-treadmill">The Hedonic Treadmill</h2>
<p>There’s an often misquoted study from ~2010 that personal income beyond about $75K (presumed to cover basic necessities with a comfortable overhead) does not equate to further happiness. This number is actually about right when it comes to simple reported happiness, which has more to do with the hedonic treadmill than anything else. But the study in question was also measuring reported “life satisfaction” as surveyed, which did not stop increasing with income. Of course, “life satisfaction” is a fraught survey metric as well, as it might actually measure a perceived comparative number with one’s neighbors (we’ll get to this later).</p>
<p>But whatever the proper measure of happiness or satisfaction is, there is a great deal of logic to thinking its relationship with income looks like this:</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="happiness income curve"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/treadmill-graph.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 720px; width: 100%"   >


    
</div>

<p>As in: there are diminishing returns to incremental income. Not a revolutionary idea. It’s obvious. But it also means that somewhere along this curve is the often-quoted $75K, and somewhere far to the right is OP’s $800K. And the curve between those points is probably pretty flat.</p>
<p>What could OP get in return for moving to the left along this flat section of the curve? Eight hours of time per workday, at least, that he finds incrementally more valuable. How much do you think those 8 hours could improve his life satisfaction on their own happiness/hours curve?</p>
<p>This is where the real paradox comes in. Gaining wealth is supposed to make your time more valuable. You choose to get more services, have a housekeeper, maybe even a private chef. But if those things actually indicate a person values their time more highly than someone poorer, how come they would even consider sacrificing most of that time doing something they find boring, or with people they find annoying? Just to maintain their position along the flat section of the curve?</p>
<p>Maybe they aren’t prioritizing happiness at all.</p>
<h2 id="keeping-up-with-the-joneses">Keeping up with the Joneses</h2>
<p>My argument so far would be absolute blasphemy to most of the $500K+ salary people who don’t have much fun at work. Let’s talk about their two most common counterarguments:</p>







<div class="paige-quote">
<blockquote class="blockquote"><ol>
<li><em>&ldquo;Work should be a sacrifice, and more money means more security for my family.&rdquo;</em></li>
</ol>
</blockquote>


</div>

<p>This is noble. It’s also way too self-sacrificial for the extremely wealthy first-world people we’re talking about. You’re making $800K. There is not a salary sacrifice in the world that will make your family “insecure.”</p>
<p>And what pattern does this even establish? You’re going to choose to be unhappy for most of your waking hours so that you can guarantee your children will be able to do the same? What are you actually working for if not you or anyone else being able to actually enjoy themselves?</p>







<div class="paige-quote">
<blockquote class="blockquote"><ol start="2">
<li><em>&ldquo;But I could make this crazy money and then retire in 5 years.&rdquo;</em></li>
</ol>
</blockquote>


</div>

<p>Now this is a good argument! You could indeed retire in 5 years after making $800K per year and then spend your time with family or pursue passion projects! The problems here are twofold:</p>
<p><strong>First</strong>, nobody does this. Instead, they spend more money. Of course, some of it will be saved, but the main thing that happens when people find themselves with far more money than needed for their family’s security is that they spend it. Bigger houses, more trips, elite schools for the kids. These make you feel well-off compared to your neighbors but don’t push you much higher on that flat curve.</p>
<p><strong>Second</strong>, people find value in being useful. There’s a reason why so many struggle in retirement. Even with a rigid FIRE plan, you’ll still want to work afterward on something interesting. So why not find that now?</p>
<p>What’s actually happening? Lifestyle creep. I think this is 90% of why people feel they could never work on something more fun or meaningful for less money. They’ve already started to spend their new money, and now losing those things would hurt more than gaining them felt good. That damn hedonic treadmill.</p>
<h2 id="where-we-go-from-here">Where we go from here</h2>
<p>What am I saying? I’m asking you to think deeply about what you value. Money isn’t a core value. Value your own time as much as your spending habits suggest you do. This is the right logic for your well-being, even if the world stays as it is. Now for my last thought:</p>
<p>I’m obsessed with AI and the technological singularity. It’s a healthy time to step back, reflect on the fundamental values driving our behavior, and make changes. Wouldn’t it be silly to spend most of our waking hours working miserably on meaningless things, only to arrive in a second half of life in a world of abundance?</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2024-02-01:/the-treadmill/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/the-treadmill/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>The Treadmill</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="this is a robot"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/ai-software-dev.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 720px; width: 100%"   >


    
</div>

<p>Lots of chatter right now about AI replacing software developers.</p>
<p>I agree - AI will take over software development. The question is: what work will be left when this happens?</p>
<p>Some considerations:</p>
<ul>
<li>Benchmarks for the best LLMs still put them solidly in the &ldquo;bad at programming&rdquo; category, scoring in the 5th percentile of human programmers on common tests. Meanwhile, LLMs score in the 80th-95th percentile for law exams and 85th–100th for psychology, statistics, and many other less technical fields. More scores available in the &ldquo;simulated exams&rdquo; section of <a href="https://openai.com/research/gpt-4">https://openai.com/research/gpt-4</a>.</li>
<li>Engineers have been using language models like tabnine and copilot as &ldquo;super-stackoverflow&rdquo; style code assistance years before chatGPT released. This means much of the velocity increase we might expect from current LLMs&rsquo; ability to write code has already been &ldquo;priced in&rdquo; to the market.</li>
<li>Many of the trends making software development more costly are growing, not shrinking: Systems are becoming more distributed. The cloud lowered infrastructure costs but made applications more complex. We&rsquo;re making more and deeper integrations among disparate systems. Auth is becoming more secure and thus complex (managed identity, MFA, etc).</li>
</ul>
<p>Github copilot chat and other LLM dev tools are speeding up the rote stuff. I’ve seen it in my own work.</p>
<p>And I really do believe new AI models will do more than just the basics, maybe in the next couple of years. Even precluding &ldquo;AGI&rdquo;, the trend we are on is that more and more work is automatable, and engineers, especially more junior ones - are going to have to shift focus away from algorithmic work that AI can do.</p>
<p>But by the time our neural nets are &ldquo;good enough&rdquo; at building software to make it significantly cheaper to build, I doubt this trend will make the news. Everything else gets automated too.</p>
<p>These are my thoughts at what seems to be the beginning of the next AI revolution in early 2024. I plan to revisit this topic and see if I&rsquo;m right in future posts.</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2024-01-24:/on-ai-software-development/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/on-ai-software-development/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2024 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>On AI Software Development</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>Editor&rsquo;s note from 2025:</p>
<p>This article was written as part of the launch of Treekeepers VR and the sole proprietorship Together Again Studios, and represents some of my core beliefs of the value of VR and where it&rsquo;s taking us socially. Though I&rsquo;m no longer actively working on Treekeepers, I do hold that VR and AR are truly the &ldquo;endgame&rdquo; of interface and one that could save us from some of the social attitudes caused by social media of today.</p>
<p>I hope you enjoy it!</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 id="with-together-again-studios-and-treekeepers-vr-were-setting-out-to-solve-an-insidious-problem-we-see-all-around-us">With Together Again Studios and Treekeepers VR, we&rsquo;re setting out to solve an insidious problem we see all around us:</h3>
<h4 id="social-media-is-anti-social">Social Media Is Anti-Social</h4>
<p>Though Facebook, Instagram, Twitter, and Tiktok all let us share more with each other than ever before, what we are sharing is surprisingly hostile and dismissive of opinions other than our own.</p>
<p>Though Zoom, Hangouts and Teams let us finally see each other from a distance, we still can&rsquo;t speak naturally. We depend on tools like &ldquo;mute&rdquo;. We create meeting upon meeting with different sets of the same group of people. And we don&rsquo;t form the depth of relationships we could in-person.</p>
<p>We as humans are all-too-capable of forming us-versus-them &ldquo;tribes&rdquo; and dehumanizing those who appear too different, and this problem is becoming ever more apparent behind the curtain of the graphical user interface.</p>
<h4 id="virtual-and-augmented-reality-are-a-way-out">Virtual and augmented reality are a way out</h4>
<p>In 2016, thanks to pioneers like Palmer Luckey, Michael Abrash, and John Carmack, we suddenly gained access to a technology that removes the curtain and forces us to see eachother. And in 2020, an event that has permanently limited our in-person interaction arose and gave new meaning to this technology.</p>
<p>In VR/AR, voices are no longer text on a screen, taken out of context by our social media bubbles. They&rsquo;re voices again.</p>
<p>In VR/AR, people are no longer user profiles with one image and a tag-line. They&rsquo;re really people, with bodies, faces, and hands that can point and gesture.</p>
<p>In VR/AR, messages are not just &ldquo;public&rdquo;, or &ldquo;direct&rdquo;. Conversations are dynamic, with people physically approaching one another to talk, with people moving in and out of physical groups, and with people attending public conversations together again while still able to have &ldquo;sidebar&rdquo; conversations.</p>
<p>All these abilities we used to have in-person, we have gained again in virtual reality.</p>
<p>Soon, we&rsquo;ll go even further with this technology. We&rsquo;ll be able to make real eye contact with eachother in VR. We&rsquo;ll use AR to invite distant friends and family over to our homes.</p>
<p>And at Together Again, we plan on using these new tools to let people like eachother again.</p>
<h3 id="treekeepers-only-possible-in-vr">Treekeepers: Only Possible in VR</h3>
<p>Why is Treekeepers a VR Game?</p>
<h4 id="multiplayer-of-this-depth-only-works-in-vr">Multiplayer of this depth only works in VR</h4>
<p>The challenges in Treekeepers VR hinge on player coordination and quick group decisions - Which weapon should we upgrade? Who&rsquo;s doing which job? Where are we going?</p>
<p>In VR, you gain the ability to gesture and point to enemies and obstacles naturally.</p>
<p>No more &ldquo;Who is the green player?&rdquo; - spend zero mental energy figuring out who you are talking to. Just turn towards them and speak.</p>
<h4 id="scale-is-the-most-fun-when-youre-in-the-world">Scale is the most fun when you&rsquo;re in the world</h4>
<p>We&rsquo;re going to be exploring oversized objects around a gigantic tree. Only VR can get the full benefit of this experience.</p>
<h4 id="vr-can-be-uncomfortable">VR can be uncomfortable</h4>
<p>BUT, experiencing it via a static vehicle which acts as a persistent frame of reference reduces motion sickness.</p>
<p>No need to rotate - gameplay is based on the hot air balloon always facing one direction, and players navigating within it.</p>
<hr>
<p>Check out Treekeepers VR <a href="/treekeepers-vr">here</a></p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2022-08-01:/social-media-is-antisocial/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/social-media-is-antisocial/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Social Media Is Anti-Social</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
