













    
        
    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    







    

    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"  xml:lang="en-us"  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            

            
                
            

            
                <link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/writing/" rel="self" type="text/html"/>
            
        
            

            

            
                <link href="http://localhost:1313/categories/writing/rss.xml" rel="alternate" type="application/rss+xml"/>
            
        

        

        

        <description>Recent content</description>

        
            <language>en-us</language>
        

        
            <lastBuildDate>2025-05-24 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</lastBuildDate>
        

        <link>http://localhost:1313/categories/writing/</link>

        

        <title>Writing · Categories · hockenworks</title>

        

        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Recently I read the <a href="https://ai-2027.com/scenario.pdf">AI 2027 paper</a>. I was surprised to see Scott Alexander&rsquo;s name on this paper and I was doubly surprised to see him do his <a href="https://www.dwarkesh.com/p/scott-daniel">first face reveal podcast about it with Dwarkesh</a></p>
<p>On its face this is one of the most aggressive predictions for when we will have AGI (at least the new definition of AGI which is something that is comparable or better than humans at all non-bodily tasks) that I have read. Even as someone who has been a long believer in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Singularity_Is_Near">Ray Kurzweil&rsquo;s Singularity predictions</a>, 2027 strikes me as very early. I realize that Kurzweil&rsquo;s AGI date was also late 2020&rsquo;s and 2045 was his singulartiy prediction - 2027 still feels early to me.</p>
<div class="paige-row-wide">
  <div style="display:grid; grid-template-columns:repeat(2, minmax(0,1fr)); gap:15px;">
      






























    













    



    






















<img  alt="AI 2027"   class="rounded-4 w-100"  crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/ai-2027.png"    >


      






























    













    



    






















<img  alt="Singularity Is Near"   class="rounded-4 w-100"  crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/The-Singularity-Is-Near.JPG"    >

</div>
</div>

<p>I won&rsquo;t get into my full take on AI 2027 here, but the core argument comes down to the same one I was making in my <a href="/on-ai-software-development">original post on AI software development</a></p>
<ul>
<li>which is that, once AI agents are able to replace software engineers, instead of just assisting them, it doesn&rsquo;t matter how they are doing another realms, because they will simply be able to improve on themselves and their own software at such a rate that the difference between the time of automating software engineering jobs and the time of automating all other jobs is negligible.</li>
</ul>
<p>So I figured it was a good time to update on where I think AI is actually at at software engineering tasks. I&rsquo;ve had the chance to test many of the latest AI software development tools and models, and we have come a long way since my original post.</p>
<p>&mdash;Notes&mdash;</p>
<p>Add links to my chat with 03 about the refund feature,</p>
<p>Add links to videos about co-pilot agents as well as codex as the state of the art actual software developers</p>
<p>Talk a little bit about my experience using cursor and what a disappointment it was for a code base as unique as mine</p>
<p>Add notes about cursor not handling context any more easily than context caddy - and that might be a bit of a stumbling block</p>
<p>First feature that sonnet 3.7 consistently failed at was simply having the compactors add ball value accumulation of compacted balls</p>
<p>Your request has been blocked as our system has detected suspicious activity from your account.If you believe this is a mistake, please contact us at <a href="mailto:hi@cursor.com">hi@cursor.com</a>.(Request ID: 997e94bb-34ee-44c0-b0aa-15bb6822add6)</p>
<p>LOL</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2025-05-24:/on-ai-software-development-2/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/on-ai-software-development-2/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2025 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>On AI Software Development, 2025 Edition</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>During my parental leave, I played through quite a few video games - something I love and one of the easiest ways to spend time while rocking my daughter to sleep.</p>
<p>They include:</p>
<ul>
<li>The Legend of Zelda: The Minish Cap <sup>Steam Deck</sup></li>
<li>Carto <sup>Steam on Windows</sup></li>
<li>Tunic <sup>Steam on Windows</sup></li>
<li>Abzu <sup>Steam on Windows</sup></li>
<li>SteamWorld: Build <sup>Steam on Windows</sup></li>
<li>World of Goo 2 <sup>Nintendo Switch</sup></li>
<li>Oblivion Remastered <sup>Steam on Windows</sup></li>
<li>Mario Kart World <sup>Nintendo Switch 2</sup></li>
<li>Donkey Kong Bananza <sup>Nintendo Switch 2</sup></li>
</ul>
<p>Most of these are indie titles, but the one I spent the most time on was the Oblivion Remaster - one which surprised me both with how good it looks and with how well it played. Oblivion is a 19 year old game, and a purely graphics-related overhaul should not have made it as good or better than modern AAA games releasing today, but in my opinion (and many others I’m reading) it absolutely did. How could this be?</p>
<h2 id="graphics">Graphics</h2>
<p>Well - I think that’s pretty clear. The only thing that has really improved about mainstream gaming in the last 20 years is graphics.</p>
<p>And boy have the graphics improved. Oblivion not only uses new techniques like ray-tracing and revamped 4K textures and normal maps etc, it uses the full suite of global illumination provided by <a href="https://dev.epicgames.com/documentation/en-us/unreal-engine/lumen-global-illumination-and-reflections-in-unreal-engine">Unreal Engine</a>, which mean when you turn the settings up, it depends on hardly any of the typical tricks games need to use, like baked light maps, instead lighting almost everything in the game dynamically or “procedurally”, including things like reflections of reflections and lit up dust and fog.</p>

<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
  <video controls loop muted autoplay style="max-width:100%;">
    <source src="/videos/bruma-clip.mp4" type="video/mp4">
    Your browser doesn’t support HTML5 video.
  </video>
  
    <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">This is from my playthrough, some outdoor torches in Bruma and mountain lighting in the background make for a pretty good use of full Lumen</span>
  
</div>

<p>Yes, Oblivion still has some simplistic design in terms of how landscapes are laid out, but that simplicity might also be why people can run it with Nvidia Lumen set up to run at ultra. Lighting is what’s really differentiating in video game graphics now, and fully simulated lighting beats or meets nearly every AAA game releasing lately that all cost tens or hundreds of millions of dollars to make..</p>
<h2 id="not-graphics">Not Graphics</h2>
<p>Left unstated is why nothing else has improved. Walking around Oblivion, meeting characters that have some scripted voice lines, responding to them with 1 of 4 options, holding down the left stick to sprint, and hitting a single button on your controller to watch your character animate a full scripted sword swing are all the standard gameplay of action-RPGs both 19 years ago and today. The same can be said of other genres - mechanics are largely untouched for the last 20 years outside of some common quality of life changes in how menus and inventory and HUDs work.</p>
<p>Here’s my theory for why: The games industry achieved the threshold of what was comfortable and possible with with the current human-computer input and output mechanisms only a few years after they were technically possible. And those inputs and outputs have not changed much since the 90s. Looking at a flat screen in front of you and pressing buttons on a controller or keyboard/mouse are incredibly limiting for gaming. Increasing the amount of pixels on the screen and making that controller wireless don&rsquo;t change the core gameplay. This is not really true for any other media than games. Reading, watching films, and all kinds of media in between essentially max out on one screen and limited input, but games immediately ran into forms of input and output as a barrier.</p>
<p>I wrote a little about this topic in <a href="/social-media-is-antisocial">my first post about VR and why I think it’s the future</a>. The only true innovation in gameplay that is happening in two places:</p>
<ul>
<li>Indie, where one-man teams can come up with strange mashups and mechanics can execute on a vision spending very little. These are almost never totally genre definiing, but they are inventive.</li>
<li>VR, where we have only scratched the surface of mechanics that work and what is possible when the player’s entire hands and 3D field of view are in the game.</li>
</ul>
<p>AAA game developers are excluded from the first by definition and is excluded from the second by their own financial decision makers.</p>
<h2 id="so-what-my-predictions">So What? My predictions</h2>
<p>Maybe people want to keep buying the same games with better graphics forever. I don’t think they do. I think those decision makers that aren’t investing in truly new AAA gameplay are short sighted. As long as we’ve been hearing that VR is the future and not seeing it totally come to fruition, at some point these companies that are milking the same game franchises for years will face the reality that people will only buy the same games reskinned with better graphics for so long. They’ll either be replaced by companies that innovate or individuals using AI that will be plenty good at recreating the same game over and over again.</p>
<p>I am hoping that the current hypestorm around AI re-kindles the ideas in the hearts of AAA game studio CFOs that they might need to invest in innovation and new ideas again. Some of the things that make Oblivion just like any RPG of today (Think about the 4 option scripted discourse and stuffy voice lines as two) would be meaningfully different if AI was applied in the right way. And I think they’d be far more powerful experiences, just like I think VR games can be - so much higher fidelity and responsive to player input.</p>
<p>Here are my predictions of things we’ll see in the next decade or so, regardless of the AAA studios pioneer them or not:</p>
<p>A decade or two from now, we will look at the period of 2005 to 2025 and see that it was a period of a great stagnation in game innovation. This will be driven by a few key technological advances and the downstream game mechanics that will flow from those, stemming mainly from the areas of AI and what is now called mixed reality.</p>
<p>I’m going to make a few specific predictions of mechanics we will see in the future that will make the magnation of the last 20 years totally transparent:</p>
<h4 id="ai">AI:</h4>
<ul>
<li>
<p>In open world games, it will become standard for non-player characters to have fully generated dialogues based on motivations and incentives rather than scripts</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>In open world games, players will speak directly or engage directly in some way with their own words that NPCs will understand and react to intelligently</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>NPCs won&rsquo;t have recorded voice lines, but instead have voices generated in real time, and AAA games will start to make contracts with celebrity talent in order to generate their voice in games</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>We will see a transition from the current minorly procedural elements of gameplay to full procedural generated worlds, especially where player actions and environmental events change landscape, buildings, etc dynamically</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Game art will go through an incredible revolution, and we will stop having massive teams of people creating 3D meshes and textures to drop around the world, with many of these meshes and textures being generated from prompts in development, but also being generated on the fly in games</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="mixed-reality">Mixed Reality:</h4>
<p>The first reasonable augmented reality glasses that consumers are willing to wear en masse will generate entirely new genres:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>A new genre of video board games, wear gameplay happens in view of a group of people in the same physical space, on a table, on the ground, in a park, etc, that will incorporate video game elements such as computations that are too complicated for typical board games, with the advantages that board games have today where players can interact with the same physical pieces, point and gesture, and socialize in person</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Another new genre of exercise programs combined with games. This will go far beyond current treadmills that have built-in virtual run routes or virtual exercise classes, this will be exercise incorporated as a leveling or other mechanic that will incentivize players to get some exercise. I&rsquo;ve had a lot of hope for this category for a long time, and the one major threat to it is GLP1 drugs that may cause a serious decline in the need and desire for people to exercise daily for calorie loss</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>When will these happen? My specific prediction is that the next 3 years will be seen as the end of the period of stagnation we are in right now, a period that will be much more apparent looking backwards than it is from within. The combo of a decline in AAA game spending and AI hype feel like ripe conditions for innovation to return to gameplay - and my hope is that all of the other potential gameplay innovations ride the same AI wave.</p>]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2025-05-12:/the-purgatory-of-aaa-gaming/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/the-purgatory-of-aaa-gaming/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>The Purgatory of AAA Gaming</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I have long been of the mind LLMs and their evolutions are truly thinking, and that they are on their way to solving all of the intellectual tasks that humans can solve today. It is just too uncanny that the technology that seems to have made the final jump to actually thinking, after a long string of attempts and architectures, is a type of neural net. It would be much easier to argue away transformer models as non-thinking stochastic parrots if we had happened to have had success with any other architecture than the one that was designed to mimic our own brains and the neurons firing off to one another within them. It&rsquo;s just too weird. They are shaped like us, they sound like us in a lot of ways, and it&rsquo;s obvious they are thinking something like us too.</p>
<h2 id="the-limitations">The Limitations</h2>
<p>That&rsquo;s not to say they are AGI in the modern definition. They can&rsquo;t do every task humans can do intellectually (IE without a body, which I will get to) for several reasons:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p>Looping reasoning.
This was a huge problem for early transformers that had to output in one shot, and the examples were obvious. This one has been essentially solved via thinking models like o1. That was a huge unlock and a huge bone for things like programming where there is lots of nested recursion of logic that has to occur to get a reasonable answer.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Memory and context.
Context windows get larger all the time but this one still is not solved. Just adding a bunch of tokens into a context window doesn&rsquo;t get you much when 2 million token models lose coherence after about the first 40,000 - which they do, and which every programmer working with anything but a tiny codebase intuitively understands. But this one too will largely be solved soon, if not through architectures that actually update their weights, it&rsquo;ll be solved through nuanced memory systems that people are actively developing on top of thinking models.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Vision</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>And this one might sound funny to someone that is paying attention to AI in particular, because GPT-4 with vision launched something like 2 years ago now. And it has been impressive for a long time, able to do things like identify what objects are in an image, where an image is from, even things that payments can&rsquo;t do glancing at an image.</p>
<p>But the vision itself is not “good” vision. It cannot really pick out small important details, and it still behaves in many ways like vision recognition models have for years now. Now that we have a model that has both thinking and image input and editing at every step, the 03 and 04 mini series just released, we can really start to see the limitations in vision. Let me take you through 2 examples that represent the 2 types of failure modes that result from these not having true image understanding, yet.</p>
<p>Each release from the major providers steadily knocks away my intelligence tests, which I admit are mostly programming oriented, but the ones that they can never really dent are the spatial reasoning ones where a model really has to think about images in its head or have to use an image provided for detailed work.</p>
<h3 id="simple-3d-modeling">Simple 3D Modeling</h3>
<p>Every major model release, <a href="/3d-modeling-with-ai">I test what models can do with OpenSCAD</a>. I won’t get technical about it here, but OpenSCAD is a CAD program (Computer Aided Design - think 3D modeling for engineers, not the artistic kind) that is defined entirely through a programming language vs the typical mousestrokes and key presses that software like Solidworks or AutoCAD depend on.</p>
<p>This makes OpenSCAD the perfect test platform for a model that inputs and output text primarily. I can describe a 3D model I want, and the model can output text that renders into a 3D model.</p>
<p>But for as amazing as LLMs are at scripting in normal programming languages, they have never been good at OpenScad (link to GPT4 chair article)</p>
<p>Here is O3’s attempt to make a</p>
<h3 id="map-reading">Map Reading</h3>
<p>I recently gave this question to the latest thinking image model, &lsquo;03: &ldquo;Here&rsquo;s an image from Google maps of the block I live on between the avenues of Burbank, hazeltine, Oxnard, and Van nuys. What is the longest continuous loop I can walk within the neighborhood without crossing my path or touching one of the avenues? This square is 1/2 mi on each side&rdquo;</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="the uploaded map"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/o3-struggle-map.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 400px; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">The image uploaded with this query</span>
    
</div>

<p>O3 thinks for 4 minutes about this question, zooming in to various parts of the map countless times to form the route. And then it fails on the first step, suggesting starting at tiara and stansbury, which do not intersect on the map. Any person looking at this image could tell that is true in just a few seconds.</p>
<p>What I think is going on in these examples is that we have a limitation in training data (duh) but it isn&rsquo;t because there aren&rsquo;t a lot of images and videos on the internet, it&rsquo;s because there is so much more information in the average image then there is in the average chunk of text, and a lot more of that information is irrelevant to any given question.</p>
<p>When I say that we have a limitation on training data, I&rsquo;m not in the typical camp of &ldquo;well, then transformer neural nets are obviously stupid because I was able to understand this thing without training on terabytes of data from the internet&rdquo;. This is always been a bad take because the average human trains on petabytes, not terabytes of data, and that data is streamed into their brains mostly in the form of images. I am also not in the camp of thinking that this means that the data &ldquo;just doesn&rsquo;t exist&rdquo; to get these models to AGI in this dimension. It&rsquo;s so clearly does exist, and it exists so abundantly that a unique mage stream can be sent to each of the billions of human brains, and they all learn the same principles that let them immediately identify the mistake that the cutting edge thinking vision model made after 4 minutes of rigor.</p>
<p>The data exists, and we never actually had a data problem in AI. We have an instruction problem. That doesn&rsquo;t mean model architecture or data massaging really, it means that we need to plug our models into the real world where all the data streams exist. I&rsquo;m guessing that this comes in the form of robots with cameras on them, the first of which is happening on mass via Tesla full self-driving, and I&rsquo;m sure those vision neural nets are quite insane compared to what we see in the consumer transform r models, but the real leap probably comes when we get to humanoids walking around collecting and learning from vision data everyday.</p>
<p>The Robots</p>
<p>If you’ve ever tried to get concrete actions to take based on a vision-transformer’s outputs, you will know it’s hard.</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2025-02-01:/vision-is-the-last-hurdle-before-agi/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/vision-is-the-last-hurdle-before-agi/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2025 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Vision is the last hurdle before AGI</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="Brian and Alice"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/brian-and-alice-gaming-zoom.jpg"   style="height: auto; max-width: 400px; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">↑ me and Alice</span>
    
</div>

<p>I&rsquo;m Brian Hockenmaier, dad, engineer, and fun haver.</p>
<p>I grew up in Ventura, California with two UCLA-engineer parents. Even though neither of them were engineers long-term, I was an engineering child. I was always building something, highlights including a functional submarine and weather balloon with Lego robotics.</p>
<p>I went to school for industrial engineering at <a href="https://www.calpoly.edu/">Cal Poly SLO</a>, nearly double majored in economics, and then promptly moved out of both fields just like my parents had moved out of their education fields of mechanical and aerospace. Since then, after reading Ray Kurzweil&rsquo;s <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Singularity_Is_Near">The Singularity is Near</a> in 2011, feeling I needed to be closer to software and realizing I liked building systems more than anything in industrial engineering, I&rsquo;ve built a career in software and then AI.</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="A lego crane"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/lego-crane.jpg"   style="height: auto; max-width: 400px; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">One of the few pictures I have from my time building robots with legos, showing a robotic crane to my Dad</span>
    
</div>

<p>At work, I try to be low time preference, high autonomy, low consensus (even contrarian), high invention, process-light.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been at one company for a long time for a millennial. I&rsquo;ve built a lot of enterprise software and four high performing software teams. I started on back-office stuff like billing systems, TV scheduling systems, IP rights management systems, and file ingest systems for News. Most recently I’m making some pretty awesome stuff in agentic AI for the mundane work that the people at my company have to do!</p>
<p>My bias is to build rather than talk. I&rsquo;m the one pushing to just try to build the thing, to scrap it early if needed, and to take risks releasing early. I figure that we always know more, and usually throw away our plans, when we start to build. I love building strange things, useful thingss, fun things. One of the things I built was this website and the game running on top of it. <a href="/this-website">Read more about that here</a></p>
<p>Other Profiles:</p>
<p>Most of my development projects are stored on public or private repos on <a href="https://github.com/hockenmaier">my github</a></p>
<p>A collection of physical projects and 3D designs can be found on <a href="https://www.thingiverse.com/hockenmaier/designs">my thingiverse</a></p>
<p>And my professional persona can be found on <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/hockenmaier/">my linkedin</a></p>
<hr>
<h1 id="where-to-start">Where to start</h1>
<p>I post here mostly about things I&rsquo;m making and occasional essays. If you’re interested in this site but don’t know where to start, try reading any of these posts that sound interesting to you. They&rsquo;re either peices or projects I put a lot of time into.</p>
<h2 id="my-games">My Games</h2>







  









  
  
  






<article class="latest-item mb-4" style="display:flex; align-items:flex-start;">
  <div class="media-column">
    <div class="media-container" style="width:300px; height:300px;">

      
        
        <a href="/land-war/">
          <img src="https://img.youtube.com/vi/5Q8PAuWcmQc/hqdefault.jpg" alt="Land War">
        </a>

      

    </div>
  </div>

  <div class="text-column" style="align-self:flex-start; margin-top:0;">
    <h2 class="post-title" style="margin-top:0 !important; margin-bottom:0 !important;">
      <a class="link-light" href="/land-war/">Land War</a>
    </h2>
    <div class="post-summary" style="margin-top:0; margin-bottom:.5rem;">
      <p>Land War is an 8-player strategy game I developed as a solo project and released to Steam in March of 2019.<br>
This game was intended to have low art requirements and simple interaction rules that result in deep strategic gameplay.</p>
<p>The core concept is that of an ultra-simplified real-time-strategy game. Each player is represented by a color and can grow their territory by moving in any direction. The strategic elements occur when players encounter other players and have to make choices about which side of their land to defend or give up. Players can use the structure of the map and the coordinated action of other players to gain defensible footholds in order to take more area and eventually be the last player on the board.</p>
    </div>
    <p class="read-more text-secondary fst-italic" style="margin:0;">
      March 1, 2019 · 3 minutes ·
      <a href="/land-war/">Read more →</a>
    </p>
  </div>
</article>


<blockquote>
<p>Land War was my first published game. I built in in 6 months and released on Steam only, where it got a few hundred downloads and made a bit over $1000</p>
</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<hr>
<p> </p>
<blockquote>
<p>Treekeepers VR was an ambitious game developement project I took on in 2021- my first published VR title and my first multiplayer title. The latter turned out to be the really hard part. Read more about it:</p>
</blockquote>
<p> </p>







  









  
  
  






<article class="latest-item mb-4" style="display:flex; align-items:flex-start;">
  <div class="media-column">
    <div class="media-container" style="width:300px; height:300px;">

      
        <a href="/treekeepers-vr/">
          <img src="http://localhost:1313/images/treekeepers_moonlight.png" alt="Treekeepers VR">
        </a>

      

    </div>
  </div>

  <div class="text-column" style="align-self:flex-start; margin-top:0;">
    <h2 class="post-title" style="margin-top:0 !important; margin-bottom:0 !important;">
      <a class="link-light" href="/treekeepers-vr/">Treekeepers VR</a>
    </h2>
    <div class="post-summary" style="margin-top:0; margin-bottom:.5rem;">
      <div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    







    



    

























    
        
    
</div>

<p>Treekeepers VR is a networked VR game where up to 4 players can cooperate to navigate an oversized world and save a giant tree.</p>
<p>Treekeepers is in production on both Quest (standalone VR) and Steam (PC VR) with full cross-play functionality. See the <a href="https://togetheragainstudios.com/treekeepersvr/">Treekeepers VR Website</a> for links to all storefronts and more detail about the game.</p>
<h2 id="heading"></h2>
    </div>
    <p class="read-more text-secondary fst-italic" style="margin:0;">
      October 1, 2022 · 2 minutes ·
      <a href="/treekeepers-vr/">Read more →</a>
    </p>
  </div>
</article>


<p> </p>
<hr>
<p> </p>
<blockquote>
<p>This Website itself was my 3rd video game:</p>
</blockquote>







  









  
  
  






<article class="latest-item mb-4" style="display:flex; align-items:flex-start;">
  <div class="media-column">
    <div class="media-container" style="width:300px; height:300px;">

      
        <a href="/this-website/">
          <img src="http://localhost:1313/images/hockenworks.png" alt="This Website">
        </a>

      

    </div>
  </div>

  <div class="text-column" style="align-self:flex-start; margin-top:0;">
    <h2 class="post-title" style="margin-top:0 !important; margin-bottom:0 !important;">
      <a class="link-light" href="/this-website/">This Website</a>
    </h2>
    <div class="post-summary" style="margin-top:0; margin-bottom:.5rem;">
      <p>I&rsquo;m <a href="/about-me">Brian Hockenmaier</a>, and this site is full of things I build and write about. I love making games and things with VR and AI. I love DIY projects, epecially ones involving programming, engineering and 3D modeling. Some of this has been cross or back-posted from my <a href="https://www.thingiverse.com/hockenmaier/designs">thingiverse</a>, <a href="https://x.com/Hockenmaier">twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/hockenmaier/">linkedin</a>, and other places, but it all lives here permanently.</p>
<p>All work and opinion here is fully my own and not my employer&rsquo;s.</p>
<p>This is an evolution of <a href="old-site/index.html">my previous site last updated in 2022, which I still keep inside this one</a> for posterity and for the AIs of the future to know more about me. I like it not because of the content as much as because it was a fully custom js and html site with no framework.. and I think it&rsquo;s sort of fun and funny that it was like this.</p>
    </div>
    <p class="read-more text-secondary fst-italic" style="margin:0;">
      March 1, 2025 · 10 minutes ·
      <a href="/this-website/">Read more →</a>
    </p>
  </div>
</article>


<p> </p>
<hr>
<p> </p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2024-04-30:/about-me/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/about-me/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Hi, I’m Brian</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I came across this tweet today that was surprisingly contentious. Maybe not so surprising given the state of Twitter, but still:</p>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/AdamRackis/status/1762321041899012307">https://twitter.com/AdamRackis/status/1762321041899012307</a></p>
<p>On the face of it, “people get twisted in their relationship with work” seems like a reasonable take. Stop complaining—you are making 16x the median salary in this country. Just do the boring job with the toxic team.</p>
<p>Let’s stop and think about this for a second. The original poster (OP from now on) is making $800K annually due to the appreciation of Spotify stock. An obscene amount of money? Maybe, maybe not. I do not have the typical hang-ups about the wealthy or ultra-wealthy. I don’t see this world as a zero-sum game, and I think the richest people out there have usually done some amazing things, especially in countries like the US where most wealth is not old wealth.</p>
<p>But there is a difference between founding a company you’re passionate about, which goes on to become incredibly valuable, and working for someone else doing a job you think is boring in order to join the 1%. In this article, I’m talking about the latter.</p>
<p>I propose this core question for this type of person: Is this large income worth doing a job you find boring, or working with people you feel are toxic? I would say no. Absolutely not. OP is clearly regretting how he’s spending his time at work. He should look for something to do that he values, even if it pays a quarter as much as he gets now. Or less!</p>
<h2 id="the-hedonic-treadmill">The Hedonic Treadmill</h2>
<p>There’s an often misquoted study from ~2010 that personal income beyond about $75K (presumed to cover basic necessities with a comfortable overhead) does not equate to further happiness. This number is actually about right when it comes to simple reported happiness, which has more to do with the hedonic treadmill than anything else. But the study in question was also measuring reported “life satisfaction” as surveyed, which did not stop increasing with income. Of course, “life satisfaction” is a fraught survey metric as well, as it might actually measure a perceived comparative number with one’s neighbors (we’ll get to this later).</p>
<p>But whatever the proper measure of happiness or satisfaction is, there is a great deal of logic to thinking its relationship with income looks like this:</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="happiness income curve"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/treadmill-graph.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 720px; width: 100%"   >


    
</div>

<p>As in: there are diminishing returns to incremental income. Not a revolutionary idea. It’s obvious. But it also means that somewhere along this curve is the often-quoted $75K, and somewhere far to the right is OP’s $800K. And the curve between those points is probably pretty flat.</p>
<p>What could OP get in return for moving to the left along this flat section of the curve? Eight hours of time per workday, at least, that he finds incrementally more valuable. How much do you think those 8 hours could improve his life satisfaction on their own happiness/hours curve?</p>
<p>This is where the real paradox comes in. Gaining wealth is supposed to make your time more valuable. You choose to get more services, have a housekeeper, maybe even a private chef. But if those things actually indicate a person values their time more highly than someone poorer, how come they would even consider sacrificing most of that time doing something they find boring, or with people they find annoying? Just to maintain their position along the flat section of the curve?</p>
<p>Maybe they aren’t prioritizing happiness at all.</p>
<h2 id="keeping-up-with-the-joneses">Keeping up with the Joneses</h2>
<p>My argument so far would be absolute blasphemy to most of the $500K+ salary people who don’t have much fun at work. Let’s talk about their two most common counterarguments:</p>







<div class="paige-quote">
<blockquote class="blockquote"><ol>
<li><em>&ldquo;Work should be a sacrifice, and more money means more security for my family.&rdquo;</em></li>
</ol>
</blockquote>


</div>

<p>This is noble. It’s also way too self-sacrificial for the extremely wealthy first-world people we’re talking about. You’re making $800K. There is not a salary sacrifice in the world that will make your family “insecure.”</p>
<p>And what pattern does this even establish? You’re going to choose to be unhappy for most of your waking hours so that you can guarantee your children will be able to do the same? What are you actually working for if not you or anyone else being able to actually enjoy themselves?</p>







<div class="paige-quote">
<blockquote class="blockquote"><ol start="2">
<li><em>&ldquo;But I could make this crazy money and then retire in 5 years.&rdquo;</em></li>
</ol>
</blockquote>


</div>

<p>Now this is a good argument! You could indeed retire in 5 years after making $800K per year and then spend your time with family or pursue passion projects! The problems here are twofold:</p>
<p><strong>First</strong>, nobody does this. Instead, they spend more money. Of course, some of it will be saved, but the main thing that happens when people find themselves with far more money than needed for their family’s security is that they spend it. Bigger houses, more trips, elite schools for the kids. These make you feel well-off compared to your neighbors but don’t push you much higher on that flat curve.</p>
<p><strong>Second</strong>, people find value in being useful. There’s a reason why so many struggle in retirement. Even with a rigid FIRE plan, you’ll still want to work afterward on something interesting. So why not find that now?</p>
<p>What’s actually happening? Lifestyle creep. I think this is 90% of why people feel they could never work on something more fun or meaningful for less money. They’ve already started to spend their new money, and now losing those things would hurt more than gaining them felt good. That damn hedonic treadmill.</p>
<h2 id="what-am-i-saying">What am I saying?</h2>
<p>I’m asking you to think deeply about what you value. Money isn’t a core value. Value your own time as much as your spending habits suggest you do. This is the right logic for your well-being, even if the world stays as it is. Now for my last thought:</p>
<p>I’m obsessed with AI and the technological singularity. It’s a healthy time to step back, reflect on the fundamental values driving our behavior, and make changes. Wouldn’t it be silly to spend most of our waking hours working miserably on meaningless things, only to arrive in a second half of life in a world of abundance?</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2024-02-01:/the-treadmill/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/the-treadmill/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>The Treadmill</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="this is a robot"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/ai-software-dev.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 720px; width: 100%"   >


    
</div>

<p>Lots of chatter right now about AI replacing software developers.</p>
<p>I agree - AI will take over software development. The question is: what work will be left when this happens?</p>
<p>Some considerations:</p>
<ul>
<li>Benchmarks for the best LLMs still put them solidly in the &ldquo;bad at programming&rdquo; category, scoring in the 5th percentile of human programmers on common tests. Meanwhile, LLMs score in the 80th-95th percentile for law exams and 85th–100th for psychology, statistics, and many other less technical fields. More scores available in the &ldquo;simulated exams&rdquo; section of <a href="https://openai.com/research/gpt-4">https://openai.com/research/gpt-4</a>.</li>
<li>Engineers have been using language models like tabnine and copilot as &ldquo;super-stackoverflow&rdquo; style code assistance years before chatGPT released. This means much of the velocity increase we might expect from current LLMs&rsquo; ability to write code has already been &ldquo;priced in&rdquo; to the market.</li>
<li>Many of the trends making software development more costly are growing, not shrinking: Systems are becoming more distributed. The cloud lowered infrastructure costs but made applications more complex. We&rsquo;re making more and deeper integrations among disparate systems. Auth is becoming more secure and thus complex (managed identity, MFA, etc).</li>
</ul>
<p>Github copilot chat and other LLM dev tools are speeding up the rote stuff. I’ve seen it in my own work.</p>
<p>And I really do believe new AI models will do more than just the basics, maybe in the next couple of years. Even precluding &ldquo;AGI&rdquo;, the trend we are on is that more and more work is automatable, and engineers, especially more junior ones - are going to have to shift focus away from algorithmic work that AI can do.</p>
<p>But by the time our neural nets are &ldquo;good enough&rdquo; at building software to make it significantly cheaper to build, I doubt this trend will make the news. Everything else gets automated too.</p>
<p>These are my thoughts at what seems to be the beginning of the next AI revolution in early 2024. I plan to revisit this topic and see if I&rsquo;m right in future posts.</p>]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2024-01-24:/on-ai-software-development/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/on-ai-software-development/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2024 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>On AI Software Development</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I have been occasionally challenging GPT to create models using <a href="https://openscad.org/">OpenSCAD</a>, a &ldquo;programming language for 3D models&rdquo;</p>
<p>Both struggle, but GPT-4 has been a massive improvement. Here are both model&rsquo;s outputs after asking for an acorn and 3 messages of me giving feedback:</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="some weird acorns"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/gpt-acorn.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 720px; width: 100%"   >


    
</div>

<p>For the record, it is impressive that these LLMs can get anything right with no visual input or training on shapes like these. Imagine looking at the programming reference for openSCAD and trying to do this blind. The fact that the 3.5 version has a bunch of strangely intersecting primitives and some union issues has been normal in my experience. It takes quite a bit of spacial logic to get a model not to look like that.</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2023-03-19:/3d-modeling-with-ai/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/3d-modeling-with-ai/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Sun, 19 Mar 2023 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>3D Modeling With AI</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>Editor&rsquo;s note from 2025:</p>
<p>This article was written as part of the launch of <a href="/treekeepers-vr">Treekeepers VR</a> and the sole proprietorship Together Again Studios, and represents some of my core beliefs of the value of VR and where it&rsquo;s taking us socially. Though I&rsquo;m no longer actively working on Treekeepers, I do hold that VR and AR are truly the &ldquo;endgame&rdquo; of interface and one that could save us from some of the social attitudes caused by social media of today. Enjoy!</p>
</blockquote>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="proofreader GPT"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/together-again-studios.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 400px; width: 100%"   >


    
</div>

<p>With Together Again Studios and Treekeepers VR, we&rsquo;re setting out to solve an insidious problem we see all around us:</p>
<p><strong>Social Media Is Anti-Social</strong></p>
<p>Though Facebook, Instagram, Twitter, and Tiktok all let us share more with each other than ever before, what we are sharing is surprisingly hostile and dismissive of opinions other than our own.</p>
<p>Though Zoom, Hangouts and Teams let us finally see each other from a distance, we still can&rsquo;t speak naturally. We depend on tools like &ldquo;mute&rdquo;. We create meeting upon meeting with different sets of the same group of people. And we don&rsquo;t form the depth of relationships we could in-person.</p>
<p>We as humans are all-too-capable of forming us-versus-them &ldquo;tribes&rdquo; and dehumanizing those who appear too different, and this problem is becoming ever more apparent behind the curtain of the graphical user interface.</p>
<p><strong>Virtual and augmented reality are a way out</strong></p>
<p>In 2016, thanks to pioneers like Palmer Luckey, Michael Abrash, and John Carmack, we suddenly gained access to a technology that removes the curtain and forces us to see eachother. And in 2020, an event that has permanently limited our in-person interaction arose and gave new meaning to this technology.</p>
<p>In VR/AR, voices are no longer text on a screen, taken out of context by our social media bubbles. They&rsquo;re voices again.</p>
<p>In VR/AR, people are no longer user profiles with one image and a tag-line. They&rsquo;re really people, with bodies, faces, and hands that can point and gesture.</p>
<p>In VR/AR, messages are not just &ldquo;public&rdquo;, or &ldquo;direct&rdquo;. Conversations are dynamic, with people physically approaching one another to talk, with people moving in and out of physical groups, and with people attending public conversations together again while still able to have &ldquo;sidebar&rdquo; conversations.</p>
<p>All these abilities we used to have in-person, we have gained again in virtual reality.</p>
<p>Soon, we&rsquo;ll go even further with this technology. We&rsquo;ll be able to make real eye contact with eachother in VR. We&rsquo;ll use AR to invite distant friends and family over to our homes.</p>
<p>And at Together Again, we plan on using these new tools to let people like eachother again.</p>
<p><strong>Treekeepers: Only Possible in VR</strong></p>
<p>Why is Treekeepers a VR Game?</p>
<p><strong>Multiplayer of this depth only works in VR</strong></p>
<p>The challenges in Treekeepers VR hinge on player coordination and quick group decisions - Which weapon should we upgrade? Who&rsquo;s doing which job? Where are we going?</p>
<p>In VR, you gain the ability to gesture and point to enemies and obstacles naturally.</p>
<p>No more &ldquo;Who is the green player?&rdquo; - spend zero mental energy figuring out who you are talking to. Just turn towards them and speak.</p>
<p><strong>Scale is the most fun when you&rsquo;re in the world</strong></p>
<p>We&rsquo;re going to be exploring oversized objects around a gigantic tree. Only VR can get the full benefit of this experience.</p>
<p><strong>VR can be uncomfortable</strong></p>
<p>BUT, experiencing it via a static vehicle which acts as a persistent frame of reference reduces motion sickness.</p>
<p>No need to rotate - gameplay is based on the hot air balloon always facing one direction, and players navigating within it.</p>
<hr>
<p>Check out Treekeepers VR <a href="/treekeepers-vr">here</a></p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2022-08-01:/social-media-is-antisocial/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/social-media-is-antisocial/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Social Media Is Anti-Social</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
