













    
        
    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    







    

    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"  xml:lang="en-us"  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            

            
                
            

            
                <link href="https://bhock.net/tags/crossplay/" rel="self" type="text/html"/>
            
        
            

            

            
                <link href="https://bhock.net/tags/crossplay/rss.xml" rel="alternate" type="application/rss+xml"/>
            
        

        

        

        <description>Recent content</description>

        
            <language>en-us</language>
        

        
            <lastBuildDate>2023-01-01 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</lastBuildDate>
        

        <link>https://bhock.net/tags/crossplay/</link>

        

        <title>Crossplay · Tags · Home</title>

        

        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>The Flapper</p>
<p>The Flapper is a project that spawned out of a simple movement mechanic test that turned out to be surprisingly fun!  The idea is to flap your arms to fly - and have it be a multiplayer battle to really get people moving.</p>
<p>Most of the start of this game was just tuning the movement mechanic, which borrowed from some physics realities and some elements I made up to make flapping feel good.</p>
<p>Here&rsquo;s a video of one of the later states of the game, where I have it fully networked and am testing with friends, though it still has a few bugs here:</p>

    <div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
      <iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" loading="eager" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Vxn8rDOZ7dU?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video"></iframe>
    </div>

]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:bhock.net,2023-01-01:/the-flapper/</guid>

                
                    <link>https://bhock.net/the-flapper/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>The Flapper</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    







    



    






















<img  alt="The Treekeepers Puddle Jumper"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://bhock.net/images/treekeepers_moonlight.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">The Treekeepers Puddle Jumper</span>
    
</div>

<p>Treekeepers VR is a networked VR game where up to 4 players can cooperate to navigate an oversized world and save a giant tree.</p>
<p>Treekeepers is in production on both Quest (standalone VR) and Steam (PC VR) with full cross-play functionality. See the <a href="https://togetheragainstudios.com/treekeepersvr/">Treekeepers VR Website</a> for links to all storefronts and more detail about the game.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="development">Development</h2>
<p>I began working on Treekeepers in June 2021, and my primary goal was to go significantly deeper into Unity and make a fully networked game. Very few co-op games existed in VR at the time (the area is still lacking), and my intention was to answer this need and create a game that 4 players could cooperate in within a static frame of reference (players move within a ship, and the ship moves through the world) while having to solve coordination challenges together.</p>
<p>I initially designed the project for SteamVR only using the SteamVR SDK but quickly realized that a VR game released only on PC would miss the majority of the userbase, as the (then Oculus) Quest 2 was quickly dominating the market. Treekeepers was a good fit for a mobile platform with its simple low-poly cel-shaded design, so I pivoted to using OpenXR about two months into the project to support VR interactions on both PC and mobile (Android) devices like the Quest 2.</p>
<p>By summer 2022, I had a releasable product, albeit only with one “world” available. I decided to push the game to early access to gather rapid feedback from real players, and after getting approved for both storefronts, Treekeepers released to early access on September 30, 2022.</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:bhock.net,2022-10-01:/treekeepers-vr/</guid>

                
                    <link>https://bhock.net/treekeepers-vr/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Treekeepers VR</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
