













    
        
    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    







    

    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"  xml:lang="en-us"  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            

            
                
            

            
                <link href="https://hockenworks.com/categories/writing/" rel="self" type="text/html"/>
            
        
            

            

            
                <link href="https://hockenworks.com/categories/writing/rss.xml" rel="alternate" type="application/rss+xml"/>
            
        

        

        

        <description>Recent content</description>

        
            <language>en-us</language>
        

        
            <lastBuildDate>2024-04-30 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</lastBuildDate>
        

        <link>https://hockenworks.com/categories/writing/</link>

        

        <title>Writing · Categories · hockenworks</title>

        

        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="Brian and Alice"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/brian-and-alice-gaming-zoom.jpg"   style="height: auto; max-width: 400px; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">↑ me and Alice</span>
    
</div>

<p>I&rsquo;m Brian Hockenmaier, dad, engineer, and fun haver.</p>
<p>I grew up in Ventura, California with two UCLA-engineer parents. Even though neither of them were engineers long-term, I was an engineering child. I was always building something, highlights including a functional submarine and weather balloon with Lego robotics.</p>
<p>I went to school for industrial engineering at <a href="https://www.calpoly.edu/">Cal Poly SLO</a>, nearly double majored in economics, and then promptly moved out of both fields just like my parents had moved out of their education fields of mechanical and aerospace. Since then, after reading Ray Kurzweil&rsquo;s <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Singularity_Is_Near">The Singularity is Near</a> in 2011, feeling I needed to be closer to software and realizing I liked building systems more than anything in industrial engineering, I&rsquo;ve built a career in software and then AI.</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="A lego crane"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/lego-crane.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 400px; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">One of the few pictures I have from my time building robots with legos, showing a robotic crane to my Dad</span>
    
</div>

<p>At work, I try to be low time preference, high autonomy, low consensus (even contrarian), high invention, process-light.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been at one company for a long time for a millennial. I&rsquo;ve built a lot of enterprise software and four high-performing software teams. I started on back-office stuff like billing systems, TV scheduling systems, IP rights management systems, and file ingest systems for News. Most recently I’m making some pretty awesome stuff in agentic AI for the mundane work that the people at my company have to do!</p>
<p>My bias is to build rather than talk. I&rsquo;m the one pushing to just try to build the thing, to scrap it early if needed, and to take risks releasing early. I figure that we always know more, and usually throw away our plans, when we start to build. I love building strange things, useful things, fun things. One of the things I built was this website and the game running on top of it. <a href="/this-website">Read more about that here</a></p>
<p>Other Profiles:</p>
<p>Most of my development projects are stored on public or private repos on <a href="https://github.com/hockenmaier">my github</a></p>
<p>A collection of physical projects and 3D designs can be found on <a href="https://www.thingiverse.com/hockenmaier/designs">my thingiverse</a></p>
<p>And my professional persona can be found on <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/hockenmaier/">my linkedin</a></p>
<hr>
<h1 id="where-to-start">Where to start</h1>
<p>I post here mostly about things I&rsquo;m making and occasional essays. If you’re interested in this site but don’t know where to start, try reading any of these posts that sound interesting to you. They&rsquo;re either pieces or projects I put a lot of time into.</p>
<h2 id="video-games">Video Games</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been developing video games on and off since 2017 or so. This has entailed more than 6 project starts and 3 finishes - those are below.</p>
<p> </p>







  








  
  

  

  
  
    
    
  








<article class="latest-item mb-4" style="display:flex; align-items:flex-start;">
  <div class="media-column">
    <div class="media-container" style="width:300px; height:300px;">

      
        <a href="/land-war/">
          <img src="images/land_war_e3.png" alt="Land War">
        </a>

      

    </div>
  </div>

  <div class="text-column" style="align-self:flex-start; margin-top:0;">
    <h2 class="post-title" style="margin-top:0 !important; margin-bottom:0 !important;">
      <a class="link-light" href="/land-war/">Land War</a>
    </h2>
    <div class="post-summary" style="margin-top:0; margin-bottom:.5rem;">
      <p>Land War is an 8-player strategy game I developed as a solo project and released to Steam in March of 2019.<br>
This game was intended to have low art requirements and simple interaction rules that result in deep strategic gameplay.</p>
<p>The core concept is that of an ultra-simplified real-time-strategy game. Each player is represented by a color and can grow their territory by moving in any direction. The strategic elements occur when players encounter other players and have to make choices about which side of their land to defend or give up. Players can use the structure of the map and the coordinated action of other players to gain defensible footholds in order to take more area and eventually be the last player on the board.</p>
    </div>
    <p class="read-more text-secondary fst-italic" style="margin:0;">
      March 1, 2019 · 3 minutes ·
      <a href="/land-war/">Read more →</a>
    </p>
  </div>
</article>


<blockquote>
<p>Land War was my first published video game, released using Unity after many unfinished starts in HTML5 and Unreal Engine. I put myself on a tight timeline, built in 6 months in my spare time and released on Steam only, where it got a few hundred downloads and made a bit over $1000</p>
</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<hr>
<p> </p>







  








  
  
  






<article class="latest-item mb-4" style="display:flex; align-items:flex-start;">
  <div class="media-column">
    <div class="media-container" style="width:300px; height:300px;">

      
        <a href="/treekeepers-vr/">
          <img src="https://hockenworks.com/images/treekeepers_moonlight.png" alt="Treekeepers VR">
        </a>

      

    </div>
  </div>

  <div class="text-column" style="align-self:flex-start; margin-top:0;">
    <h2 class="post-title" style="margin-top:0 !important; margin-bottom:0 !important;">
      <a class="link-light" href="/treekeepers-vr/">Treekeepers VR</a>
    </h2>
    <div class="post-summary" style="margin-top:0; margin-bottom:.5rem;">
      <div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    







    



    

























    
        
    
</div>

<p>Treekeepers VR is a networked VR game where up to 4 players can cooperate to navigate an oversized world and save a giant tree.</p>
<p>Treekeepers is in production on both Quest (standalone VR) and Steam (PC VR) with full cross-play functionality. See the <a href="https://togetheragainstudios.com/treekeepersvr/">Treekeepers VR Website</a> for links to all storefronts and more detail about the game.</p>
<h2 id="heading"></h2>
    </div>
    <p class="read-more text-secondary fst-italic" style="margin:0;">
      October 1, 2022 · 2 minutes ·
      <a href="/treekeepers-vr/">Read more →</a>
    </p>
  </div>
</article>


<blockquote>
<p>Treekeepers VR was an ambitious game development project I took on in 2021- my first published VR title and my first multiplayer title. The latter turned out to be the really hard part. It&rsquo;s now free on two platforms. Read more about it:</p>
</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<hr>
<p> </p>







  








  
  

  

  
  
    
    
  








<article class="latest-item mb-4" style="display:flex; align-items:flex-start;">
  <div class="media-column">
    <div class="media-container" style="width:300px; height:300px;">

      
        <a href="/this-website/">
          <img src="images/bubble4.gif" alt="This Website">
        </a>

      

    </div>
  </div>

  <div class="text-column" style="align-self:flex-start; margin-top:0;">
    <h2 class="post-title" style="margin-top:0 !important; margin-bottom:0 !important;">
      <a class="link-light" href="/this-website/">This Website</a>
    </h2>
    <div class="post-summary" style="margin-top:0; margin-bottom:.5rem;">
      <p>I&rsquo;m <a href="/about-me">Brian Hockenmaier</a>, and this site is full of things I build and write about. I love making games and things with VR and AI. I love DIY projects, especially ones involving programming, engineering and 3D modeling. Some of this has been cross or back-posted from my <a href="https://www.thingiverse.com/hockenmaier/designs">thingiverse</a>, <a href="https://x.com/Hockenmaier">twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/hockenmaier/">linkedin</a>, and other places, but it all lives here permanently.</p>
<p>All work and opinion here is fully my own and not my employer&rsquo;s.</p>
<p>This is an evolution of <a href="old-site/index.html">my previous site last updated in 2022, which I still keep inside this one</a> for posterity and for the AIs of the future to know more about me. I like it not because of the content as much as because it was a fully custom js and html site with no framework.. and I think it&rsquo;s sort of fun and funny that it was like this.</p>
    </div>
    <p class="read-more text-secondary fst-italic" style="margin:0;">
      May 28, 2025 · 13 minutes ·
      <a href="/this-website/">Read more →</a>
    </p>
  </div>
</article>


<blockquote>
<p>This Website itself was my 3rd released video game</p>
</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<hr>
<h2 id="top-3d-prints">Top 3D Prints</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been 3D Modeling since Cal Poly and printing since I got my first printer - the MakerGearM2 - in 2013. I have dozens of designs on thingiverse, some of which got pretty popular. A lot of my best work is made up of 3D printed games and game paraphernalia.</p>
<p> </p>







  








  
  
  






<article class="latest-item mb-4" style="display:flex; align-items:flex-start;">
  <div class="media-column">
    <div class="media-container" style="width:300px; height:300px;">

      
        <a href="/bloom-or-bust/">
          <img src="https://hockenworks.com/images/bloom-or-bust-characters.jpg" alt="Bloom Or Bust!">
        </a>

      

    </div>
  </div>

  <div class="text-column" style="align-self:flex-start; margin-top:0;">
    <h2 class="post-title" style="margin-top:0 !important; margin-bottom:0 !important;">
      <a class="link-light" href="/bloom-or-bust/">Bloom Or Bust!</a>
    </h2>
    <div class="post-summary" style="margin-top:0; margin-bottom:.5rem;">
      <p>Here&rsquo;s a peek at my first major board game creation!</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve made a few clones or slight enhancements of games I like before like <a href="/nope-game">Nope</a> and <a href="/hocken-pocket-blokus">Hocken-Pocket-Blokus</a>, but Bloom or Bust is my first attempt at something of my own design with very high production quality.</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    

























    
        
    
</div>

<p>This is a risk-taking game where players compete to take over a tree with their specific type of fruit. Trees and bees are becoming a recurring theme in my games!</p>
<p>All parts of this game are hand-designed by me, mostly in VR with a tool called Gravity Sketch, blender, and one of my favorite programmer&rsquo;s 3D tools called OpenSCAD.</p>
    </div>
    <p class="read-more text-secondary fst-italic" style="margin:0;">
      May 28, 2025 · 2 minutes ·
      <a href="/bloom-or-bust/">Read more →</a>
    </p>
  </div>
</article>


<blockquote>
<p>Bloom Or Bust is my latest and best board game. Fully designed from scratch using OpenSCAD and Gravity Sketch (A very fun VR-based 3D Modeling program)</p>
</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<hr>
<p> </p>







  








  
  
  






<article class="latest-item mb-4" style="display:flex; align-items:flex-start;">
  <div class="media-column">
    <div class="media-container" style="width:300px; height:300px;">

      
        <a href="/8-bit-coasters-10-year/">
          <img src="https://hockenworks.com/images/2023-8-bit-set-2.jpg" alt="8-Bit Videogame Coasters, 10 Year Anniversary Edition">
        </a>

      

    </div>
  </div>

  <div class="text-column" style="align-self:flex-start; margin-top:0;">
    <h2 class="post-title" style="margin-top:0 !important; margin-bottom:0 !important;">
      <a class="link-light" href="/8-bit-coasters-10-year/">8-Bit Videogame Coasters, 10 Year Anniversary Edition</a>
    </h2>
    <div class="post-summary" style="margin-top:0; margin-bottom:.5rem;">
      <p>If you like retro video games and also drinking things, you&rsquo;re in luck!
Print them for your living room! Print them for your friends!
I hope these characters remind you of some of your favorite series.</p>
<p>I returned to <a href="/8-bit-coasters">this project</a> after 10 years to make more coasters, including some designs for multi-plastic printers and a reinforced 4-coaster holder!</p>
<div class="paige-row-wide">
  <div style="display:grid; grid-template-columns:repeat(2, minmax(0,1fr)); gap:15px;">
      






























    













    



    

























      






























    













    



    
























</div>
</div>

<div class="paige-row-wide">
  <div style="display:grid; grid-template-columns:repeat(2, minmax(0,1fr)); gap:15px;">
      






























    













    



    

























      






























    













    



    
























</div>
</div>

<p>It was super fun returning to this project! I was able to fix a few things that I had noticed failing over the years, like the new reinforced sides to the &ldquo;? Block&rdquo; holder. Now that multi-color prints are proliferating more widely, I&rsquo;m hoping people can use the new colored files - they really pop with the Silk+Matte PLA combo I used here. Links to those filaments:</p>
    </div>
    <p class="read-more text-secondary fst-italic" style="margin:0;">
      August 6, 2023 · 1 minute ·
      <a href="/8-bit-coasters-10-year/">Read more →</a>
    </p>
  </div>
</article>


<blockquote>
<p>My most popular 3D design, remade for color in 2023.</p>
</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<hr>
<p> </p>







  








  
  
  






<article class="latest-item mb-4" style="display:flex; align-items:flex-start;">
  <div class="media-column">
    <div class="media-container" style="width:300px; height:300px;">

      
        <a href="/nope-game/">
          <img src="https://hockenworks.com/images/nope-1.jpg" alt="NOPE - A 3D and 2D Printed Card Game">
        </a>

      

    </div>
  </div>

  <div class="text-column" style="align-self:flex-start; margin-top:0;">
    <h2 class="post-title" style="margin-top:0 !important; margin-bottom:0 !important;">
      <a class="link-light" href="/nope-game/">NOPE - A 3D and 2D Printed Card Game</a>
    </h2>
    <div class="post-summary" style="margin-top:0; margin-bottom:.5rem;">
      <p>This game is based off of a similar card game called &ldquo;No Thanks!&rdquo; but expands the number of players to 8.</p>
    </div>
    <p class="read-more text-secondary fst-italic" style="margin:0;">
      January 19, 2015 · 2 minutes ·
      <a href="/nope-game/">Read more →</a>
    </p>
  </div>
</article>


<blockquote>
<p>My first custom game, NOPE is an expanded version of No Thanks that I released for free on Thingiverse</p>
</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<hr>
<p> </p>







  








  
  
  






<article class="latest-item mb-4" style="display:flex; align-items:flex-start;">
  <div class="media-column">
    <div class="media-container" style="width:300px; height:300px;">

      
        
        <a href="/3d-key/">
          <img src="https://img.youtube.com/vi/_H2W8qXUJtg/hqdefault.jpg" alt="3D Printed Key">
        </a>

      

    </div>
  </div>

  <div class="text-column" style="align-self:flex-start; margin-top:0;">
    <h2 class="post-title" style="margin-top:0 !important; margin-bottom:0 !important;">
      <a class="link-light" href="/3d-key/">3D Printed Key</a>
    </h2>
    <div class="post-summary" style="margin-top:0; margin-bottom:.5rem;">
      <p>I 3D Modeled and printed my apartment building&rsquo;s key with the Makergear M2. I won&rsquo;t be posting the model because it IS in fact a key to my apartment. Thanks for watching!</p>
    </div>
    <p class="read-more text-secondary fst-italic" style="margin:0;">
      May 13, 2013 · 1 minute ·
      <a href="/3d-key/">Read more →</a>
    </p>
  </div>
</article>


<blockquote>
<p>One of my first great 3D printing experiments, I duplicated my apartment key in CAD shortly after getting my first 3D printer, and actually used these keys as spares.</p>
</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<hr>
<p> </p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:hockenworks.com,2024-04-30:/about-me/</guid>

                
                    <link>https://hockenworks.com/about-me/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Hi, I’m Brian</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="this is a robot"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/ai-software-dev.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 720px; width: 100%"   >


    
</div>

<p>Lots of chatter right now about AI replacing software developers.</p>
<p>I agree - AI will take over software development. The question is: what work will be left when this happens?</p>
<p>Some considerations:</p>
<ul>
<li>Benchmarks for the best LLMs still put them solidly in the &ldquo;bad at programming&rdquo; category, scoring in the 5th percentile of human programmers on common tests. Meanwhile, LLMs score in the 80th-95th percentile for law exams and 85th–100th for psychology, statistics, and many other less technical fields. More scores available in the &ldquo;simulated exams&rdquo; section of <a href="https://openai.com/research/gpt-4">https://openai.com/research/gpt-4</a>.</li>
<li>Engineers have been using language models like tabnine and copilot as &ldquo;super-stackoverflow&rdquo; style code assistance years before chatGPT released. This means much of the velocity increase we might expect from current LLMs&rsquo; ability to write code has already been &ldquo;priced in&rdquo; to the market.</li>
<li>Many of the trends making software development more costly are growing, not shrinking: Systems are becoming more distributed. The cloud lowered infrastructure costs but made applications more complex. We&rsquo;re making more and deeper integrations among disparate systems. Auth is becoming more secure and thus complex (managed identity, MFA, etc).</li>
</ul>
<p>Github copilot chat and other LLM dev tools are speeding up the rote stuff. I’ve seen it in my own work.</p>
<p>And I really do believe new AI models will do more than just the basics, maybe in the next couple of years. Even precluding &ldquo;AGI&rdquo;, the trend we are on is that more and more work is automatable, and engineers, especially more junior ones - are going to have to shift focus away from algorithmic work that AI can do.</p>
<p>But by the time our neural nets are &ldquo;good enough&rdquo; at building software to make it significantly cheaper to build, I doubt this trend will make the news. Everything else gets automated too.</p>
<p>These are my thoughts at what seems to be the beginning of the next AI revolution in early 2024. I plan to revisit this topic and see if I&rsquo;m right in future posts.</p>]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:hockenworks.com,2024-01-24:/on-ai-software-development/</guid>

                
                    <link>https://hockenworks.com/on-ai-software-development/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2024 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>On AI Software Development</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I have been occasionally challenging GPT to create models using <a href="https://openscad.org/">OpenSCAD</a>, a &ldquo;programming language for 3D models&rdquo;</p>
<p>Both struggle, but GPT-4 has been a massive improvement. Here are both models&rsquo; outputs after asking for an acorn and 3 messages of me giving feedback:</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="some weird acorns"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/gpt-acorn.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 720px; width: 100%"   >


    
</div>

<p>For the record, it is impressive that these LLMs can get anything right with no visual input or training on shapes like these. Imagine looking at the programming reference for openSCAD and trying to do this blind. The fact that the 3.5 version has a bunch of strangely intersecting primitives and some union issues has been normal in my experience. It takes quite a bit of spatial logic to get a model not to look like that.</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:hockenworks.com,2023-03-19:/3d-modeling-with-ai/</guid>

                
                    <link>https://hockenworks.com/3d-modeling-with-ai/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Sun, 19 Mar 2023 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>3D Modeling With AI</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>Editor&rsquo;s note from 2025:</p>
<p>This article was written as part of the launch of <a href="/treekeepers-vr">Treekeepers VR</a> and the sole proprietorship Together Again Studios, and represents some of my core beliefs of the value of VR and where it&rsquo;s taking us socially. Though I&rsquo;m no longer actively working on Treekeepers, I do hold that VR and AR are truly the &ldquo;endgame&rdquo; of interface and one that could save us from some of the social attitudes caused by social media of today. Enjoy!</p>
</blockquote>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="proofreader GPT"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/together-again-studios.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 400px; width: 100%"   >


    
</div>

<p>With Together Again Studios and Treekeepers VR, we&rsquo;re setting out to solve an insidious problem we see all around us:</p>
<p><strong>Social Media Is Anti-Social</strong></p>
<p>Though Facebook, Instagram, Twitter, and Tiktok all let us share more with each other than ever before, what we are sharing is surprisingly hostile and dismissive of opinions other than our own.</p>
<p>Though Zoom, Hangouts and Teams let us finally see each other from a distance, we still can&rsquo;t speak naturally. We depend on tools like &ldquo;mute&rdquo;. We create meeting upon meeting with different sets of the same group of people. And we don&rsquo;t form the depth of relationships we could in-person.</p>
<p>We as humans are all-too-capable of forming us-versus-them &ldquo;tribes&rdquo; and dehumanizing those who appear too different, and this problem is becoming ever more apparent behind the curtain of the graphical user interface.</p>
<p><strong>Virtual and augmented reality are a way out</strong></p>
<p>In 2016, thanks to pioneers like Palmer Luckey, Michael Abrash, and John Carmack, we suddenly gained access to a technology that removes the curtain and forces us to see eachother. And in 2020, an event that has permanently limited our in-person interaction arose and gave new meaning to this technology.</p>
<p>In VR/AR, voices are no longer text on a screen, taken out of context by our social media bubbles. They&rsquo;re voices again.</p>
<p>In VR/AR, people are no longer user profiles with one image and a tag-line. They&rsquo;re really people, with bodies, faces, and hands that can point and gesture.</p>
<p>In VR/AR, messages are not just &ldquo;public&rdquo;, or &ldquo;direct&rdquo;. Conversations are dynamic, with people physically approaching one another to talk, with people moving in and out of physical groups, and with people attending public conversations together again while still able to have &ldquo;sidebar&rdquo; conversations.</p>
<p>All these abilities we used to have in-person, we have gained again in virtual reality.</p>
<p>Soon, we&rsquo;ll go even further with this technology. We&rsquo;ll be able to make real eye contact with eachother in VR. We&rsquo;ll use AR to invite distant friends and family over to our homes.</p>
<p>And at Together Again, we plan on using these new tools to let people like eachother again.</p>
<p><strong>Treekeepers: Only Possible in VR</strong></p>
<p>Why is Treekeepers a VR Game?</p>
<p><strong>Multiplayer of this depth only works in VR</strong></p>
<p>The challenges in Treekeepers VR hinge on player coordination and quick group decisions - Which weapon should we upgrade? Who&rsquo;s doing which job? Where are we going?</p>
<p>In VR, you gain the ability to gesture and point to enemies and obstacles naturally.</p>
<p>No more &ldquo;Who is the green player?&rdquo; - spend zero mental energy figuring out who you are talking to. Just turn towards them and speak.</p>
<p><strong>Scale is the most fun when you&rsquo;re in the world</strong></p>
<p>We&rsquo;re going to be exploring oversized objects around a gigantic tree. Only VR can get the full benefit of this experience.</p>
<p><strong>VR can be uncomfortable</strong></p>
<p>BUT, experiencing it via a static vehicle which acts as a persistent frame of reference reduces motion sickness.</p>
<p>No need to rotate - gameplay is based on the hot air balloon always facing one direction, and players navigating within it.</p>
<hr>
<p>Check out Treekeepers VR <a href="/treekeepers-vr">here</a></p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:hockenworks.com,2022-08-01:/social-media-is-antisocial/</guid>

                
                    <link>https://hockenworks.com/social-media-is-antisocial/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Social Media Is Anti-Social</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
