













    
        
    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    







    

    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"  xml:lang="en-us"  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            

            
                
            

            
                <link href="https://hockenworks.com/categories/writing/" rel="self" type="text/html"/>
            
        
            

            

            
                <link href="https://hockenworks.com/categories/writing/rss.xml" rel="alternate" type="application/rss+xml"/>
            
        

        

        

        <description>Recent content</description>

        
            <language>en-us</language>
        

        
            <lastBuildDate>2025-05-24 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</lastBuildDate>
        

        <link>https://hockenworks.com/categories/writing/</link>

        

        <title>Writing · Categories · hockenworks</title>

        

        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Recently I read the <a href="https://ai-2027.com/scenario.pdf">AI 2027 paper</a>. I was surprised to see Scott Alexander&rsquo;s name on this paper and I was doubly surprised to see him do his <a href="https://www.dwarkesh.com/p/scott-daniel">first face reveal podcast about it with Dwarkesh</a></p>
<p>On its face this is one of the most aggressive predictions for when we will have AGI (at least the new definition of AGI which is something that is comparable or better than humans at all non-bodily tasks) that I have read. Even as someone who has been a long believer in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Singularity_Is_Near">Ray Kurzweil&rsquo;s Singularity predictions</a>, 2027 strikes me as very early. I realize that Kurzweil&rsquo;s AGI date was also late 2020&rsquo;s and 2045 was his singulartiy prediction - 2027 still feels early to me.</p>
<div class="paige-row-wide">
  <div style="display:grid; grid-template-columns:repeat(2, minmax(0,1fr)); gap:15px;">
      






























    













    



    






















<img  alt="AI 2027"   class="rounded-4 w-100"  crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/ai-2027.png"    >


      






























    













    



    






















<img  alt="Singularity Is Near"   class="rounded-4 w-100"  crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/The-Singularity-Is-Near.JPG"    >

</div>
</div>

<p>I won&rsquo;t get into my full take on AI 2027 here, but the core argument comes down to the same one I was making in my <a href="/on-ai-software-development">original post on AI software development</a></p>
<ul>
<li>which is that, once AI agents are able to replace software engineers, instead of just assisting them, it doesn&rsquo;t matter how they are doing another realms, because they will simply be able to improve on themselves and their own software at such a rate that the difference between the time of automating software engineering jobs and the time of automating all other jobs is negligible.</li>
</ul>
<p>So I figured it was a good time to update on where I think AI is actually at at software engineering tasks. I&rsquo;ve had the chance to test many of the latest AI software development tools and models, and we have come a long way since my original post.</p>
<p>I have been doing a lot of development with AI for the last few years, especially the last couple of months on leave building the game in this site. And they are good. But the core problems with these models for software engineering are:</p>
<ol>
<li>They can&rsquo;t deal well with contexts over 30K tokens or so (even the best models with supposed millions of token windows).</li>
</ol>
<p>This means the actual developer (me and you) are the ones picking specific files and functions to send into the context window, lest we confuse the model. This is arduous unless the codebase is small enough to fit entirely into the context window. That&rsquo;s exactly what I think is going on with most of the new &ldquo;vibe coded&rdquo; projects we see showing impressive results - these are just tiny POC apps that haven&rsquo;t hit more than a few thousand lines of code yet. For context, most serious enterprise apps containing the detailed logic and edge cases real use cases require are in the millions or hundreds of millions of lines of code.</p>
<ol start="2">
<li>They are biased to be &ldquo;advisors&rdquo; as well as &ldquo;doers&rdquo;</li>
</ol>
<p>This is just annoying, and I hope it gets trained out soon. Models just really <em>want</em> you to be doing everything, and to act themselves as an advisor. It makes sense with one of the main sources of code training data being from Stackoverflow and other blogs, where developers can never seem to rid themselves of a pseudo-condescending &ldquo;you should have been able to read the docs and learn this yourself&rdquo; tone. It&rsquo;s also just a pattern exhibited by people in general - more often than not, especially in the corporate world, people are trained to be the &ldquo;coaches&rdquo; rather than the &ldquo;worker bees&rdquo;. One reason why things get done so slowly in big political companies sometimes.</p>
<p>&mdash;Notes&mdash;</p>
<p>Add links to my chat with 03 about the refund feature,</p>
<p>Add links to videos about co-pilot agents as well as codex as the state of the art actual software developers</p>
<p>Talk a little bit about my experience using cursor and what a disappointment it was for a code base as unique as mine</p>
<p>Add notes about cursor not handling context any more easily than context caddy - and that might be a bit of a stumbling block</p>
<p>First feature that sonnet 3.7 consistently failed at was simply having the compactors add ball value accumulation of compacted balls</p>
<p>Your request has been blocked as our system has detected suspicious activity from your account.If you believe this is a mistake, please contact us at <a href="mailto:hi@cursor.com">hi@cursor.com</a>.(Request ID: 997e94bb-34ee-44c0-b0aa-15bb6822add6)</p>
<p>LOL</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:hockenworks.com,2025-05-24:/on-ai-software-development-2/</guid>

                
                    <link>https://hockenworks.com/on-ai-software-development-2/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Sat, 24 May 2025 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>On AI Software Development, 2025 Edition</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>During my parental leave, I played through quite a few video games - something I love and one of the easiest ways to spend time while rocking my daughter to sleep.</p>
<p>They include:</p>
<ul>
<li>The Legend of Zelda: The Minish Cap <sup>Steam Deck</sup></li>
<li>Carto <sup>Steam on Windows</sup></li>
<li>Tunic <sup>Steam on Windows</sup></li>
<li>Abzu <sup>Steam on Windows</sup></li>
<li>SteamWorld: Build <sup>Steam on Windows</sup></li>
<li>World of Goo 2 <sup>Nintendo Switch</sup></li>
<li>Oblivion Remastered <sup>Steam on Windows</sup></li>
<li>Mario Kart World <sup>Nintendo Switch 2</sup></li>
<li>Donkey Kong Bananza <sup>Nintendo Switch 2</sup></li>
</ul>
<p>Most of these are indie titles, but the one I spent the most time on was the Oblivion Remaster - one which surprised me both with how good it looks and with how well it played. Oblivion is a 19 year old game, and a purely graphics-related overhaul should not have made it as good or better than modern AAA games releasing today, but in my opinion (and many others I’m reading) it absolutely did. How could this be?</p>
<h2 id="graphics">Graphics</h2>
<p>Well - I think that’s pretty clear. The only thing that has really improved about mainstream gaming in the last 20 years is graphics.</p>
<p>And boy have the graphics improved. Oblivion not only uses new techniques like ray-tracing and revamped 4K textures and normal maps etc, it uses the full suite of global illumination provided by <a href="https://dev.epicgames.com/documentation/en-us/unreal-engine/lumen-global-illumination-and-reflections-in-unreal-engine">Unreal Engine</a>, which means when you turn the settings up, it depends on hardly any of the typical tricks games need to use, like baked light maps, instead lighting almost everything in the game dynamically or “procedurally”, including things like reflections of reflections and lit up dust and fog.</p>

<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
  <video controls loop muted autoplay style="max-width:100%;">
    <source src="/videos/bruma-clip.mp4" type="video/mp4">
    Your browser doesn’t support HTML5 video.
  </video>
  
    <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">This is from my playthrough, some outdoor torches in Bruma and mountain lighting in the background make for a pretty good use of full Lumen</span>
  
</div>

<p>Yes, Oblivion still has some simplistic design in terms of how landscapes are laid out, but that simplicity might also be why people can run it with Nvidia Lumen set up to run at ultra. Lighting is what’s really differentiating in video game graphics now, and fully simulated lighting beats or meets nearly every AAA game releasing lately that all cost tens or hundreds of millions of dollars to make.</p>
<h2 id="not-graphics">Not Graphics</h2>
<p>Left unstated is why nothing else has improved. Walking around Oblivion, meeting characters that have some scripted voice lines, responding to them with 1 of 4 options, holding down the left stick to sprint, and hitting a single button on your controller to watch your character animate a full scripted sword swing are all the standard gameplay of action-RPGs both 19 years ago and today. The same can be said of other genres - mechanics are largely untouched for the last 20 years outside of some common quality of life changes in how menus and inventory and HUDs work.</p>
<p>Here’s my theory for why: The games industry achieved the threshold of what was comfortable and possible with the current human-computer input and output mechanisms only a few years after they were technically possible. And those inputs and outputs have not changed much since the 90s. Looking at a flat screen in front of you and pressing buttons on a controller or keyboard/mouse are incredibly limiting for gaming. Increasing the amount of pixels on the screen and making that controller wireless don&rsquo;t change the core gameplay. This is not really true for any other media than games. Reading, watching films, and all kinds of media in between essentially max out on one screen and limited input, but games immediately ran into forms of input and output as a barrier.</p>
<p>I wrote a little about this topic in <a href="/social-media-is-antisocial">my first post about VR and why I think it’s the future</a>. The only true innovation in gameplay that is happening in two places:</p>
<ul>
<li>Indie, where one-man teams can come up with strange mashups and mechanics can execute on a vision spending very little. These are almost never totally genre defining, but they are inventive.</li>
<li>VR, where we have only scratched the surface of mechanics that work and what is possible when the player’s entire hands and 3D field of view are in the game.</li>
</ul>
<p>AAA game developers are excluded from the first by definition and are excluded from the second by their own financial decision makers.</p>
<h2 id="so-what-my-predictions">So What? My predictions</h2>
<p>Maybe people want to keep buying the same games with better graphics forever. I don’t think they do. I think those decision makers that aren’t investing in truly new AAA gameplay are short sighted. As long as we’ve been hearing that VR is the future and not seeing it totally come to fruition, at some point these companies that are milking the same game franchises for years will face the reality that people will only buy the same games reskinned with better graphics for so long. They’ll either be replaced by companies that innovate or individuals using AI that will be plenty good at recreating the same game over and over again.</p>
<p>I am hoping that the current hypestorm around AI re-kindles the ideas in the hearts of AAA game studio CFOs that they might need to invest in innovation and new ideas again. Some of the things that make Oblivion just like any RPG of today (Think about the four-option scripted discourse and stuffy voice lines as two) would be meaningfully different if AI was applied in the right way. And I think they’d be far more powerful experiences, just like I think VR games can be - so much higher fidelity and responsive to player input.</p>
<p>Here are my predictions of things we’ll see in the next decade or so, regardless of the AAA studios pioneer them or not:</p>
<p>A decade or two from now, we will look at the period of 2005 to 2025 and see that it was a period of a great stagnation in game innovation. This will be driven by a few key technological advances and the downstream game mechanics that will flow from those, stemming mainly from the areas of AI and what is now called mixed reality.</p>
<p>I’m going to make a few specific predictions of mechanics we will see in the future that will make the stagnation of the last 20 years totally transparent:</p>
<h4 id="ai">AI:</h4>
<ul>
<li>
<p>In open world games, it will become standard for non-player characters to have fully generated dialogues based on motivations and incentives rather than scripts</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>In open world games, players will speak directly or engage directly in some way with their own words that NPCs will understand and react to intelligently</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>NPCs won&rsquo;t have recorded voice lines, but will instead have voices generated in real time, and AAA games will start to make contracts with celebrity talent in order to generate their voice in games</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>We will see a transition from the current minorly procedural elements of gameplay to full procedural generated worlds, especially where player actions and environmental events change landscape, buildings, etc dynamically</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Game art will go through an incredible revolution, and we will stop having massive teams of people creating 3D meshes and textures to drop around the world, with many of these meshes and textures being generated from prompts in development, but also being generated on the fly in games</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="mixed-reality">Mixed Reality:</h4>
<p>The first reasonable augmented reality glasses that consumers are willing to wear en masse will generate entirely new genres:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>A new genre of video board games, where gameplay happens in view of a group of people in the same physical space, on a table, on the ground, in a park, etc, that will incorporate video game elements such as computations that are too complicated for typical board games, with the advantages that board games have today where players can interact with the same physical pieces, point and gesture, and socialize in person</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Another new genre of exercise programs combined with games. This will go far beyond current treadmills that have built-in virtual run routes or virtual exercise classes, this will be exercise incorporated as a leveling or other mechanic that will incentivize players to get some exercise. I&rsquo;ve had a lot of hope for this category for a long time, and the one major threat to it is GLP-1 drugs that may cause a serious decline in the need and desire for people to exercise daily for calorie loss</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>When will these happen? My specific prediction is that the next 3 years will be seen as the end of the period of stagnation we are in right now, a period that will be much more apparent looking backwards than it is from within. The combo of a decline in AAA game spending and AI hype feel like ripe conditions for innovation to return to gameplay - and my hope is that all of the other potential gameplay innovations ride the same AI wave.</p>]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:hockenworks.com,2025-05-12:/the-purgatory-of-aaa-gaming/</guid>

                
                    <link>https://hockenworks.com/the-purgatory-of-aaa-gaming/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 12 May 2025 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>The Purgatory of AAA Gaming</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="Brian and Alice"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/brian-and-alice-gaming-zoom.jpg"   style="height: auto; max-width: 400px; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">↑ me and Alice</span>
    
</div>

<p>I&rsquo;m Brian Hockenmaier, dad, engineer, and fun haver.</p>
<p>I grew up in Ventura, California with two UCLA-engineer parents. Even though neither of them were engineers long-term, I was an engineering child. I was always building something, highlights including a functional submarine and weather balloon with Lego robotics.</p>
<p>I went to school for industrial engineering at <a href="https://www.calpoly.edu/">Cal Poly SLO</a>, nearly double majored in economics, and then promptly moved out of both fields just like my parents had moved out of their education fields of mechanical and aerospace. Since then, after reading Ray Kurzweil&rsquo;s <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Singularity_Is_Near">The Singularity is Near</a> in 2011, feeling I needed to be closer to software and realizing I liked building systems more than anything in industrial engineering, I&rsquo;ve built a career in software and then AI.</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="A lego crane"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/lego-crane.jpg"   style="height: auto; max-width: 400px; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">One of the few pictures I have from my time building robots with legos, showing a robotic crane to my Dad</span>
    
</div>

<p>At work, I try to be low time preference, high autonomy, low consensus (even contrarian), high invention, process-light.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been at one company for a long time for a millennial. I&rsquo;ve built a lot of enterprise software and four high performing software teams. I started on back-office stuff like billing systems, TV scheduling systems, IP rights management systems, and file ingest systems for News. Most recently I’m making some pretty awesome stuff in agentic AI for the mundane work that the people at my company have to do!</p>
<p>My bias is to build rather than talk. I&rsquo;m the one pushing to just try to build the thing, to scrap it early if needed, and to take risks releasing early. I figure that we always know more, and usually throw away our plans, when we start to build. I love building strange things, useful thingss, fun things. One of the things I built was this website and the game running on top of it. <a href="/this-website">Read more about that here</a></p>
<p>Other Profiles:</p>
<p>Most of my development projects are stored on public or private repos on <a href="https://github.com/hockenmaier">my github</a></p>
<p>A collection of physical projects and 3D designs can be found on <a href="https://www.thingiverse.com/hockenmaier/designs">my thingiverse</a></p>
<p>And my professional persona can be found on <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/hockenmaier/">my linkedin</a></p>
<hr>
<h1 id="where-to-start">Where to start</h1>
<p>I post here mostly about things I&rsquo;m making and occasional essays. If you’re interested in this site but don’t know where to start, try reading any of these posts that sound interesting to you. They&rsquo;re either peices or projects I put a lot of time into.</p>
<h2 id="my-games">My Games</h2>







  








  
  

  

  
  
    
    
  








<article class="latest-item mb-4" style="display:flex; align-items:flex-start;">
  <div class="media-column">
    <div class="media-container" style="width:300px; height:300px;">

      
        <a href="/land-war/">
          <img src="images/land_war_e3.png" alt="Land War">
        </a>

      

    </div>
  </div>

  <div class="text-column" style="align-self:flex-start; margin-top:0;">
    <h2 class="post-title" style="margin-top:0 !important; margin-bottom:0 !important;">
      <a class="link-light" href="/land-war/">Land War</a>
    </h2>
    <div class="post-summary" style="margin-top:0; margin-bottom:.5rem;">
      <p>Land War is an 8-player strategy game I developed as a solo project and released to Steam in March of 2019.<br>
This game was intended to have low art requirements and simple interaction rules that result in deep strategic gameplay.</p>
<p>The core concept is that of an ultra-simplified real-time-strategy game. Each player is represented by a color and can grow their territory by moving in any direction. The strategic elements occur when players encounter other players and have to make choices about which side of their land to defend or give up. Players can use the structure of the map and the coordinated action of other players to gain defensible footholds in order to take more area and eventually be the last player on the board.</p>
    </div>
    <p class="read-more text-secondary fst-italic" style="margin:0;">
      March 1, 2019 · 3 minutes ·
      <a href="/land-war/">Read more →</a>
    </p>
  </div>
</article>


<blockquote>
<p>Land War was my first published game. I built in in 6 months and released on Steam only, where it got a few hundred downloads and made a bit over $1000</p>
</blockquote>
<p> </p>
<hr>
<p> </p>
<blockquote>
<p>Treekeepers VR was an ambitious game developement project I took on in 2021- my first published VR title and my first multiplayer title. The latter turned out to be the really hard part. Read more about it:</p>
</blockquote>
<p> </p>







  








  
  
  






<article class="latest-item mb-4" style="display:flex; align-items:flex-start;">
  <div class="media-column">
    <div class="media-container" style="width:300px; height:300px;">

      
        <a href="/treekeepers-vr/">
          <img src="https://hockenworks.com/images/treekeepers_moonlight.png" alt="Treekeepers VR">
        </a>

      

    </div>
  </div>

  <div class="text-column" style="align-self:flex-start; margin-top:0;">
    <h2 class="post-title" style="margin-top:0 !important; margin-bottom:0 !important;">
      <a class="link-light" href="/treekeepers-vr/">Treekeepers VR</a>
    </h2>
    <div class="post-summary" style="margin-top:0; margin-bottom:.5rem;">
      <div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    







    



    

























    
        
    
</div>

<p>Treekeepers VR is a networked VR game where up to 4 players can cooperate to navigate an oversized world and save a giant tree.</p>
<p>Treekeepers is in production on both Quest (standalone VR) and Steam (PC VR) with full cross-play functionality. See the <a href="https://togetheragainstudios.com/treekeepersvr/">Treekeepers VR Website</a> for links to all storefronts and more detail about the game.</p>
<h2 id="heading"></h2>
    </div>
    <p class="read-more text-secondary fst-italic" style="margin:0;">
      October 1, 2022 · 2 minutes ·
      <a href="/treekeepers-vr/">Read more →</a>
    </p>
  </div>
</article>


<p> </p>
<hr>
<p> </p>
<blockquote>
<p>This Website itself was my 3rd video game:</p>
</blockquote>







  








  
  

  

  
  
    
    
  








<article class="latest-item mb-4" style="display:flex; align-items:flex-start;">
  <div class="media-column">
    <div class="media-container" style="width:300px; height:300px;">

      
        <a href="/this-website/">
          <img src="images/this-website-ball-machine-1.png" alt="This Website">
        </a>

      

    </div>
  </div>

  <div class="text-column" style="align-self:flex-start; margin-top:0;">
    <h2 class="post-title" style="margin-top:0 !important; margin-bottom:0 !important;">
      <a class="link-light" href="/this-website/">This Website</a>
    </h2>
    <div class="post-summary" style="margin-top:0; margin-bottom:.5rem;">
      <p>I&rsquo;m <a href="/about-me">Brian Hockenmaier</a>, and this site is full of things I build and write about. I love making games and things with VR and AI. I love DIY projects, epecially ones involving programming, engineering and 3D modeling. Some of this has been cross or back-posted from my <a href="https://www.thingiverse.com/hockenmaier/designs">thingiverse</a>, <a href="https://x.com/Hockenmaier">twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/hockenmaier/">linkedin</a>, and other places, but it all lives here permanently.</p>
<p>All work and opinion here is fully my own and not my employer&rsquo;s.</p>
<p>This is an evolution of <a href="old-site/index.html">my previous site last updated in 2022, which I still keep inside this one</a> for posterity and for the AIs of the future to know more about me. I like it not because of the content as much as because it was a fully custom js and html site with no framework.. and I think it&rsquo;s sort of fun and funny that it was like this.</p>
    </div>
    <p class="read-more text-secondary fst-italic" style="margin:0;">
      March 1, 2025 · 10 minutes ·
      <a href="/this-website/">Read more →</a>
    </p>
  </div>
</article>


<p> </p>
<hr>
<p> </p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:hockenworks.com,2024-04-30:/about-me/</guid>

                
                    <link>https://hockenworks.com/about-me/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Hi, I’m Brian</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="this is a robot"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/ai-software-dev.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 720px; width: 100%"   >


    
</div>

<p>Lots of chatter right now about AI replacing software developers.</p>
<p>I agree - AI will take over software development. The question is: what work will be left when this happens?</p>
<p>Some considerations:</p>
<ul>
<li>Benchmarks for the best LLMs still put them solidly in the &ldquo;bad at programming&rdquo; category, scoring in the 5th percentile of human programmers on common tests. Meanwhile, LLMs score in the 80th-95th percentile for law exams and 85th–100th for psychology, statistics, and many other less technical fields. More scores available in the &ldquo;simulated exams&rdquo; section of <a href="https://openai.com/research/gpt-4">https://openai.com/research/gpt-4</a>.</li>
<li>Engineers have been using language models like tabnine and copilot as &ldquo;super-stackoverflow&rdquo; style code assistance years before chatGPT released. This means much of the velocity increase we might expect from current LLMs&rsquo; ability to write code has already been &ldquo;priced in&rdquo; to the market.</li>
<li>Many of the trends making software development more costly are growing, not shrinking: Systems are becoming more distributed. The cloud lowered infrastructure costs but made applications more complex. We&rsquo;re making more and deeper integrations among disparate systems. Auth is becoming more secure and thus complex (managed identity, MFA, etc).</li>
</ul>
<p>Github copilot chat and other LLM dev tools are speeding up the rote stuff. I’ve seen it in my own work.</p>
<p>And I really do believe new AI models will do more than just the basics, maybe in the next couple of years. Even precluding &ldquo;AGI&rdquo;, the trend we are on is that more and more work is automatable, and engineers, especially more junior ones - are going to have to shift focus away from algorithmic work that AI can do.</p>
<p>But by the time our neural nets are &ldquo;good enough&rdquo; at building software to make it significantly cheaper to build, I doubt this trend will make the news. Everything else gets automated too.</p>
<p>These are my thoughts at what seems to be the beginning of the next AI revolution in early 2024. I plan to revisit this topic and see if I&rsquo;m right in future posts.</p>]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:hockenworks.com,2024-01-24:/on-ai-software-development/</guid>

                
                    <link>https://hockenworks.com/on-ai-software-development/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2024 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>On AI Software Development</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I have been occasionally challenging GPT to create models using <a href="https://openscad.org/">OpenSCAD</a>, a &ldquo;programming language for 3D models&rdquo;</p>
<p>Both struggle, but GPT-4 has been a massive improvement. Here are both model&rsquo;s outputs after asking for an acorn and 3 messages of me giving feedback:</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="some weird acorns"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/gpt-acorn.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 720px; width: 100%"   >


    
</div>

<p>For the record, it is impressive that these LLMs can get anything right with no visual input or training on shapes like these. Imagine looking at the programming reference for openSCAD and trying to do this blind. The fact that the 3.5 version has a bunch of strangely intersecting primitives and some union issues has been normal in my experience. It takes quite a bit of spacial logic to get a model not to look like that.</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:hockenworks.com,2023-03-19:/3d-modeling-with-ai/</guid>

                
                    <link>https://hockenworks.com/3d-modeling-with-ai/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Sun, 19 Mar 2023 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>3D Modeling With AI</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>Editor&rsquo;s note from 2025:</p>
<p>This article was written as part of the launch of <a href="/treekeepers-vr">Treekeepers VR</a> and the sole proprietorship Together Again Studios, and represents some of my core beliefs of the value of VR and where it&rsquo;s taking us socially. Though I&rsquo;m no longer actively working on Treekeepers, I do hold that VR and AR are truly the &ldquo;endgame&rdquo; of interface and one that could save us from some of the social attitudes caused by social media of today. Enjoy!</p>
</blockquote>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="proofreader GPT"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/together-again-studios.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 400px; width: 100%"   >


    
</div>

<p>With Together Again Studios and Treekeepers VR, we&rsquo;re setting out to solve an insidious problem we see all around us:</p>
<p><strong>Social Media Is Anti-Social</strong></p>
<p>Though Facebook, Instagram, Twitter, and Tiktok all let us share more with each other than ever before, what we are sharing is surprisingly hostile and dismissive of opinions other than our own.</p>
<p>Though Zoom, Hangouts and Teams let us finally see each other from a distance, we still can&rsquo;t speak naturally. We depend on tools like &ldquo;mute&rdquo;. We create meeting upon meeting with different sets of the same group of people. And we don&rsquo;t form the depth of relationships we could in-person.</p>
<p>We as humans are all-too-capable of forming us-versus-them &ldquo;tribes&rdquo; and dehumanizing those who appear too different, and this problem is becoming ever more apparent behind the curtain of the graphical user interface.</p>
<p><strong>Virtual and augmented reality are a way out</strong></p>
<p>In 2016, thanks to pioneers like Palmer Luckey, Michael Abrash, and John Carmack, we suddenly gained access to a technology that removes the curtain and forces us to see eachother. And in 2020, an event that has permanently limited our in-person interaction arose and gave new meaning to this technology.</p>
<p>In VR/AR, voices are no longer text on a screen, taken out of context by our social media bubbles. They&rsquo;re voices again.</p>
<p>In VR/AR, people are no longer user profiles with one image and a tag-line. They&rsquo;re really people, with bodies, faces, and hands that can point and gesture.</p>
<p>In VR/AR, messages are not just &ldquo;public&rdquo;, or &ldquo;direct&rdquo;. Conversations are dynamic, with people physically approaching one another to talk, with people moving in and out of physical groups, and with people attending public conversations together again while still able to have &ldquo;sidebar&rdquo; conversations.</p>
<p>All these abilities we used to have in-person, we have gained again in virtual reality.</p>
<p>Soon, we&rsquo;ll go even further with this technology. We&rsquo;ll be able to make real eye contact with eachother in VR. We&rsquo;ll use AR to invite distant friends and family over to our homes.</p>
<p>And at Together Again, we plan on using these new tools to let people like eachother again.</p>
<p><strong>Treekeepers: Only Possible in VR</strong></p>
<p>Why is Treekeepers a VR Game?</p>
<p><strong>Multiplayer of this depth only works in VR</strong></p>
<p>The challenges in Treekeepers VR hinge on player coordination and quick group decisions - Which weapon should we upgrade? Who&rsquo;s doing which job? Where are we going?</p>
<p>In VR, you gain the ability to gesture and point to enemies and obstacles naturally.</p>
<p>No more &ldquo;Who is the green player?&rdquo; - spend zero mental energy figuring out who you are talking to. Just turn towards them and speak.</p>
<p><strong>Scale is the most fun when you&rsquo;re in the world</strong></p>
<p>We&rsquo;re going to be exploring oversized objects around a gigantic tree. Only VR can get the full benefit of this experience.</p>
<p><strong>VR can be uncomfortable</strong></p>
<p>BUT, experiencing it via a static vehicle which acts as a persistent frame of reference reduces motion sickness.</p>
<p>No need to rotate - gameplay is based on the hot air balloon always facing one direction, and players navigating within it.</p>
<hr>
<p>Check out Treekeepers VR <a href="/treekeepers-vr">here</a></p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:hockenworks.com,2022-08-01:/social-media-is-antisocial/</guid>

                
                    <link>https://hockenworks.com/social-media-is-antisocial/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Social Media Is Anti-Social</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
