













    
        
    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    







    

    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"  xml:lang="en-us"  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            

            
                
            

            
                <link href="https://hockenworks.com/tags/indie-games/" rel="self" type="text/html"/>
            
        
            

            

            
                <link href="https://hockenworks.com/tags/indie-games/rss.xml" rel="alternate" type="application/rss+xml"/>
            
        

        

        

        <description>Recent content</description>

        
            <language>en-us</language>
        

        
            <lastBuildDate>2025-07-07 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</lastBuildDate>
        

        <link>https://hockenworks.com/tags/indie-games/</link>

        

        <title>Indie Games · Tags · hockenworks</title>

        

        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>During my parental leave, which ends tomorrow, I played through quite a few video games - something I love and one of the easiest ways to spend time while rocking my baby daughter to sleep. And it doesn&rsquo;t hurt that my amazing wife loves watching games about as much as TV or movies with me, as long as they are beautiful or cooperative in some way. All of these are.</p>
<p>They include, in order:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Legend_of_Zelda:_The_Minish_Cap">The Legend of Zelda: The Minish Cap</a> <sup>Steam Deck</sup></li>
<li><a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/1172450/Carto/">Carto</a> <sup>Steam on Windows</sup> – also where my favorite Daddy-daughter song so far, <a href="https://open.spotify.com/track/669Y0Jq6EBlsvToJ6AeUNz?si=1b321f505f4e4f8c">Bond</a> comes from.</li>
<li><a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/553420/TUNIC/">Tunic</a> <sup>Steam on Windows</sup></li>
<li><a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/384190/ABZU/">Abzu</a> <sup>Steam on Windows</sup></li>
<li><a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/2134770/SteamWorld_Build/">SteamWorld: Build</a> <sup>Steam on Windows</sup></li>
<li><a href="https://www.nintendo.com/us/store/products/world-of-goo-2-switch/">World of Goo 2</a> <sup>Nintendo Switch</sup></li>
<li><a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/2623190/The_Elder_Scrolls_IV_Oblivion_Remastered/">Oblivion Remastered</a> <sup>Steam on Windows</sup></li>
<li><a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/2379780/Balatro/">Balatro</a> <sup>Steam on Windows</sup></li>
<li><a href="https://www.nintendo.com/us/store/products/mario-kart-world-switch-2/">Mario Kart World</a> <sup>Nintendo Switch 2</sup></li>
<li><a href="https://www.nintendo.com/us/store/products/nintendo-switch-2-welcome-tour-switch-2/">Nintendo Switch 2 Welcome Tour</a> <sup>Nintendo Switch 2</sup></li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yoshi%27s_Island">Yoshi&rsquo;s Island SNES</a> <sup>Nintendo Switch 2</sup></li>
<li><a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/1601570/The_Alters/">The Alters</a> <sup>Steam on Windows</sup></li>
</ul>
<p>And yes, I did pick the game from my favorite series that happens to be about miniature people as the first game my miniature daughter Alice would hear.</p>
<p>Most of these are indie titles, but the one I spent the most time on was the Oblivion Remaster - one which surprised me both with how good it looks and with how well it played. Oblivion is a 19 year old game, and a purely graphics-related overhaul should not have made it as good or better than modern AAA games releasing today, but in my opinion (and many others I’m reading) it absolutely did. How could this be?</p>
<h2 id="graphics">Graphics</h2>
<p>Well - I think that’s pretty clear. The only thing that has really improved about mainstream gaming in the last 20 years is graphics.</p>
<p>And boy have the graphics improved. Oblivion not only uses new techniques like ray-tracing and revamped 4K textures and normal maps etc, it uses the full suite of global illumination provided by <a href="https://dev.epicgames.com/documentation/en-us/unreal-engine/lumen-global-illumination-and-reflections-in-unreal-engine">Unreal Engine</a>, which means when you turn the settings up, it depends on hardly any of the typical tricks games need to use, like baked light maps, instead lighting almost everything in the game dynamically or “procedurally”, including things like reflections of reflections and lit up dust and fog.</p>
<p>
    <div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
      <iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" loading="eager" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/dbd00XaK1so?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video"></iframe>
    </div>

<em>This is from my playthrough, some outdoor torches in Bruma and mountain lighting in the background make for a pretty good use of full Lumen</em></p>
<p>Yes, Oblivion still has some simplistic design in terms of how landscapes are laid out, but that simplicity might also be why people can run it with Unreal&rsquo;s Lumen set up to run at ultra. Lighting is what’s really differentiating in video game graphics now, and fully simulated lighting beats or meets nearly every AAA game releasing lately that all cost tens or hundreds of millions of dollars to make.</p>
<h2 id="not-graphics">Not Graphics</h2>
<p>Left unstated is why nothing else has improved. Walking around Oblivion, meeting characters that have some scripted voice lines, responding to them with 1 of 4 options, holding down the left stick to sprint, and hitting a single button on your controller to watch your character animate a full scripted sword swing are all the standard gameplay of action-RPGs both 19 years ago and today. The same can be said of other genres - mechanics are largely untouched for the last 20 years outside of some common quality of life changes in how menus and inventory and HUDs work.</p>
<p>Here’s my theory for why: The games industry achieved the threshold of what was comfortable and possible with the current human-computer input and output mechanisms only a few years after they were technically possible. And those inputs and outputs have not changed much since the 90s. Looking at a flat screen in front of you and pressing buttons on a controller or keyboard/mouse is incredibly limiting for gaming. Increasing the amount of pixels on the screen and making that controller wireless don&rsquo;t change the core gameplay. This is not really true for any other media than games. Reading, watching films, and all kinds of media in between essentially max out on one screen and limited input, but games immediately ran into forms of input and output as a barrier.</p>
<p>I wrote a little about this topic in <a href="/social-media-is-antisocial">my first post about VR and why I think it’s the future</a>. The only true innovation in gameplay that is happening in two places:</p>
<ul>
<li>Indie, where one-man teams can come up with strange mashups and mechanics can execute on a vision spending very little. These are almost never totally genre defining, but they are inventive.</li>
<li>VR, where we have only scratched the surface of mechanics that work and what is possible when the player’s entire hands and 3D field of view are in the game.</li>
</ul>
<p>AAA game developers are excluded from the first by definition and are excluded from the second by their own financial decision makers.</p>
<h2 id="so-what-my-predictions">So What? My predictions</h2>
<p>Maybe people want to keep buying the same games with better graphics forever. I don’t think they do. I think those decision makers that aren’t investing in truly new AAA gameplay are short sighted. As long as we’ve been hearing that VR is the future and not seeing it totally come to fruition, at some point these companies that are milking the same game franchises for years will face the reality that people will only buy the same games reskinned with better graphics for so long. They’ll either be replaced by companies that innovate or individuals using AI that will be plenty good at recreating the same game over and over again.</p>
<p>I am hoping that the current hypestorm around AI re-kindles the ideas in the hearts of AAA game studio CFOs that they might need to invest in innovation and new ideas again. Some of the things that make Oblivion just like any RPG of today (Think about the four-option scripted discourse and stuffy voice lines as two) would be meaningfully different if AI was applied in the right way. And I think they’d be far more powerful experiences, just like I think VR games can be - so much higher fidelity and responsive to player input.</p>
<p>Here are my predictions of things we’ll see in the next decade or so, regardless of the AAA studios pioneer them or not:</p>
<p>A decade or two from now, we will look at the period of 2005 to 2025 and see that it was a period of a great stagnation in game innovation. This will be driven by a few key technological advances and the downstream game mechanics that will flow from those, stemming mainly from the areas of AI and what is now called mixed reality.</p>
<p>I’m going to make a few specific predictions of mechanics we will see in the future that will make the stagnation of the last 20 years totally transparent:</p>
<h4 id="ai">AI:</h4>
<ul>
<li>
<p>In open world games, it will become standard for non-player characters to have fully generated dialogues based on motivations and incentives rather than scripts</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>In open world games, players will speak directly or engage directly in some way with their own words that NPCs will understand and react to intelligently</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>NPCs won&rsquo;t have recorded voice lines, but will instead have voices generated in real time, and AAA games will start to make contracts with celebrity talent in order to generate their voice in games</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>We will see a transition from the current minorly procedural elements of gameplay to full procedural generated worlds, especially where player actions and environmental events change landscape, buildings, etc dynamically</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Game art will go through an incredible revolution, and we will stop having massive teams of people creating 3D meshes and textures to drop around the world, with many of these meshes and textures being generated from prompts in development, but also being generated on the fly in games</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h4 id="mixed-reality">Mixed Reality:</h4>
<p>The first reasonable augmented reality glasses that consumers are willing to wear en masse will generate entirely new genres:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>A new genre of video board games, where gameplay happens in view of a group of people in the same physical space, on a table, on the ground, in a park, etc, that will incorporate video game elements such as computations that are too complicated for typical board games, with the advantages that board games have today where players can interact with the same physical pieces, point and gesture, and socialize in person</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Another new genre of exercise programs combined with games. This will go far beyond current treadmills that have built-in virtual run routes or virtual exercise classes, this will be exercise incorporated as a leveling or other mechanic that will incentivize players to get some exercise. I&rsquo;ve had a lot of hope for this category for a long time, and the one major threat to it is GLP-1 drugs that may cause a serious decline in the need and desire for people to exercise daily for calorie loss</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>When will these happen? My specific prediction is that the next 3 years will be seen as the end of the period of stagnation we are in right now, a period that will be much more apparent looking backwards than it is from within. The combo of a decline in AAA game spending and AI hype feels like ripe conditions for innovation to return to gameplay - and my hope is that all of the other potential gameplay innovations ride the same AI wave.</p>]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:hockenworks.com,2025-07-07:/the-purgatory-of-aaa-gaming/</guid>

                
                    <link>https://hockenworks.com/the-purgatory-of-aaa-gaming/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jul 2025 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>The Purgatory of AAA Gaming</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>&ldquo;The Flapper&rdquo; is a project that spawned out of a simple VR movement mechanic test that I had in my head for a while, which turned out to be surprisingly fun! The idea is to flap your arms to fly - wrapped up as a multiplayer battle to really get people moving.</p>
<p>In order to start working on this game, because there was so much standard VR code that I had to write for <a href="/treekeepers-vr">Treekeepers</a>, I decided to make a sort of engine out of the Treekeepers codebase and work off of that rather than start from scratch. That let me tie in some of the nice associated graphics, music and sound effects I had made, and a bunch of other helper functions and tools I use for things like the camera following around the character, how I deal with collisions, a bunch of netcode, etc.</p>
<p>You can see my more detailed post about that engine here: <a href="/treekeepers-engine">Treekeepers Engine</a></p>
<h2 id="core-mechanic--gameplay">Core Mechanic &amp; Gameplay</h2>
<p>Most of the start of this game was just tuning the movement mechanic, which borrowed from some physics realities and some elements I made up to make flapping feel good. But, the essential idea was that each arm generates unique thrust in the direction it moves with an exponential applied to its speed. It&rsquo;s hard to describe any native VR mechanic with words and videos only, but to me and the folks I demoed it to, it felt &ldquo;right&rdquo; for how flying should work if you did it by flapping your arms - and that feeling is based in the physical reality of wing-powered flight. I had a ton of fun just jetting around the obstacle courses I made for myself.</p>
<p>My idea for this other than just the mechanic was to make a sort of gorilla tag-esque multiplayer game where players would fly around and try to pop each other&rsquo;s balloons in an NES balloon fight {link} style. Ideally something like 15 to 20 people would be in a lobby flying around and trying to pop each other.</p>
<p>Like gorilla tag I didn&rsquo;t want anyone to have to &ldquo;sit out&rdquo; of the game, so it&rsquo;s essentially a deathmatch where the player who pops the most balloons wins, and is also visible who&rsquo;s winning, because they also gain the balloons that they pop. In some playtests players would have 20 or 30 balloons on their heads. This was my clever idea of adding a built-in rubber-band effect to the gameplay as well, since having more balloons over your head made you a bigger target to pop. The gameplay worked well - but I never quite got the game to a place with netcode and networking engine where multiplayer felt seamless enough.</p>
<p>Here’s a video of one of the later states of the game, where I have it fully networked and am testing with friends, though it still has a few bugs here:</p>

    <div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
      <iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" loading="eager" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Vxn8rDOZ7dU?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video"></iframe>
    </div>

<h2 id="today">Today</h2>
<p>I stopped working on this project after about 3 months. It turned out that flying alone with this mechanic was very compelling (and also a great workout!) but the networking engine I had used for Treekeepers, Photon, was not up to the task for how low latency a competitive game needed to be. Treekeepers was four-player co-op so Photon was just fine.</p>
<p>In the future I might pick this one back up (or maybe have an AI agent pick it up for me depending on how that goes) using <a href="https://spacetimedb.com/">space-time DB</a> which looks like a great solution for this type of game that doesn&rsquo;t require a whole ton of cloud programming and setup</p>
<p>I haven&rsquo;t made a build of this game public yet due to its unfinished and multiplayer nature - it&rsquo;s not set up with a usable server other than for testing. If I receive interest in playing it from enough people, I&rsquo;ll go back in and package up the single player parts as a tech demo and put a download here.</p>
<p>I learned a lot from this project, both in terms of game code organization and game mechanic design, and I still think it&rsquo;s a great concept. I hope this movement mechanic becomes the basis for a full game in the future and with any luck with the direction software development AI is going I might get that opportunity sooner vs later. About 3 weeks from now, I will be releasing an article on the modern state of AI software development, including a deep dive on some of the latest tools for web and game development, so stay tuned!</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:hockenworks.com,2025-06-23:/the-flapper/</guid>

                
                    <link>https://hockenworks.com/the-flapper/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>The Flapper - A Physical VR Multiplayer Game</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I made my latest Unity project into a multi-application &ldquo;engine&rdquo;. I am now building and releasing two applications from one project. Let me show you how it works.</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="Switching apps in the treekeepers engine"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/treekeepers-app-switcher-1.gif"   style="height: auto; max-width: 720px; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">Switching apps in the treekeepers engine</span>
    
</div>

<p>I did this because I had a lot of assets and code in Treekeepers that would directly translate to a new project I was prototyping. I considered other approaches - git submodules, unity packages, just cloning my old project. After a cost-benefit writeup I decided on this.</p>
<p>Now when I change variables, I edit a class called “Application Definition” for each application, which look like this:</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="An applictaion definition in the editor"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/treekeepers-app-switcher-2.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 400px; width: 100%"   >


    
</div>

<p>My plan is to use this new &ldquo;Engine project&rdquo; to not only update multiple games with common assets and code easily, but also as an instant starting point for any new networked VR/AR prototype.</p>
<p>As I go, any code I refactor to be generic across all projects goes in an Engine folder. Same for prefabs, materials, etc.</p>
<p>This way, if this gets cumbersome in the future, I can make a git submodule out of everything in &ldquo;Engine&rdquo; and import that into a new project.</p>
<p>Here are the scripts. The first runs via the Editor UI and takes variables for anything that needs to be different by project. The second file has the application definition classes you saw in the image above.</p>
<p><a href="https://gist.github.com/hockenmaier/14d50ff0bb90aece1cc6de1b9fc5419d">https://gist.github.com/hockenmaier/14d50ff0bb90aece1cc6de1b9fc5419d</a></p>
<script src="https://gist.github.com/hockenmaier/14d50ff0bb90aece1cc6de1b9fc5419d.js"></script>

<p>The files are free to use. Check them out if you&rsquo;re in a similar situation, but be warned there are still some hard-coded things and references you’ll need to change.</p>
<p>Has anyone taken this approach before? Curious on other&rsquo;s take or approaches to similar problems!</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:hockenworks.com,2023-03-17:/treekeepers-engine/</guid>

                
                    <link>https://hockenworks.com/treekeepers-engine/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Fri, 17 Mar 2023 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Treekeepers Engine</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    





    







    



    























<img  alt="The Treekeepers Puddle Jumper"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/treekeepers_moonlight.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">The Treekeepers Puddle Jumper</span>
    
</div>

<p>Treekeepers VR is a networked VR game where up to 4 players can cooperate to navigate an oversized world and save a giant tree.</p>
<p>Treekeepers is in production on both Quest (standalone VR) and Steam (PC VR) with full cross-play functionality. See the <a href="https://togetheragainstudios.com/treekeepersvr/">Treekeepers VR Website</a> for links to all storefronts and more detail about the game.</p>
<h2 id="heading"></h2>
<h2 id="development">Development</h2>
<p>I began working on Treekeepers in June 2021, and my primary goal was to go significantly deeper into Unity and make a fully networked game. Very few co-op games existed in VR at the time (the area is still lacking), and my intention was to answer this need and create a game that 4 players could cooperate in within a static frame of reference (players move within a ship, and the ship moves through the world) while having to solve coordination challenges together.</p>
<p>I initially designed the project for SteamVR only using the SteamVR SDK but quickly realized that a VR game released only on PC would miss the majority of the userbase, as the (then Oculus) Quest 2 was quickly dominating the market. Treekeepers was a good fit for a mobile platform with its simple low-poly cel-shaded design, so I pivoted to using OpenXR about two months into the project to support VR interactions on both PC and mobile (Android) devices like the Quest 2.</p>
<p>By summer 2022, I had a releasable product, albeit only with one “world” available. I decided to push the game to early access to gather rapid feedback from real players, and after getting approved for both storefronts, Treekeepers released to early access on September 30, 2022.</p>]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:hockenworks.com,2022-10-01:/treekeepers-vr/</guid>

                
                    <link>https://hockenworks.com/treekeepers-vr/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Treekeepers VR</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>Editor&rsquo;s note from 2025:</p>
<p>This article was written as part of the launch of <a href="/treekeepers-vr">Treekeepers VR</a> and the sole proprietorship Together Again Studios, and represents some of my core beliefs of the value of VR and where it&rsquo;s taking us socially. Though I&rsquo;m no longer actively working on Treekeepers, I do hold that VR and AR are truly the &ldquo;endgame&rdquo; of interface and one that could save us from some of the social attitudes caused by social media of today. Enjoy!</p>
</blockquote>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="proofreader GPT"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/together-again-studios.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 400px; width: 100%"   >


    
</div>

<p>With Together Again Studios and Treekeepers VR, we&rsquo;re setting out to solve an insidious problem we see all around us:</p>
<p><strong>Social Media Is Anti-Social</strong></p>
<p>Though Facebook, Instagram, Twitter, and Tiktok all let us share more with each other than ever before, what we are sharing is surprisingly hostile and dismissive of opinions other than our own.</p>
<p>Though Zoom, Hangouts and Teams let us finally see each other from a distance, we still can&rsquo;t speak naturally. We depend on tools like &ldquo;mute&rdquo;. We create meeting upon meeting with different sets of the same group of people. And we don&rsquo;t form the depth of relationships we could in-person.</p>
<p>We as humans are all-too-capable of forming us-versus-them &ldquo;tribes&rdquo; and dehumanizing those who appear too different, and this problem is becoming ever more apparent behind the curtain of the graphical user interface.</p>
<p><strong>Virtual and augmented reality are a way out</strong></p>
<p>In 2016, thanks to pioneers like Palmer Luckey, Michael Abrash, and John Carmack, we suddenly gained access to a technology that removes the curtain and forces us to see eachother. And in 2020, an event that has permanently limited our in-person interaction arose and gave new meaning to this technology.</p>
<p>In VR/AR, voices are no longer text on a screen, taken out of context by our social media bubbles. They&rsquo;re voices again.</p>
<p>In VR/AR, people are no longer user profiles with one image and a tag-line. They&rsquo;re really people, with bodies, faces, and hands that can point and gesture.</p>
<p>In VR/AR, messages are not just &ldquo;public&rdquo;, or &ldquo;direct&rdquo;. Conversations are dynamic, with people physically approaching one another to talk, with people moving in and out of physical groups, and with people attending public conversations together again while still able to have &ldquo;sidebar&rdquo; conversations.</p>
<p>All these abilities we used to have in-person, we have gained again in virtual reality.</p>
<p>Soon, we&rsquo;ll go even further with this technology. We&rsquo;ll be able to make real eye contact with eachother in VR. We&rsquo;ll use AR to invite distant friends and family over to our homes.</p>
<p>And at Together Again, we plan on using these new tools to let people like eachother again.</p>
<p><strong>Treekeepers: Only Possible in VR</strong></p>
<p>Why is Treekeepers a VR Game?</p>
<p><strong>Multiplayer of this depth only works in VR</strong></p>
<p>The challenges in Treekeepers VR hinge on player coordination and quick group decisions - Which weapon should we upgrade? Who&rsquo;s doing which job? Where are we going?</p>
<p>In VR, you gain the ability to gesture and point to enemies and obstacles naturally.</p>
<p>No more &ldquo;Who is the green player?&rdquo; - spend zero mental energy figuring out who you are talking to. Just turn towards them and speak.</p>
<p><strong>Scale is the most fun when you&rsquo;re in the world</strong></p>
<p>We&rsquo;re going to be exploring oversized objects around a gigantic tree. Only VR can get the full benefit of this experience.</p>
<p><strong>VR can be uncomfortable</strong></p>
<p>BUT, experiencing it via a static vehicle which acts as a persistent frame of reference reduces motion sickness.</p>
<p>No need to rotate - gameplay is based on the hot air balloon always facing one direction, and players navigating within it.</p>
<hr>
<p>Check out Treekeepers VR <a href="/treekeepers-vr">here</a></p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:hockenworks.com,2022-08-01:/social-media-is-antisocial/</guid>

                
                    <link>https://hockenworks.com/social-media-is-antisocial/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Social Media Is Anti-Social</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Land War is an 8-player strategy game I developed as a solo project and released to Steam in March of 2019.<br>
This game was intended to have low art requirements and simple interaction rules that result in deep strategic gameplay.</p>
<p>The core concept is that of an ultra-simplified real-time-strategy game. Each player is represented by a color and can grow their territory by moving in any direction. The strategic elements occur when players encounter other players and have to make choices about which side of their land to defend or give up. Players can use the structure of the map and the coordinated action of other players to gain defensible footholds in order to take more area and eventually be the last player on the board.</p>

    <div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
      <iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" loading="eager" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/5Q8PAuWcmQc?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video"></iframe>
    </div>

<p>A full game of the final product released on Steam played on a Windows computer.</p>
<h3 id="development">Development</h3>
<p>I built Land War over the course of 7 months and 400 hours of work using Unity with C#. Though art requirements were intentionally low for a video game, I still had to produce several hundred static graphics and GIFs, and commissioned custom music for the menu and gameplay.</p>
<p>This project is one of my favorite examples of what can be done in relatively little time with a focused vision and a constant eye on scope creep. From the very start, I knew that a key to making compelling software was to flesh out the core concept before all else. This is why I started on the most fundamental strategic interaction of the players and built an MVP version of the game without a menu, sound, art, or even a win condition.</p>
<p>I started the project on a Memorial Day Monday, and by Friday had a rudimentary prototype playable with 8 players on Nintendo Joy-Con controllers paired to a Windows machine via Bluetooth.<br>
This is what the project looked like for my first play-test with other people 5 days in:</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    







    





    



    























<img  alt="Land War 4-day MVP"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/land_war_mvp.gif"   style="height: auto; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">4-player game played with Nintendo Joy-Cons on a build of the game from 5 days into development.</span>
    
</div>

<p>From there, I continued to work on depth and full feature functionality including menus, a tutorial, a map generator, a dynamic scoring and round system, better sound and sprite graphics, different play modes and settings, and support for many controllers. I released the game with very little marketing aside from some Reddit posts and a physical handout at E3 but was happy to receive positive reviews and several hundred purchases of the game.</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    







    





    



    























<img  alt="Player Select screen"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/land_war_player_select.png"   style="height: auto; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">Player Select screen. Supporting menu and player controls across hundreds of controller types was one of the largest unforeseen challenges in developing Land War.</span>
    
</div>

<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    







    





    



    























<img  alt="Settings menu"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/land_war_settings.png"   style="height: auto; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">Settings menu. Most interesting mechanics I found while developing the game were added as options to keep the game interesting here.</span>
    
</div>

<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="E3 marketing material"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/land_war_e3.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 400px; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">The only physical marketing material developed for Land War. Several hundred Steam keys (copies of the game) were handed out during the E3 convention in 2019.</span>
    
</div>


    <div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
      <iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" loading="eager" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/BylKEPF4EeU?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video"></iframe>
    </div>

<p><em>Land War&rsquo;s Steam release announcement trailer.</em></p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:hockenworks.com,2019-03-01:/land-war/</guid>

                
                    <link>https://hockenworks.com/land-war/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Land War</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
