













    
        
    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    







    

    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"  xml:lang="en-us"  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            

            
                
            

            
                <link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/experimental/" rel="self" type="text/html"/>
            
        
            

            

            
                <link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/experimental/rss.xml" rel="alternate" type="application/rss+xml"/>
            
        

        

        

        <description>Recent content</description>

        
            <language>en-us</language>
        

        
            <lastBuildDate>2025-01-01 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</lastBuildDate>
        

        <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/experimental/</link>

        

        <title>Experimental · Tags · Home</title>

        

        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>The advent of general coding AI assistants almost immediately changed how I thought about the hiring process and interviews. And it changed how I talked about it with colleages and my own team.</p>
<p>In the software engineerging world, this mindset shift was pretty easy for me psychologically, because I had always had a bias against the types of coding questions that I personally do badly at - specifically ones that require knowledge or rote memory of specific language capabilities, libraries, syntax. It is not that psychologically easy for everyone, especially those that have developed a core skillset of running &ldquo;leetcode-style&rdquo; interviews. Even before AI, the only types of coding questions I would personally ask were things that simply evaluate whether a candidate is lying or not about whether they can code at all, which was and still is surprisingly common. I have interviewed people that list bullet points like 7 years of Java experience but can&rsquo;t pass a fizz buzz like question, and this was a question I gave out on paper with a closed door and no significant time pressure.</p>
<p>So, when LLMS that could remember any syntax or attribute of any programming language perfectly were released, not only was I excited but I immediately saw that a huge chunk of the programming questions my team and many other software teams liked to ask were essentially irrelevant now, not only because people could cheat on interviews, at least virtually, but because that knowledge simply lost a lot of value overnight.</p>
<p>Over a few conversations with friends and colleagues I began to explore the idea of what this meant generally for the interview process. There are just lots of questions that we ask in every field, it turns out, that are mostly solved by LLMS that have memorized most useful information, even when the original intent of the interview question was to test for experience.</p>
<h1 id="the-build">The Build</h1>
<p>In the summer of 2022 it got to the point where I really wanted to test my hypothesis - that LLMS and continuous audio transcription could let someone with no knowledge answer many interview questions correctly- and after searching for apps on the appstore that did what I was thinking in terms of, I found that surprisingly none did.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m still not sure if that was a legal thing at the time, or if it&rsquo;s hard to get apps that continuously transcribe audio published, but as of 2025 apps like this definitely exist. Some of them have gotten famous and one has gotten its creator expelled from an ivy League for revealing that he used it to ace interviews with some top tech companies. Link for the curious here:</p>
<p><a href="https://cluely.com/">https://cluely.com/</a></p>
<p>But, in mid 2023, these apps were apparently not a thing, so I decided to make a prototype.</p>
<p>My basic requirements were simply something that could continuously transcribe words being spoken in a meeting or over a call, group them up into meaningfully long chunks, and then send those to two different AI passes:</p>
<ol>
<li>An AI pass that would try to make meaningful questions out of the transcribed potential gibberish</li>
<li>An AI pass that would answer those questions</li>
</ol>
<p>My tech stack for this was a little weird, but I know unity well and I don&rsquo;t know other ways of deploying mobile apps well, and this definitely need to be a mobile app if it was going to sit on the phone and continuously transcribe audio. Web has all kinds of restrictions on their APIs and I don&rsquo;t know native mobile web very well anyway.</p>
<p>This was surprisingly easy to do, even in 2023. I ran into a few hiccups mainly around continuous audio transcription, but for an app that I wasn&rsquo;t going to publish that I was directly putting onto my own Android device, I got around that by simply starting up a new audio transcription thread every time one closed.</p>
<div style="display: flex; align-items: center; justify-content: center; gap: 10px; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    







    



    






















<img  alt="the app ui"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/make-us-smarter.jpg"   style="height: auto; max-width: 200px"   >


    
        <span style="font-style: italic;">Super barebones UI just showing the continuously auto-transcribed words, questions derived from those words, and answers to those questions.  This particular screen was grabbed long after my api key had expired and is only here to show the basic output of the app, transcription building continuously in the background and detected questions and answers in the foreground.</span>
    
</div>

<p>And the results were surprisingly compelling. Of course I was using some of the very first versions of GPT-4 and AI is still not perfect, but the main result of this was that occasionally questions were picked up that were not actually implied by the meeting audio, and occasionally real questions were missed. The part that I knew was going to work did indeed work incredibly well: when I simulated some fizz-buzz style questions and there were no major audio transcription issues, the second question-answering AI nailed them and was able to put a succinct script to answer the question on screen within a few seconds.</p>
<p>There was clearly more work to be done on UI and also the flow between the AI passes, and more agentic APIs of today could definitely do this all more seamlessly.</p>
<p>But for me, my question was answered: My hunch was right and we should definitely not be asking questions about basic constructs of programming languages or simple scripts in interviews anymore.</p>
<p>I open sourced the project which is a pretty small unity build, and it&rsquo;s a unity version from a couple of years ago now but anyone is happy to look through and modify the code anyway they want:</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/hockenmaier/make-us-smarter">https://github.com/hockenmaier/make-us-smarter</a></p>
<h1 id="interviewing-today">Interviewing Today</h1>
<p>This whole experience and a whole slew of interviews that came building my team the last year have me settled on an interview approach that I think is infallible (for now). And it doesn&rsquo;t require sending someone home with a project or any of that stuff that good candidates often don&rsquo;t even consider. I heard about a version of this technique on Twitter so can&rsquo;t take full credit here:</p>
<p>What I do is ask candidates to bring some code that they have written, regardless of language of framework, and I simply walk through it with them in the interview. It only takes 15 minutes or so, and it usually gets much better conversation going than sample interviewing questions do. It leans on the fact that you need an interviewer that can mostly understand most programming projects, but it cannot be faked with any LLM assistance. Llm written code is pretty obvious for one, much better commented and differently organized than most humans would write, but even if the code was very sneakily written AI code, having a human go through and explain the parts that they thought were clever defeats the purpose of cheating with AI anyway.</p>
<p>So there you go, little tidbit from what I&rsquo;ve learned. I hope no one out there that I know is using these apps to cheat on interviews, but we all need to be wise to the fact that it is trivially easy to do so, and we should shift focus to testing for the qualities that actually matter in the era of AI.</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2025-01-01:/my-experiments-with-ai-cheating/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/my-experiments-with-ai-cheating/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>My Experiments with AI Cheating</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[
    <div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
      <iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" loading="eager" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/q_1itpdiPb4?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video"></iframe>
    </div>

<p>The &ldquo;Human Joystick&rdquo; is an experimental VR movement system in which the player moves through the virtual environment by changing their physical location within their VR &ldquo;playspace&rdquo;.</p>
<p>A demo of the human joystick movement system, showing how the system can work on flat surfaces or terrain.</p>
<p>This was my first barebones VR project. Though I knew Unity going in, VR and 3D games in general have a lot of unique aspects that I wanted to learn about while trying to solve an actual problem, rather than following tutorials or demos online.</p>
<p>VR has some adoption problems in its current state. We all know of some of the main problems- the clunky headset, the nausea issues, and of course the pricetag. But one major problem that you don&rsquo;t really notice until you get into it, is the lack of a good solution for virtual movement.</p>
<p>I had been wondering about &ldquo;the human joystick&rdquo; as a potential a solution to this particular problem ever since getting into consumer VR in 2016.</p>
<p>In most modern VR systems, the player can move physically around the room if they choose. Some applications and games depend on this - they put you in a small space and rely on your physical movement in order to reach different areas and interact with things. But games that provide a more traditional sense of scale and allow players to move through large worlds cannot rely on physical motion, because their users are constrained by physical space. Because of this, you see all kinds of &ldquo;artificial&rdquo; locomotion systems in order to let people move around - some just like traditional 2D games that let users &ldquo;slide&rdquo; their playspaces around the world using a joystick, and others that adopt teleportation mechanics. Neither feel very natural as compared to actually walking, and some can be downright sickening.</p>
<p>My goal with this project was to solve this problem with a mixture of physical and artificial movement.</p>
<p>It works like this: When the player is standing near the center of their playspace, physical VR movement applies. The player can move around and interact with things with their actual bodies. But once the player moves further from the center, the plaspace starts to move with them in the same direction as the vector from the center of the player&rsquo;s space to their current position. This allows for some of the benefits that physical movement experiences have, while allowing the players to more naturally move through an infinite amount of space.</p>
<p>I experimented with several speeds, both static and scaling with the distance between the center and the player. I also experimented with the size of the physical movement &ldquo;deadzone&rdquo; and with vertical and constrained movement across hills, valleys, and buildings.</p>
<hr>
<table>
  <thead>
      <tr>
          <th style="text-align: center">


















<div class="paige-image">
    




























    



    

    
        

        

        
    
        

        

        
    
        

        
            

    



    







    





    



    






















<img   class="img-fluid "  crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/human_joystick_centered.jpg"   style="display:block; height: auto; margin:0 auto; width: 60%"   >


</div>
</th>
          <th style="text-align: left"><em>View from the player&rsquo;s perspective looking at the guides at his feet. With the white dot in the red deadzone, the player isn&rsquo;t moving.</em></th>
      </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
      <tr>
          <td style="text-align: center">


















<div class="paige-image">
    




























    



    

    
        

        

        
    
        

        

        
    
        

        
            

    



    







    





    



    






















<img   class="img-fluid "  crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/human_joystick_moving.jpg"   style="display:block; height: auto; margin:0 auto; width: 60%"   >


</div>
</td>
          <td style="text-align: left"><strong><em>When the white dot is in the green area, the player moves in that direction. Here I am moving forward and left at about half of max speed.</em></strong></td>
      </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<hr>
<p>Eventually I found some good default values and the system worked, but there were some unforeseen problems: First, it was more difficult to center yourself within the playspace without looking at the visible guides I put at the player&rsquo;s feet than I expected. Second and more importantly, when you were already moving in one direction, it was not as simple as I thought to start moving in another direction accurately without fully returning to center, which was an immersion breaker.</p>
<p>Ultimately I put the project up for others to view but have not expanded it into a full experience or released it on any marketplaces. Feel free to download the Unity project and try it on your own VR setup if you&rsquo;re curious.</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2020-01-01:/human-joystick/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/human-joystick/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Human Joystick VR</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p><strong>Raspberry Pi Control Panel</strong> is a hardware project I designed in 2016 to manage home automation systems. The project involved designing a custom 3D-printed case for a Raspberry Pi microcomputer with a touchscreen interface.</p>
<p>Links:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/hockenmaier/RaspberryPiControlPanel">GitHub</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:2524560">Thingiverse</a></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>I created this panel display in 2026 to control much of the home automation I used in my Studio City apartment. Mainly a hardware project, I designed and 3D-printed a case and frame for the touchscreen and raspberry pi microcomputer in order to mount them to the wall. The software running the control panel is SaaS, but I did write a custom html wrapper to control the orientation and settings of the site, which is available on the github linked above.</p>
<p>Update in 2025: This panel is still my main view into my home automation in my new house in Sherman Oaks, almost 10 years in with no modification!</p>
<p>Here&rsquo;s a video to see the panel in action:</p>
<h2 id="hahahugoshortcode176s0hbhb">
    <div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
      <iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" loading="eager" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/iFGmm-ijJvE?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video"></iframe>
    </div>
</h2>
<p>Feel free to explore the linked repositories for schematics and source code.</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2016-01-01:/raspberry-pi-panel/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/raspberry-pi-panel/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Raspberry Pi Control Panel</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
