













    
        
    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    







    

    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"  xml:lang="en-us"  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            

            
                
            

            
                <link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/video-games/" rel="self" type="text/html"/>
            
        
            

            

            
                <link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/video-games/rss.xml" rel="alternate" type="application/rss+xml"/>
            
        

        

        

        <description>Recent content</description>

        
            <language>en-us</language>
        

        
            <lastBuildDate>2025-06-23 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</lastBuildDate>
        

        <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/video-games/</link>

        

        <title>Video Games · Tags · hockenworks</title>

        

        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>&ldquo;The Flapper&rdquo; is a project that spawned out of a simple VR movement mechanic test that I had had in my head for a while, which turned out to be surprisingly fun! The idea is to flap your arms to fly - and have it be a multiplayer battle to really get people moving.</p>
<p>In order to start working on this game, because there was so much standard VR code that I had to write for tree keepers, I decided to make a sort of engine out of tree keepers and work off of that rather than start from scratch. That let me tie in some of the nice associated graphics, music and sound effects I had made, and a bunch of other helper functions and things I use for things like the camera following around the character, how I deal with collisions, a bunch of netcode, etc.</p>
<p>You can see my more detailed post about that engine here: <a href="/treekeepers-engine">Treekeepers Engine</a></p>
<h2 id="core-mechanic--gameplay">Core Mechanic &amp; Gameplay</h2>
<p>Most of the start of this game was just tuning the movement mechanic, which borrowed from some physics realities and some elements I made up to make flapping feel good. But, the essential idea was that each arm would generate unique thrust in the direction it was moving with an exponenthel applied to how fast it was moving. It&rsquo;s hard to describe any native VR mechanic with words and videos only, but to me and the folks I demoed it to; it felt &ldquo;right&rdquo; for how flying should work if you did it by flapping your arms. I had a ton of fun just jetting around the obstacle courses I made for myself.</p>
<p>My idea for this other than just the mechanic was to make a sort of gorilla tag-esque multiplayer game where players would fly around and try to pop each other&rsquo;s balloons in a NES balloon fight {link} style. Ideally something like 15 to 20 people would be in a lobby flying around and trying to pop each other.</p>
<p>Like gorilla tag I didn&rsquo;t want anyone to have to &ldquo;sit out&rdquo; of the game, so it&rsquo;s essentially a deathmatch where the player who pops the most balloons wins, and is also visible who&rsquo;s winning, because they also gain the balloons that they pop. In some playtests players would have 20 or 30 balloons on their head. This was my clever idea of adding a built-in rubber-band effect to the gameplay as well, since having more balloons over your head made you a bigger target to pop. The gameplay worked well - but I never quite got the game to a place with netcode and networking engine where multiplayer felt seamless enough.</p>
<p>Here’s a video of one of the later states of the game, where I have it fully networked and am testing with friends, though it still has a few bugs here:</p>

    <div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
      <iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" loading="eager" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Vxn8rDOZ7dU?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video"></iframe>
    </div>

<h2 id="today">Today</h2>
<p>I stopped working on this project after about 3 months. It turned out that flying alone with this mechanic was very compelling (and also a great workout!) but the networking engine I had used for Teeekeepers, Photon, was not up to task for how low latency a competitive game needed to be. Treekeepers was four-player co-op so photon was just fine.</p>
<p>In the future I might pick this one back up (or maybe have an AI agent pick it up for me depending on how that goes) using space-time DB {link}</p>
<p>which looks like a great solution for this type of game that doesn&rsquo;t require a whole ton of cloud programming and setup.</p>
<p>You can try a build of the game here:</p>
<p>{Download of latest build}</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2025-06-23:/the-flapper/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/the-flapper/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>The Flapper - A Physical VR Multiplayer Game</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m <a href="/about-me">Brian Hockenmaier</a>, and this site is full of things I build and write about. I love making games and things with VR and AI. And I love DIY projects, especially ones involving programming, engineering and 3D modeling. Some of this has been cross or back-posted from my <a href="https://www.thingiverse.com/hockenmaier/designs">thingiverse</a>, <a href="https://github.com/hockenmaier">github</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/hockenmaier/">linkedin</a>, and other places, but it all lives here permanently.</p>
<p>This is an evolution of <a href="old-site/index.html">my previous site last updated in 2022, which I still keep inside this one</a> for posterity and for the AIs of the future to know more about me. I like it not because of the content as much as because it was a fully custom js and html site with no framework&hellip; and I think it&rsquo;s sort of fun and funny that it was like this.</p>
<p>All work and opinions here are my own, not my employer&rsquo;s.</p>
<h1 id="why-im-making-it">Why I&rsquo;m making it</h1>
<p>I&rsquo;m creating this website in 2025 after starting a family as well as my first full-time role in AI. It&rsquo;s an effort to clean up my website&rsquo;s focus, move several disparate collections into one place, and emphasize what I truly care about. I wanted it to be easier to add content, CMS style, and I wanted a space to occasionally post written content, too.</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="the hockenworks homepage"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/hockenworks.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 720px; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">This webpage, if you hadn&#39;t noticed</span>
    
</div>

<p>A big reason I&rsquo;m doing this now is that, after listening to the Dwarkesh podcast with Gwern, I was convinced I really should have more of a record for future AIs to learn about me. I really don’t have a social media presence, nor do I want one, and over the years I have had a lot of projects and writing that I have unnecessarily kept private. AGI or not, there are non-artificial intelligences that may be interested one day. Talking to you, Alice :) When I started this website, your cousin Lily kept asking where you were and didn&rsquo;t seem to get the concept that you currently occupied the same space as Kaitlin.</p>
<p>I love some of the 2010s era blogs, and though mine is not going to be nearly as longform, nearly as focused on prose, or nearly as articulate, two of the sites I&rsquo;m trying to take inspiration from are <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/about/">Slate Star Codex</a> and <a href="https://gwern.net/about">Gwern&rsquo;s website</a> which are definitely advising on style here. Other than the fact that mine is also a game.</p>
<hr>
<h1 id="etymology-of-hockenworks">Etymology of &ldquo;hockenworks&rdquo;</h1>
<p><strong>Hockenmaier</strong> is a great name. I&rsquo;ve always loved it. Not just because it’s unique and has my favorite number of letters, but because of its meaning, at least my family’s “folk-etymology” for it.</p>
<p>You have:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Hocken</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Which can roughly translate to “sitting down, squatting, settling, idling”.</p>
<p>And then you have:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Maier</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Which has many different spellings, and ours has southern German roots, but all &ldquo;Meyer&rdquo; names come from the latin root &ldquo;maior&rdquo; meaning steward, administrator, or more generally &ldquo;worker&rdquo;</p>
<p>My family often puts these two ideas together as &ldquo;Lazy Worker,&rdquo; which is very on-brand for our sense of humor, but I think it&rsquo;s not just funny, but true.</p>
<p>“Lazy Worker” is perfect for someone who wants to get a lot done, especially in software engineering. We only have so many hours, and the best lives are lived restricting the number of hours spent on work that isn&rsquo;t done with people you love. So you better be efficient about it. You better be lazy. There are <a href="https://blog.codinghorror.com/how-to-be-lazy-dumb-and-successful/?utm_source=chatgpt.com">many</a> <a href="https://xkcd.com/1205/?utm_source=chatgpt.com">correct</a> <a href="https://thethreevirtues.com/">takes</a> out there on the value of being lazy when programming.</p>
<p>Now that we are starting to have AI, it&rsquo;s even better. A lazy worker like myself will not only avoid unnecessary work, but will delegate all that can be delegated to the new AI workers that are multiplying in our computers. That makes the &ldquo;steward&rdquo; connotation of &ldquo;Maier&rdquo; all the more fitting.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m proud to be the lazy worker, and this site is all about sharing my lazy works. My <em>hockenworks</em>.</p>
<hr>
<h1 id="ball-machine---the-game">Ball Machine - The Game</h1>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="A ball machine"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/bubble4.gif"   style="height: auto; max-width: 720px; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">The Ball Machine</span>
    
</div>

<p>Most blogs and personal websites are a bit boring. I think that is because most professionals consider what they do &ldquo;for work&rdquo; a bit boring by its nature, and don&rsquo;t necessarily make a concerted effort to have fun with it.</p>
<p>I have always tried to be the opposite, and with kids coming I am trying to make a bigger effort than ever to have fun whatever I&rsquo;m doing. Which is often working, in some way or another.</p>
<p>So for my website, I wanted it to be intentionally fun. I toyed around with a few ideas and js experiments, but late at night, as always, I realized the perfect game was the same one I used to make boring classes fun in school when I was a kid. That game consisted of the book of graph paper I always kept with me, plus a pencil, a ruler, and a protractor. I was a bit obsessed with physics simulation at the time. My favorite game in church growing up, where I was often daydreaming and looking at the huge arched ceiling, was to imagine a laser coming out of my line of sight and bouncing off of every surface in the room, to see where it would end up. This graph paper game I played was similar.</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="balls everywhere"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/this-website-ball-machine-1.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 720px; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">Some of my early playtests got pretty chaotic</span>
    
</div>

<p>I would start by making a &ldquo;spawn point&rdquo; usually near the top left of the page, where balls would start falling. I would draw out the path of these balls a few inches from each other along their path with &ldquo;speed lines&rdquo; to denote which way they were going, and how fast. Then I would add platforms, trampolines, loops, curves, &ldquo;booster&rdquo; acceleration zones, jumps, machines that would disassemble and reassemble balls, and so many other things - usually something new each sheet of paper - and I would end up with a Rube Goldberg machine of balls flying all around the sheet. The only goal was to fill the sheet with more ridiculous paths.</p>
<p>I started calling the sheets my &ldquo;ball machines&rdquo;. I wish I still had some of these drawings. I remember them being quite intricate.. I must have reserved English class for them.</p>
<p>So, to honor kid Brian, I am making my website a permanent ball machine. I hope you have fun with it and see all there is to unlock!</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="balls everywhere"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/waves2.gif"   style="height: auto; max-width: 300px; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">Even on the limited phone version, you can create some productive chaos</span>
    
</div>

<h2 id="how-its-made">How it&rsquo;s made</h2>
<p>I don&rsquo;t typically make complicated things like this with JavaScript. So when I found the perfect physics engine for the game - <a href="https://brm.io/matter-js/">matter.js</a> - I knew I would need help from our new little assistants. And though this game is a bit too structured to call it &ldquo;vibe coded&rdquo; - at times, it was close.</p>
<p>I ended up making my own tool called <a href="/context-caddy">Context Caddy</a> to help me with it. Part of the reason I leaned so hard into this is because I&rsquo;m always trying to push the limits of current AI, and I hadn&rsquo;t built a game since the GPT-4 days (I&rsquo;ll post about that soon). The new thinking models are truly a step above GPT-4 (this was mostly done with o3 and its minis) but they&rsquo;re still way too eager to write duplicate code, and they still don&rsquo;t &ldquo;get&rdquo; the structure of your project a lot of the time, especially with visual and physical things like this. Still, they were a great help here.</p>
<p>This game is made extra complicated by the fact that it runs on top of <a href="https://gohugo.io/">Hugo</a>, which is the static site generator behind the &ldquo;content&rdquo; part of this site. This probably doubled or tripled the effort of making this game. But, the balls in the &ldquo;ball machines&rdquo; of my youth would interact with my text notes and drawings, so this ball machine needed to do so as well.</p>
<p>There is quite a bit going on under the hood to make these two very distinct types of development projects work in tandem, and for both of them to work well. The Ball Machine would love to eat up all of the resources and make the site content unresponsive, and the content was quite a lot to dynamically build physical bodies and colliders around. I like the end result. But I like it a lot better on desktop, where the two can really interact, so I think you should play it on a real computer with a mouse.</p>
<h2 id="how-to-play">How to Play</h2>
<span
  style="
    float: left;
    width: 150px;
    margin: 0 1rem 1rem 0;
    display: inline-block;
  "
>
  




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="ball chute"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/ball-chute-hatch-1.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 200px; width: 100%"   >

 
  <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem">
    This tube creates balls every time you click it
  </span>
  
</span>

<p>The ball machine on this site is a gamified version of my graph paper drawings as a kid. Each time you load a page, you&rsquo;ll see a little pneumatic delivery tube on the top right of the screen.</p>
<p>When you spawn your first ball, you&rsquo;ll see a few things appear. First - you&rsquo;ll find a goal     <span
  style="
    display: inline-block;
    width: 40px;
    margin: 0 1rem 0 0;
    vertical-align: middle;
    text-align: left;
  "
>
  




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="the goal"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/goal.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 40px; width: 100%"   >

 
</span>
 somewhere randomly on the page. Find a way to get the balls you spawn into that goal. But there is a bit of a trick - balls start out being worth 1 coin and accumulate another coin in value every two seconds. So, the longer you can keep balls around, the more they will be worth when going into the goals, and this might get more and more challenging as your drawings take up more of the screen and balls start bouncing off of each other.</p>
<p><strong>Keep Clicking!</strong></p>
<p>It&rsquo;s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Incremental_game">a clicker game</a> - start by manually clicking the pneumatic delivery tube to spawn balls, but as you accumulate coins you&rsquo;ll be able to unlock different drawables and things that will let you accumulate more coins faster. If it feels like it&rsquo;s taking a while to make coins and unlock things, try playing around more with how the balls interact with the content, and use all of the tools you can draw. The site also works across multiple pages. And if all else fails&hellip; just give it time. This is a clicker game after all, so waiting is always a strategy! There is plenty to read while you wait.</p>
<p>It works best when you&rsquo;re on desktop, working on one tab at a time.</p>
<p> </p>
<blockquote>
<p>Quick Disclaimer: This game is designed for big screens, ideally desktop computers. If you must play on a phone, try landscape mode!</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 id="controls">Controls</h3>
<p><span
  style="
    display: inline-block;
    width: 100px;
    margin: 0 1rem 0 0;
    vertical-align: middle;
    text-align: left;
  "
>
  




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="line toggle"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/line-mode.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 200px; width: 100%"   >

 
</span>

<span
  style="
    display: inline-block;
    width: 100px;
    margin: 0 1rem 0 0;
    vertical-align: middle;
    text-align: left;
  "
>
  




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="curved line toggle"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/curve-mode.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 200px; width: 100%"   >

 
</span>

<span
  style="
    display: inline-block;
    width: 100px;
    margin: 0 1rem 0 0;
    vertical-align: middle;
    text-align: left;
  "
>
  




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="compactor toggle"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/compactor-mode.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 200px; width: 100%"   >

 
</span>
</p>
<p>To start drawing your ball machine, you need to <kbd>Left Click</kbd> or <kbd>Tap</kbd> one of these drawable toggles in the main UI (top left of the screen)</p>
<p>When you have a drawable tool toggled on, you won&rsquo;t be able to click other links on the site. You&rsquo;ll see this visually indicated when you choose them. Unselect the currently selected tool in order to see it</p>
<p>Every drawable item (lines, launchers, and more) uses the following mechanics:</p>
<p> </p>
<h4 id="drawing-on-desktop">Drawing on Desktop</h4>
<p><strong>Spawn Balls:</strong> <kbd>Left Click</kbd> on the pneumatic spawner tube</p>
<p><strong>Draw Objects:</strong> <kbd>Left Click</kbd> and drag to see a preview, then <kbd>Left Click </kbd> to place</p>
<ul>
<li>Some drawables have a second action, like curved lines, that is previewed after the second click and confirmed with a third click</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Cancel Drawing</strong> After you&rsquo;ve started a line or other drawing but before you&rsquo;ve clicked again to confirm, <kbd>Right Click</kbd> to cancel it.</p>
<p><strong>Delete Objects:</strong> Hover over a drawn item and <kbd>Right Click</kbd> to delete it, getting 50% of your money back</p>
<p> </p>
<h4 id="drawing-on-mobile">Drawing on Mobile</h4>
<p><span
  style="
    color: #ff0040;
    font-family: 'Arial Black', Arial, sans-serif;
    font-size: 20px;
  "
>
   Mobile Scroll Lock Warning:
</span>
 On Mobile, scrolling the page is blocked while you&rsquo;re drawing to allow you to draw lines in any direction.</p>
<p>You will need to untoggle your selected tool before you can scroll or click links.</p>
<p>If your phone has gesture controls to reload, go back or forward, or other browser things, you should disable them if you really want to play on your phone. Or, just play on desktop!</p>
<p><strong>Spawn Balls:</strong> <kbd>Tap</kbd> on the pneumatic spawner tube</p>
<p><strong>Draw Objects:</strong> <kbd>Touch and Drag</kbd> to see a preview, then <kbd>Release</kbd> to place</p>
<ul>
<li>Some drawables have a second action, like curved lines, that is previewed and confirmed on the next touch-and-drag.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Cancel Drawing</strong> After you&rsquo;ve started a line or other drawing but before you&rsquo;ve released to confirm, go back to where you started and release around there to cancel it. The threshold to cancel is within 25 pixels of where you started.</p>
<p><strong>Delete Objects:</strong> <kbd>Tap and hold</kbd> an object to delete it, getting 50% of your money back. You will see it pulse before it deletes.</p>
<p> </p>
<h4 id="the-auto-clicker">The Auto-Clicker</h4>
<span
  style="
    display: inline-block;
    width: 100px;
    margin: 0 1rem 0 0;
    vertical-align: middle;
    text-align: left;
  "
>
  




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="auto clicker"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/auto-clicker.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 200px; width: 100%"   >

 
</span>

<p>This is the autoclicker button that lets you pay to auto-spawn balls.</p>
<p><kbd>Left Click</kbd> or <kbd>Tap</kbd> to buy the first auto-clicker, or upgrade it.</p>
<p><kbd>Right Click</kbd> on desktop or <kbd>Tap and hold</kbd> on mobile to refund and downgrade it to the previous click frequency.</p>
<p> </p>
<h3 id="money--other-hints">Money &amp; Other Hints</h3>
<p>You&rsquo;ll quickly find ways to lengthen your Rube-Goldberg Machines and build up value before you send balls into the goal. Your money is displayed on the coin counter next to the ball spawner.</p>
<p> </p>
<p><span
  style="
    display: inline-block;
    width: 100px;
    margin: 0 1rem 0 0;
    vertical-align: middle;
    text-align: left;
  "
>
  




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="dotted line toggle"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/everything-has-a-price.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 200px; width: 100%"   >

 
</span>
<strong>Everything has a price!</strong></p>
<p>If you can&rsquo;t draw an item, you probably can&rsquo;t afford it. You&rsquo;ll see your coin counter flash red in the UI when this happens.</p>
<p><span
  style="
    display: inline-block;
    width: 100px;
    margin: 0 1rem 0 0;
    vertical-align: middle;
    text-align: left;
  "
>
  




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="dotted line toggle"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/dotted-line-mode.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 200px; width: 100%"   >

 
</span>
<strong>You get what you pay for&hellip;</strong></p>
<p>If you ever find yourself out of money, these dotted lines are free. They are not saved permanently like other lines and they go away after 50 balls hit them.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>❌ A couple of things to watch out for when building ball machines:</p>
<ul>
<li>Balls have to be moving at all times. If they sit still for too long, they are considered dead and will poof out of existence.</li>
<li>This applies to balls hitting the goal, too. If your balls aren&rsquo;t moving much when they hit the target, they won&rsquo;t go in.
So keep your balls moving!</li>
</ul>
<p>😵 If you have a good run going, but it descends into chaos, it can be hard to recover. That&rsquo;s what the <kbd>Erase Balls</kbd> button above the draw tools is for!</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Each post on this site will be a slightly different randomized game! Try making ball machines on multiple pages at once. Your work will be saved in realtime, and you can make money even on pages you&rsquo;re not currently playing on.</p>
<p><span
  style="
    display: inline-block;
    width: 100px;
    margin: 0 1rem 0 0;
    vertical-align: middle;
    text-align: left;
  "
>
  




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="dotted line toggle"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/page-revenue.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 200px; width: 100%"   >

 
</span>
 These counters display how much <strong>sustainable</strong> coin revenue per second you&rsquo;re making on this page, and how much other pages you&rsquo;re not currently working on are contributing. Any balls that are spawned automatically and continuously travel through your contraption to hit the goal will be averaged into the top amount. When you visit other pages, you will keep making this money - that&rsquo;s what the &ldquo;Other Pages&rdquo; revenue displays.</p>
<p>Your progress is saved to your device because your contraptions will be highly dependent on the screen size the site renders to.</p>
<p>The game works a bit differently on desktop and mobile, and the best experience is really on desktop - so try on a computer if you can! If on mobile, flip to landscape.</p>
<h3 id="the-end-of-the-game">The End of the Game</h3>
<p>Right now, the Ball Machine doesn&rsquo;t end, but you will be surprised the amount of money you can make across the whole site! Eventually, there will be other ways to spend coins on this site and potentially &ldquo;beat&rdquo; the ball machine. The late game items change the game in very interesting ways! I hope you make some fun machines on my website.</p>
<p>You&rsquo;ll know you&rsquo;ve done about all there is to do by tracking the achievements below!</p>
<h4 id="achievements">Achievements</h4>
<div id="achievements-list"></div>
<script>
document.addEventListener('DOMContentLoaded', function(){
  var container = document.getElementById('achievements-list');
  if(!container){ console.error('Achievements container missing'); return; }
  try {
    var defs = (window.App && App.Achievements && App.Achievements.defs) || [];
    var unlocked = JSON.parse(localStorage.getItem('game.achievementsUnlocked') || '{}');
    var yes = 'http:\/\/localhost:1313\/images\/achievement-yes.png';
    var no = 'http:\/\/localhost:1313\/images\/achievement-no.png';
    if(!defs.length){
      console.warn('No achievements definitions found');
    }
    defs.forEach(function(a){
      var row = document.createElement('div');
      var img = document.createElement('img');
      var got = unlocked[a.id];
      img.src = got ? yes : no;
      img.alt = got ? 'Unlocked' : 'Locked';
      img.style.width = '16px';
      img.style.height = '16px';
      img.style.marginRight = '4px';
      row.appendChild(img);
      var b = document.createElement('b');
      b.textContent = a.name;
      row.appendChild(b);
      if(got){
        row.appendChild(document.createTextNode(' – ' + a.desc));
      }
      container.appendChild(row);
    });
    if (location.hash && location.hash.includes('achievements')) {
      var anchor = document.getElementById('achievements');
      if (anchor) {
        setTimeout(function(){ anchor.scrollIntoView(); }, 50);
      }
    }
  } catch(e){
    console.error('Failed to render achievements', e);
    container.textContent = 'Error loading achievements.';
  }
});
</script>

<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<h3 id="resetting-the-game">Resetting the Game</h3>
<span
  style="
    color: #ff0040;
    font-family: 'Arial Black', Arial, sans-serif;
    font-size: 20px;
  "
>
   WARNING! Don't navigate to the below page unless you're sure you want to reset the ball machine game
</span>

<p>Resetting will erase all of your drawings on all pages and reset your goal locations, unlocks, coins and everything else.</p>
<p>If you are thinking about doing this because you want to try on another device, you don&rsquo;t need to, because progress is already saved to your device. The only reason to do this is to have a fresh start on this device.</p>
<p>Navigate <a href="/reset-ball-machine">here</a> and click reset to do that.</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2025-05-28:/this-website/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/this-website/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>This Website</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>If you like retro video games and also drinking things, you&rsquo;re in luck!
Print them for your living room! Print them for your friends!
I hope these characters remind you of some of your favorite series.</p>
<p>I returned to <a href="/8-bit-coasters">this project</a> after 10 years to make more coasters, including some designs for multi-plastic printers and a reinforced 4-coaster holder!</p>
<div class="paige-row-wide">
  <div style="display:grid; grid-template-columns:repeat(2, minmax(0,1fr)); gap:15px;">
      






























    













    



    






















<img   class="rounded-3 w-100"  crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/2023-8-bit-set-2.jpg"    >


      






























    













    



    






















<img   class="rounded-3 w-100"  crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/2023-8-bit-set-1.jpg"    >

</div>
</div>

<div class="paige-row-wide">
  <div style="display:grid; grid-template-columns:repeat(2, minmax(0,1fr)); gap:15px;">
      






























    













    



    






















<img   class="rounded-3 w-100"  crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/2023-8-bit-set-3.jpg"    >


      






























    













    



    






















<img   class="rounded-3 w-100"  crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/2023-8-bit-set-4.jpg"    >

</div>
</div>

<p>It was super fun returning to this project! I was able to fix a few things that I had noticed failing over the years, like the new reinforced sides to the &ldquo;? Block&rdquo; holder. Now that multi-color prints are proliferating more widely, I&rsquo;m hoping people can use the new colored files - they really pop with the Silk+Matte PLA combo I used here. Links to those filaments:</p>
<p><a href="https://us.store.bambulab.com/products/pla-matte">https://us.store.bambulab.com/products/pla-matte</a>
<a href="https://us.store.bambulab.com/products/pla-silk-upgrade">https://us.store.bambulab.com/products/pla-silk-upgrade</a></p>
<p>Download on Thingiverse:
<a href="https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:6158533">https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:6158533</a></p>
<p>If you have a Bambulab printer, there is an included .3mf file with coloring and print settings ready to go!</p>
<p>Here&rsquo;s the original thing: <a href="https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:115150">https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:115150</a></p>
<p>Also pictured (third to last picture) are 18 of my favorite remixed coasters from my original thing. Find them in the remixes of the link above!</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve included an openscad file for customizing multiple sizes of pixel art for your own designs, based on the awesome customizable version by ahtly here:
<a href="http://www.thingiverse.com/thing:139754">http://www.thingiverse.com/thing:139754</a></p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2023-08-06:/8-bit-coasters-10-year/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/8-bit-coasters-10-year/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Sun, 06 Aug 2023 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>8-Bit Videogame Coasters, 10 Year Anniversary Edition</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I made my latest Unity project into a multi-application &ldquo;engine&rdquo;. I am now building and releasing two applications from one project. Let me show you how it works.</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="Switching apps in the treekeepers engine"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/treekeepers-app-switcher-1.gif"   style="height: auto; max-width: 720px; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">Switching apps in the treekeepers engine</span>
    
</div>

<p>I did this because I had a lot of assets and code in Treekeepers that would directly translate to a new project I was prototyping. I considered other approaches - git submodules, unity packages, just cloning my old project. After a cost-benefit writeup I decided on this.</p>
<p>Now when I change variables, I edit a class called “Application Definition” for each application, which look like this:</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="An applictaion definition in the editor"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/treekeepers-app-switcher-2.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 400px; width: 100%"   >


    
</div>

<p>My plan is to use this new &ldquo;Engine project&rdquo; to not only update multiple games with common assets and code easily, but also as an instant starting point for any new networked VR/AR prototype.</p>
<p>As I go, any code I refactor to be generic across all projects goes in an Engine folder. Same for prefabs, materials, etc.</p>
<p>This way, if this gets cumbersome in the future, I can make a git submodule out of everything in &ldquo;Engine&rdquo; and import that into a new project.</p>
<p>Here are the scripts. The first runs via the Editor UI and takes variables for anything that needs to be different by project. The second file has the application definition classes you saw in the image above.</p>
<p><a href="https://gist.github.com/hockenmaier/14d50ff0bb90aece1cc6de1b9fc5419d">https://gist.github.com/hockenmaier/14d50ff0bb90aece1cc6de1b9fc5419d</a></p>
<script src="https://gist.github.com/hockenmaier/14d50ff0bb90aece1cc6de1b9fc5419d.js"></script>

<p>The files are free to use. Check them out if you&rsquo;re in a similar situation, but be warned there are still some hard-coded things and references you’ll need to change.</p>
<p>Has anyone taken this approach before? Curious on other&rsquo;s take or approaches to similar problems!</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2023-03-17:/treekeepers-engine/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/treekeepers-engine/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Fri, 17 Mar 2023 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Treekeepers Engine</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been playing around with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neural_radiance_field">neural radiance fields</a> (NeRFs) lately and thought a fun way to explore them would be flying through them in the Treekeepers “Puddle Jumper” in true scale.</p>

    <div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
      <iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" loading="eager" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/QguH3aK90Ck?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video"></iframe>
    </div>

<p>Of course, you lose a lot of the draw of NeRFs when you export the model into a 3d engine because it has to flatten all the textures and lighting, and also Luma AI cuts off 3D model exports as a jarring cube</p>
<p>But still - I was amazed at how well just applying a day/night lighting cycle and mesh colliders worked with this. Projectile and enemy physics played well too.</p>
<p>It’s still early days, but I could see 3D model generation from this tech getting a lot better and forming the basis for some really interesting user-generated content in the future!</p>
<p>Neat stuff - big thanks to Luma AI for the free toolset.</p>]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2023-02-01:/nerfs/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/nerfs/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>NeRFs in VR</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    







    



    






















<img  alt="The Treekeepers Puddle Jumper"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/treekeepers_moonlight.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">The Treekeepers Puddle Jumper</span>
    
</div>

<p>Treekeepers VR is a networked VR game where up to 4 players can cooperate to navigate an oversized world and save a giant tree.</p>
<p>Treekeepers is in production on both Quest (standalone VR) and Steam (PC VR) with full cross-play functionality. See the <a href="https://togetheragainstudios.com/treekeepersvr/">Treekeepers VR Website</a> for links to all storefronts and more detail about the game.</p>
<h2 id="heading"></h2>
<h2 id="development">Development</h2>
<p>I began working on Treekeepers in June 2021, and my primary goal was to go significantly deeper into Unity and make a fully networked game. Very few co-op games existed in VR at the time (the area is still lacking), and my intention was to answer this need and create a game that 4 players could cooperate in within a static frame of reference (players move within a ship, and the ship moves through the world) while having to solve coordination challenges together.</p>
<p>I initially designed the project for SteamVR only using the SteamVR SDK but quickly realized that a VR game released only on PC would miss the majority of the userbase, as the (then Oculus) Quest 2 was quickly dominating the market. Treekeepers was a good fit for a mobile platform with its simple low-poly cel-shaded design, so I pivoted to using OpenXR about two months into the project to support VR interactions on both PC and mobile (Android) devices like the Quest 2.</p>
<p>By summer 2022, I had a releasable product, albeit only with one “world” available. I decided to push the game to early access to gather rapid feedback from real players, and after getting approved for both storefronts, Treekeepers released to early access on September 30, 2022.</p>]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2022-10-01:/treekeepers-vr/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/treekeepers-vr/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Treekeepers VR</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>Editor&rsquo;s note from 2025:</p>
<p>This article was written as part of the launch of <a href="/treekeepers-vr">Treekeepers VR</a> and the sole proprietorship Together Again Studios, and represents some of my core beliefs of the value of VR and where it&rsquo;s taking us socially. Though I&rsquo;m no longer actively working on Treekeepers, I do hold that VR and AR are truly the &ldquo;endgame&rdquo; of interface and one that could save us from some of the social attitudes caused by social media of today. Enjoy!</p>
</blockquote>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="proofreader GPT"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/together-again-studios.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 400px; width: 100%"   >


    
</div>

<p>With Together Again Studios and Treekeepers VR, we&rsquo;re setting out to solve an insidious problem we see all around us:</p>
<p><strong>Social Media Is Anti-Social</strong></p>
<p>Though Facebook, Instagram, Twitter, and Tiktok all let us share more with each other than ever before, what we are sharing is surprisingly hostile and dismissive of opinions other than our own.</p>
<p>Though Zoom, Hangouts and Teams let us finally see each other from a distance, we still can&rsquo;t speak naturally. We depend on tools like &ldquo;mute&rdquo;. We create meeting upon meeting with different sets of the same group of people. And we don&rsquo;t form the depth of relationships we could in-person.</p>
<p>We as humans are all-too-capable of forming us-versus-them &ldquo;tribes&rdquo; and dehumanizing those who appear too different, and this problem is becoming ever more apparent behind the curtain of the graphical user interface.</p>
<p><strong>Virtual and augmented reality are a way out</strong></p>
<p>In 2016, thanks to pioneers like Palmer Luckey, Michael Abrash, and John Carmack, we suddenly gained access to a technology that removes the curtain and forces us to see eachother. And in 2020, an event that has permanently limited our in-person interaction arose and gave new meaning to this technology.</p>
<p>In VR/AR, voices are no longer text on a screen, taken out of context by our social media bubbles. They&rsquo;re voices again.</p>
<p>In VR/AR, people are no longer user profiles with one image and a tag-line. They&rsquo;re really people, with bodies, faces, and hands that can point and gesture.</p>
<p>In VR/AR, messages are not just &ldquo;public&rdquo;, or &ldquo;direct&rdquo;. Conversations are dynamic, with people physically approaching one another to talk, with people moving in and out of physical groups, and with people attending public conversations together again while still able to have &ldquo;sidebar&rdquo; conversations.</p>
<p>All these abilities we used to have in-person, we have gained again in virtual reality.</p>
<p>Soon, we&rsquo;ll go even further with this technology. We&rsquo;ll be able to make real eye contact with eachother in VR. We&rsquo;ll use AR to invite distant friends and family over to our homes.</p>
<p>And at Together Again, we plan on using these new tools to let people like eachother again.</p>
<p><strong>Treekeepers: Only Possible in VR</strong></p>
<p>Why is Treekeepers a VR Game?</p>
<p><strong>Multiplayer of this depth only works in VR</strong></p>
<p>The challenges in Treekeepers VR hinge on player coordination and quick group decisions - Which weapon should we upgrade? Who&rsquo;s doing which job? Where are we going?</p>
<p>In VR, you gain the ability to gesture and point to enemies and obstacles naturally.</p>
<p>No more &ldquo;Who is the green player?&rdquo; - spend zero mental energy figuring out who you are talking to. Just turn towards them and speak.</p>
<p><strong>Scale is the most fun when you&rsquo;re in the world</strong></p>
<p>We&rsquo;re going to be exploring oversized objects around a gigantic tree. Only VR can get the full benefit of this experience.</p>
<p><strong>VR can be uncomfortable</strong></p>
<p>BUT, experiencing it via a static vehicle which acts as a persistent frame of reference reduces motion sickness.</p>
<p>No need to rotate - gameplay is based on the hot air balloon always facing one direction, and players navigating within it.</p>
<hr>
<p>Check out Treekeepers VR <a href="/treekeepers-vr">here</a></p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2022-08-01:/social-media-is-antisocial/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/social-media-is-antisocial/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Social Media Is Anti-Social</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>The &ldquo;Human Joystick&rdquo; is an experimental VR movement system in which the player moves through the virtual environment by changing their physical location within their VR &ldquo;playspace&rdquo;.</p>

    <div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
      <iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" loading="eager" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/q_1itpdiPb4?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video"></iframe>
    </div>

<p>A demo of the human joystick movement system, showing how the system can work on flat surfaces or terrain.</p>
<p>This was my first barebones VR project. Though I knew Unity going in, VR and 3D games in general have a lot of unique aspects that I wanted to learn about while trying to solve an actual problem, rather than following tutorials or demos online.</p>
<p>VR has some adoption problems in its current state. We all know of some of the main problems- the clunky headset, the nausea issues, and of course the pricetag. But one major problem that you don&rsquo;t really notice until you get into it, is the lack of a good solution for virtual movement.</p>
<p>I had been wondering about &ldquo;the human joystick&rdquo; as a potential a solution to this particular problem ever since getting into consumer VR in 2016.</p>
<p>In most modern VR systems, the player can move physically around the room if they choose. Some applications and games depend on this - they put you in a small space and rely on your physical movement in order to reach different areas and interact with things. But games that provide a more traditional sense of scale and allow players to move through large worlds cannot rely on physical motion, because their users are constrained by physical space. Because of this, you see all kinds of &ldquo;artificial&rdquo; locomotion systems in order to let people move around - some just like traditional 2D games that let users &ldquo;slide&rdquo; their playspaces around the world using a joystick, and others that adopt teleportation mechanics. Neither feel very natural as compared to actually walking, and some can be downright sickening.</p>
<p>My goal with this project was to solve this problem with a mixture of physical and artificial movement.</p>
<p>It works like this: When the player is standing near the center of their playspace, physical VR movement applies. The player can move around and interact with things with their actual bodies. But once the player moves further from the center, the plaspace starts to move with them in the same direction as the vector from the center of the player&rsquo;s space to their current position. This allows for some of the benefits that physical movement experiences have, while allowing the players to more naturally move through an infinite amount of space.</p>
<p>I experimented with several speeds, both static and scaling with the distance between the center and the player. I also experimented with the size of the physical movement &ldquo;deadzone&rdquo; and with vertical and constrained movement across hills, valleys, and buildings.</p>
<hr>
<table>
  <thead>
      <tr>
          <th style="text-align: center">


















<div class="paige-image">
    




























    



    

    
        

        

        
    
        

        

        
    
        

        
            

    



    







    





    



    






















<img   class="img-fluid "  crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/human_joystick_centered.jpg"   style="display:block; height: auto; margin:0 auto; width: 60%"   >


</div>
</th>
          <th style="text-align: left"><em>View from the player&rsquo;s perspective looking at the guides at his feet. With the white dot in the red deadzone, the player isn&rsquo;t moving.</em></th>
      </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
      <tr>
          <td style="text-align: center">


















<div class="paige-image">
    




























    



    

    
        

        

        
    
        

        

        
    
        

        
            

    



    







    





    



    






















<img   class="img-fluid "  crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/human_joystick_moving.jpg"   style="display:block; height: auto; margin:0 auto; width: 60%"   >


</div>
</td>
          <td style="text-align: left"><strong><em>When the white dot is in the green area, the player moves in that direction. Here I am moving forward and left at about half of max speed.</em></strong></td>
      </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<hr>
<p>Eventually I found some good default values and the system worked, but there were some unforeseen problems: First, it was more difficult to center yourself within the playspace without looking at the visible guides I put at the player&rsquo;s feet than I expected. Second and more importantly, when you were already moving in one direction, it was not as simple as I thought to start moving in another direction accurately without fully returning to center, which was an immersion breaker.</p>
<p>Ultimately I put the project up for others to view but have not expanded it into a full experience or released it on any marketplaces. Feel free to download the Unity project and try it on your own VR setup if you&rsquo;re curious.</p>]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2020-01-01:/human-joystick/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/human-joystick/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Human Joystick VR</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Land War is an 8-player strategy game I developed as a solo project and released to Steam in March of 2019.<br>
This game was intended to have low art requirements and simple interaction rules that result in deep strategic gameplay.</p>
<p>The core concept is that of an ultra-simplified real-time-strategy game. Each player is represented by a color and can grow their territory by moving in any direction. The strategic elements occur when players encounter other players and have to make choices about which side of their land to defend or give up. Players can use the structure of the map and the coordinated action of other players to gain defensible footholds in order to take more area and eventually be the last player on the board.</p>

    <div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
      <iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" loading="eager" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/5Q8PAuWcmQc?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video"></iframe>
    </div>

<p>A full game of the final product released on Steam played on a Windows computer.</p>
<h3 id="development">Development</h3>
<p>I built Land War over the course of 7 months and 400 hours of work using Unity with C#. Though art requirements were intentionally low for a video game, I still had to produce several hundred static graphics and GIFs, and commissioned custom music for the menu and gameplay.</p>
<p>This project is one of my favorite examples of what can be done in relatively little time with a focused vision and a constant eye on scope creep. From the very start, I knew that a key to making compelling software was to flesh out the core concept before all else. This is why I started on the most fundamental strategic interaction of the players and built an MVP version of the game without a menu, sound, art, or even a win condition.</p>
<p>I started the project on a Memorial Day Monday, and by Friday had a rudimentary prototype playable with 8 players on Nintendo Joy-Con controllers paired to a Windows machine via Bluetooth.<br>
This is what the project looked like for my first play-test with other people 5 days in:</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    







    





    



    






















<img  alt="Land War 4-day MVP"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/land_war_mvp.gif"   style="height: auto; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">4-player game played with Nintendo Joy-Cons on a build of the game from 5 days into development.</span>
    
</div>

<p>From there, I continued to work on depth and full feature functionality including menus, a tutorial, a map generator, a dynamic scoring and round system, better sound and sprite graphics, different play modes and settings, and support for many controllers. I released the game with very little marketing aside from some Reddit posts and a physical handout at E3 but was happy to receive positive reviews and several hundred purchases of the game.</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    







    





    



    






















<img  alt="Player Select screen"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/land_war_player_select.png"   style="height: auto; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">Player Select screen. Supporting menu and player controls across hundreds of controller types was one of the largest unforeseen challenges in developing Land War.</span>
    
</div>

<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    







    





    



    






















<img  alt="Settings menu"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/land_war_settings.png"   style="height: auto; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">Settings menu. Most interesting mechanics I found while developing the game were added as options to keep the game interesting here.</span>
    
</div>

<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    



    





    



    






















<img  alt="E3 marketing material"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/land_war_e3.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 400px; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">The only physical marketing material developed for Land War. Several hundred Steam keys (copies of the game) were handed out during the E3 convention in 2019.</span>
    
</div>


    <div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
      <iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" loading="eager" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/BylKEPF4EeU?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video"></iframe>
    </div>

<p><em>Land War&rsquo;s Steam release announcement trailer.</em></p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2019-03-01:/land-war/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/land-war/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Land War</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>Editor&rsquo;s note from 2025:</p>
<p>This was my most-downloaded original 3D print, and my first design to be featured on the homepage.
I&rsquo;ve redesigned and re-released these coasters! <a href="/8-bit-coasters-10-year">Check out the 10 year anniversary edition.</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>If you like retro video games and also drinking things, you&rsquo;re in luck!
This full set of 8 unique video game coasters comes with themed coaster holders for sets of either 4 or 8! Print them for your living room! Print them for your friends!
I hope these characters remind you of some of your favorite series.</p>
<div class="paige-row-wide">
  <div style="display:grid; grid-template-columns:repeat(2, minmax(0,1fr)); gap:15px;">
      






























    













    



    






















<img   class="rounded-3 w-100"  crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/2013-8-bit-set-1.png"    >


      






























    













    



    






















<img   class="rounded-3 w-100"  crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/2013-8-bit-set-2.jpg"    >

</div>
</div>

<div class="paige-row-wide">
  <div style="display:grid; grid-template-columns:repeat(2, minmax(0,1fr)); gap:15px;">
      






























    













    



    






















<img   class="rounded-3 w-100"  crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/2013-8-bit-set-3.jpg"    >


      






























    













    



    






















<img   class="rounded-3 w-100"  crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/2013-8-bit-set-4.jpg"    >

</div>
</div>

<p>Also find an awesome customizable version by ahtly here:
<a href="http://www.thingiverse.com/thing:139754">http://www.thingiverse.com/thing:139754</a></p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2013-07-09:/8-bit-coasters/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/8-bit-coasters/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2013 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>8-Bit Videogame Coasters</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
