













    
        
    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    







    

    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"  xml:lang="en-us"  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            

            
                
            

            
                <link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/hardware/" rel="self" type="text/html"/>
            
        
            

            

            
                <link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/hardware/rss.xml" rel="alternate" type="application/rss+xml"/>
            
        

        

        

        <description>Recent content</description>

        
            <language>en-us</language>
        

        
            <lastBuildDate>2025-01-01 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</lastBuildDate>
        

        <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/hardware/</link>

        

        <title>Hardware · Tags · hockenworks</title>

        

        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Here&rsquo;s a peek at my first major board game creation.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve made a few clones or slight alterations of games I like before (links to nope and hocken pocket blokus) but blue more bust is my first attempt at something of my own design and very high production quality.</p>
<p>(Pics)</p>
<p>This is a risk-taking game where players compete to take over a tree with their specific type of fruit. Trees and bees are becoming a recurring theme in my games!</p>
<p>All parts of this game or hand designed by me, mostly in VR with a tool called gravity Sketch, blender, and one of my favorite programmer&rsquo;s 3D tools called OpenSCAD.</p>
<p>(Link those)</p>
<p>Of all my models, this one takes most advantage of my multicolor BambuLab printer. All parts including the custom box which cleverly incorporates the instructions and game board itself are printed in bamboo lab Matte PLA, which in my opinion is probably the most beautiful way to print.</p>
<p>Production is batched with 80 to 150 of each fruit or bee on a build plate, but heavily limited by the game board and latching box each requiring a separate print.</p>
<p>I have looked into outsourcing production of this game so that I can actually distribute it but that has not happened yet since its design is so dependent on multicolor 3D printing, and most print farms would require nearly 30 bucks to produce it, let alone shipping it and my own margin. Injection molding is an option but also gets expensive with this level of detailed color, and requires remodeling in several significant ways. It still might happen. Or I might put it out on a site that lets people buy the model and print it themselves.</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2025-01-01:/bloom-or-bust/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/bloom-or-bust/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Bloom Or Bust</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p><strong>Raspberry Pi Control Panel</strong> is a hardware project I designed in 2016 to manage home automation systems. The project involved designing a custom 3D-printed case for a Raspberry Pi microcomputer with a touchscreen interface.</p>
<p>Links:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/hockenmaier/RaspberryPiControlPanel">GitHub</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:2524560">Thingiverse</a></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>I created this panel display in 2026 to control much of the home automation I used in my Studio City apartment. Mainly a hardware project, I designed and 3D-printed a case and frame for the touchscreen and raspberry pi microcomputer in order to mount them to the wall. The software running the control panel is SaaS, but I did write a custom html wrapper to control the orientation and settings of the site, which is available on the github linked above.</p>
<p>Update in 2025: This panel is still my main view into my home automation in my new house in Sherman Oaks, almost 10 years in with no modification!</p>
<p>Here&rsquo;s a video to see the panel in action:</p>
<h2 id="hahahugoshortcode20s0hbhb">
    <div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
      <iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" loading="eager" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/iFGmm-ijJvE?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video"></iframe>
    </div>
</h2>
<p>Feel free to explore the linked repositories for schematics and source code.</p>]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2016-01-01:/raspberry-pi-panel/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/raspberry-pi-panel/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Raspberry Pi Control Panel</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
