













    
        
    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    







    

    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"  xml:lang="en-us"  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            

            
                
            

            
                <link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/singularity/" rel="self" type="text/html"/>
            
        
            

            

            
                <link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/singularity/rss.xml" rel="alternate" type="application/rss+xml"/>
            
        

        

        

        <description>Recent content</description>

        
            <language>en-us</language>
        

        
            <lastBuildDate>2025-07-28 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</lastBuildDate>
        

        <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/singularity/</link>

        

        <title>Singularity · Tags · hockenworks</title>

        

        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Recently I read the <a href="https://ai-2027.com/scenario.pdf">AI 2027 paper</a>. I was surprised to see Scott Alexander&rsquo;s name on this paper and I was doubly surprised to see him do his <a href="https://www.dwarkesh.com/p/scott-daniel">first face reveal podcast about it with Dwarkesh</a></p>
<p>On its face this is one of the most aggressive predictions for when we will have AGI (at least the new definition of AGI which is something that is comparable or better than humans at all non-bodily tasks) that I have read. Even as someone who has been a long believer in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Singularity_Is_Near">Ray Kurzweil&rsquo;s Singularity predictions</a>, 2027 strikes me as very early. I realize that Kurzweil&rsquo;s AGI date was also late 2020&rsquo;s and 2045 was his singulartiy prediction - 2027 still feels early to me.</p>
<div class="paige-row-wide">
  <div style="display:grid; grid-template-columns:repeat(2, minmax(0,1fr)); gap:15px;">
      































    













    



    























<img  alt="AI 2027"   class="rounded-3 w-100"  crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/ai-2027.png"    >


      































    













    



    























<img  alt="Singularity Is Near"   class="rounded-3 w-100"  crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/The-Singularity-Is-Near.jpg"    >

</div>
</div>

<p>I won&rsquo;t get into my full take on AI 2027 here, but the core argument comes down to the same one I was making in my <a href="/on-ai-software-development">original post on AI software development</a> - which is that, once AI agents are able to replace software engineers, instead of just assisting them, it doesn&rsquo;t matter their current performance in non-software domains, because they will simply be able to improve on their own software and training procedures at such a rate that the time difference between the moment of automating software engineering tasks and the moment of automating all other tasks is negligible.</p>
<p>In light of AI 2027, I figured it was a good time to update where I think AI is actually in terms of software engineering. I&rsquo;ve had the chance to test many of the latest AI software development tools and models, and they have come a long way since my original post.</p>
<h1 id="what-i-built">What I Built</h1>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been developing with AI since 2021, but I got a special chance to really put the latest models and tools to the last few months while on parental leave. And I think I have a more valuable type of project with which to accurately evaluate these models on their creative capacity for programming, which is really the hard stuff.</p>
<p>This project is absolutely not in the training data, not even a little bit. That&rsquo;s because it&rsquo;s a game, which AI is already much worse than other types of developments (mobile and web dev in particular are particular), but also because it&rsquo;s a game combined with a CMS website. <a href="/this-website/#ball-machine---the-game">This website!</a>.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a very strange project. I won&rsquo;t get too much into the weeds here, but essentially we have a <a href="https://gohugo.io/">hugo CMS</a> underneath everything, and that Hugo CMS has a bunch of short code that interacts with a bunch of other custom JavaScript that loads dynamically when the player decides to start playing any given page. Just try it on the top right corner of this page and you&rsquo; might start to imagine how weird of an application this would be to work on.</p>
<h1 id="three-ways-for-ai-to-build-your-project">Three Ways for AI to Build Your Project</h1>
<p>Over the course of 5 months, I worked on this game via 3 main methods, which happen to be the main 3 ways that anyone is writing code with AI these days.</p>
<ol>
<li>Chat Assistants - particularly the O4-mini and O3 models</li>
<li>Automated IDEs - particularly Cursor</li>
<li>Autonomous Coding Agents - particularly OpenAI&rsquo;s &ldquo;Codex&rdquo;, which launched about 2 months before I finished the project.</li>
</ol>
<p>I&rsquo;m going to cover what they are and how they performed on my game.</p>
<h2 id="chat-assistants">Chat Assistants</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>What Are They?</p>
<p>Chat Assistants are models running in a client such as <a href="https://chatgpt.com/">ChatGPT</a>, <a href="https://claude.ai/login?returnTo=%2F%3F">Claude</a>, or <a href="https://gemini.google.com/app">Gemini</a>. Getting these assistants to write code for you entails passing in instructions and sometimes code context from your project.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Chat assistants are great and have been helping developers for a long time! These are the closest most people get to running LLMs &ldquo;raw&rdquo; rather than through specialized tools designed to limit their errors or make them more agentic. So, you can think of the performance of Chat Assistants for coding as sort of the &ldquo;default performance&rdquo; of AI models to today at coding tasks. The other methods of having AI writing code still have the general performance dynamics I&rsquo;m going to talk about here at their cores, even if they mitigate some types of failures by running their own tests and dealing with console errors.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ll start with what might be an obvious statement: LLMs are great at producing simple, low context code. Like - so great that most humans won&rsquo;t need to do write much algorithmic logic from here on out. I certainly didn&rsquo;t when making this game, or really anything else I&rsquo;ve made in the last two years.</p>
<p>But basic coding is not all of software engineering, and LLMS still have major issues:</p>
<p><strong>1. They can&rsquo;t deal well with contexts over 30K tokens or so (even the best models with supposed millions of token context windows).</strong></p>
<p>This means the actual developer (me and you) are typically the ones picking specific files and functions to send into the context window, lest we confuse the model. This is arduous unless the codebase is small enough to fit entirely into the context window. That&rsquo;s exactly what I think is going on with most of the new &ldquo;vibe coded&rdquo; projects we see showing impressive results - these are just tiny POC apps that haven&rsquo;t hit more than a few thousand lines of code yet. For context, most serious enterprise apps containing the detailed logic and edge cases real use cases require are in the millions or hundreds of millions of lines of code.</p>
<p>This issue is compounded by the fact that the largest labs seem to recognize it, and have modified their chat clients in secret ways to the user to save themselves money. OpenAI in particular implements and invisible, silently failing ~40K token limit on text pasted into the chat window. I have run into many strange issues caused by this, and it’s an insane policy on OpenAI’s part because they have non-invisible text limits for some models like 4o that tell you when your message is too long. My theory on why is pretty insidious if true: I think they want paying customers to think their very large thinking models can accept the full token limit of the models, and don’t think many customers will find out they are truncating them for cost reasons anyway, because these models become so forgetful after 30K tokens or so anyway.</p>
<p><strong>2. They are biased to be &ldquo;advisors&rdquo; rather than &ldquo;doers&rdquo;</strong></p>
<p>This is just annoying, and I hope it gets trained out soon, even when models are running as chat assistants. When they are not specifically trained out of this mindset, most AI models just really <em>want</em> you, the human, to be doing everything, and to act themselves as an advisor. This makes sense with one of the main sources of code training data being from Stackoverflow and other blogs, where developers can never seem to rid themselves of a pseudo-condescending &ldquo;you should have been able to read the docs and learn this yourself&rdquo; tone. It&rsquo;s also just a pattern exhibited by people in general - more often than not, especially in the corporate world, people are trained to be the &ldquo;coaches&rdquo; rather than the &ldquo;worker bees&rdquo;. One reason why things get done so slowly in big political companies sometimes.</p>
<p><strong>3. They are still wrong sometimes, even on the basics, but they&rsquo;re wrong MUCH more confidently than human developers.</strong></p>
<p>This is probably the biggest issue for all code produced by AI, regardless of interface. But I&rsquo;m including it in the &ldquo;Chat Assistants&rdquo; section because there are no guardrails on chat assistants other than the human user: they won&rsquo;t run tests and they won&rsquo;t encounter errors. Here&rsquo;s a recent example of a true algorithmic mistake that cost me days of confusion developing my game. This is with O3, potentially the best model for coding, via a chat client.</p>
<pre tabindex="0"><code>setInterval(() =&gt; {
/_ --- recompute every 30 engine ticks (~0.5 s) ---------------------- _/
if (engine.timing.timestamp % 20 === 0) {
let maxV = 0;
Matter.Composite.allBodies(engine.world).forEach((b) =&gt; {
if (b.label === &#34;BallFallBall&#34;) {
const v = Math.hypot(b.velocity.x, b.velocity.y);
if (v &gt; maxV) maxV = v;
}
});

        /* map speed → substeps (1‒5) */
        let target =
          maxV &gt; 40 ? 8 : maxV &gt; 25 ? 8 : maxV &gt; 12 ? 8 : maxV &gt; 3 ? 8 : 1;


        /* mobile caps at 2 */
        if (isMobileLike &amp;&amp; target &gt; 2) target = 2;
        substeps = target;
        console.log(&#34;New Substeps: &#34; + substeps);
      }


      const dt = baseDt / substeps;
      for (let i = 0; i &lt; substeps; i++) {
        Matter.Engine.update(engine, dt * engine.timing.timeScale);
      }
    }, baseDt);
</code></pre><p>This code was confidently written by o3 after lots of correct, thoughtful discussion about how often we should run physics simulation on my game in times/s. 60 hz is a common simulation time, which is Matter.js’s default, but when you have small objects moving around quickly, you need to increase it so that they don’t tunnel through each other.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Tunneling in physics simulations is when one of two objects is moving fast enough that there is not single frame where they are colliding, and so they simply pass through each other</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is all good theory, and o3 came up with a really thorough chart for this little line:</p>
<pre tabindex="0"><code>maxV &gt; 40 ? 8 : maxV &gt; 25 ? 8 : maxV &gt; 12 ? 8 : maxV &gt; 3 ? 8 : 1;
</code></pre><p>Which tried to determine dynamically how many physics steps to run based on how fast objects are moving on the screen. It&rsquo;s a great idea, it is simple algorithmic work, and I was happy not to have to write or think about it.</p>
<p>There was just one problem. The condition at the start of this snippet, <em>if (engine.timing.timestamp % 20 === 0)</em>, would never be true, because we are always dividing time up into little chunks in a way that they wouldn’t even be whole numbers. The entire code snippet above never runs.</p>
<p>Here&rsquo;s where it gets really hairy, and the confidence issue really compounds in a negative way. I asked o3 and many other AI chatbots and agents about this code, and all “assumed” it was correct and would fire when I told them it wasn’t working. They would dig into all the little minutia of this function, the thresholds, how we were getting the max velocity, etc, and none figured out that why it wasn’t working was something more basic like this.. that it was never firing at all because of the faulty condition that O3 wrote at the top.</p>
<p>To be fair, I, the human, should have caught this before asking yet more AI agents why it wasn’t working. But the AI has taught me to be a little bit lazy, and what does it say about the state of AI independently-written software if multiple passes by state-of-the-art agents didn’t see the issue with a snippet of less than 20 lines of code?</p>
<h2 id="agentic-ides">Agentic IDEs</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>Automated IDEs are &ldquo;development environments&rdquo;, the software that humans use to write code, with LLM integrations added in to auto-complete or produce new code somewhat agentically. They can do things like read terminal output and attempt to fix their mistakes before you see them. The main examples right now are <a href="https://cursor.com/en">Cursor</a> and <a href="https://windsurf.com/editor">Windsurf</a>. Amazon just launched <a href="https://kiro.dev/blog/introducing-kiro/">Kiro</a> in this category.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>After I became a parent and then started having a few hours a day to come up for air, one of the first things I wanted to do was REALLY crack into one of these vibe-coding tools to see what it was all about. I picked Cursor.</p>
<p>Simple download, login, install. All going well. The very first feature I decided to through at it (using Claude 3.7 which was at the time the top recommended model) was something relatively simple: I wanted to modify the behaviour of the &ldquo;Compactor&rdquo; item in the Ball Machine so that it would not only combine the value of balls, but also remember how many balls had been combined and combine their value growth per second. This would need to change about 3 files and read from maybe 5 more.</p>
<p>The first real dissapointment here happened after I entered my detailed prompt for how I wanted this to work: Cursor not only wanted an instruction file telling the AI how my codebase worked, it also wanted me to <em>manually pick every file</em> to include in the context. I laughed out loud when I saw this. I had been under some impression that Cursor was more than essentially copying and pasting a prompt and some code context into ChatGPT.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, I picked all the files I thought were relevant - about 10 of them - and let the agent run. I did this at least 3 times, testing each one. Some of these runs were many minutes of Claude 3.7 iteratively coding.</p>
<p>Abject failure. Nonsense written into the files. Total disregard for the context I had provided.</p>
<p>After the final attempt with prompt tweaks and file context tweaks, I just gave up on Cursor doing this. I used Context Caddy and O3 and got code (Code I had to tweak and find the right place for) that worked. Apparently this was too complicated for Cursor and its top recommended AI model. I was able to achieve simple, mostly one file edits with Cursor using simple natural language prompts. It never seemed to respond well to my multi-pager prompts that I have grown accustomed to giving big thinking models like O3.</p>
<p>In the end I cannot argue that using a raw LLM via a chat assistant is better than using an automated IDE. There is theoretically nothing that Cursor could not do that a web chat-based LLM could, provided you are willing to pay for an expensive model like O3 behind it, prompt it carefully, and correct its mistakes. But I was not willing to do that - the benefits of Cursor didn&rsquo;t seem worth this cost to me. And, there is a lot that it can do, like reading and correcting basic terminal errors.</p>
<p>Perhaps I had been spoiled by my own creation, context caddy, which is a vs code extension I made that essentially let me use any typical chat assistant with the same kind of context file picker.</p>
<p>If you were used to simply plugging in prompts to ChatGPT, being able to pick files for context and then having the model able to respond to terminal errors could seem like a big upgrade.</p>
<p>After all this, here&rsquo;s my hottest take of the article: Automated IDEs like Cursor and Kiro are a fad that will pass us by soon.</p>
<p>They exist today because IDEs are where all code editing takes place, and putting LLMs there was obvious. The next obvious thing was to let them run code and read output from the terminal in a loop. The next most obvious thing is to give them &ldquo;specs&rdquo; instead of prompts, so they have more patterns to follow rather than duplicating code everywhere as LLMs always want to do. This is where we&rsquo;re at with these Agentic IDEs, and they are useful.</p>
<p>But the core issue with this obvious progression of features is that it ignores this fundamental reality: Once AI models are actually good enough to do a software engineering task, there is no reason for that task to happen in an IDE at all, a tool made for humans to write code.</p>
<h2 id="autonomous-coding-agents">Autonomous Coding Agents</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>Autonomous Coding Agents, unlike Agentic IDEs, approach the problem of agentic software development without the lens of the toolspace that humans rely on. Using these systems does not depend on the actual code ever living on your own computer. Instead, you give them access to the code in your remote repository such as Github, and they do all the work to clone that code, look through it, make changes, test what they can, and ultimately contribute directly back to that codebase in the form of a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Distributed_version_control#Pull_requests">Pull Request</a>. The main two right now are OpenAI&rsquo;s <a href="https://openai.com/codex/">Codex</a> and <a href="https://github.blog/news-insights/product-news/github-copilot-the-agent-awakens/">Github Copilot Agents</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>On the face of it, Autonomous Coding Agents aim to do the same thing which has come to be the top feature of Agentic IDEs: The let you specify a feature, change, or fix by simply speaking or typing English, and then they proceed through a loop of coding, evaluating, and refining until they &ldquo;think&rdquo; the feature is done. And both types of system can do that job. But in my experience with Codex, the Autonomous Coding Agent I used, the experience was night and day.</p>
<p>I think Codex benefits most from its limitations. It does not sit in an IDE, so it could not possibly ask you, the human, to pick the files to add to system context. It doesn&rsquo;t run on your computer with you watching it, so it needs to handle all of its own looping, eval, and stop logic on its own. It needed to &ldquo;get good&rdquo; at these things. And that it did.</p>
<p>I will just skip straight to the punchline: OpenAI&rsquo;s Codex was writing full new features for my game via my voice-texted prompts alone (most of which I spoke while walking the baby) within days of me setting it up. In fact, the <a href="/this-website/#achievements">entire achievements feature of my game</a>, including the UI components, the logic to detect them, and save them - everything but the images I used for the achivement icon - was created in two Codex PRs generated without me touching the codebase.</p>
<p>I had built up to this point a little bit. I started Codex on simple tasks reminiscent of the one I started Cursor on, but I found that I was willing to lend more tasks to Codex, because I knew it wouldn&rsquo;t interupt my work at all. I would just end up with a PR I could review 20 minutes later or so, and if it worked I would merge it. Compare that to the experience with Agentic IDEs, where most of the time you need to open your computer, type up a prompt, select all the context you think is necessary, and then &ldquo;help it along&rdquo; when it gets stuck. This is not to say Codex didn&rsquo;t get stuck - there were things it couldn&rsquo;t do, even the occasional simple thing, but for those I would pull the PR, see that it didn&rsquo;t work, and then just reject it. No longer was I in the world of trying to &ldquo;help along&rdquo; the AI ending up in strange diff states and git stashing to clean up my own workspace. It was just &ldquo;Hey this is a thing the robot could do&rdquo;, then quick voice text, and 20 minutes later 80% of the time a working PR.</p>
<p><strong>But that thought, &ldquo;this is a thing the robot could do&rdquo; is very important</strong></p>
<p>For all the advantages of Codex, it’s still just as bad and generally uncreative as any other AI. And of course that is highly dependent on how standard and boilerplate your code is. Codex is better than any agent I&rsquo;ve used at following a super detailed prompt to completion (The first prompt for that achievements feature is almost 2 pages long) - but you still need to know your project well enough to write that super detailed prompt. For my game, I just know there are things I could never do with AI. Those involve messing with the fundamental architecture of the code, rethinking gameplay look and feel, or anything with too many moving parts. AI has a limit, and in 2025 that limit is still quite low. It&rsquo;s a junior developer that writes super fast. But I found that, when shifting from thinking of AI as an assistant I would proactively try to use, vs something I chould completely offload half of my tasks to &ldquo;set and forget&rdquo; - the latter is a much more meaningful time savings. It really forced me to draw the line of what could be automated and what the AI could do for me.</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2025-07-28:/on-ai-software-development-2/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/on-ai-software-development-2/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>On AI Software Development, 2025 Edition</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Early last year, I came across this tweet:</p>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/AdamRackis/status/1762321041899012307">https://twitter.com/AdamRackis/status/1762321041899012307</a></p>
<p>The discussion was surprisingly contentious. Maybe I should stop being surprised given the state of Twitter and all social media, but still sometimes shocking how dug-in people are in their beliefs about work. On the face of it, “people get twisted in their relationship with work” seems like a reasonable take. &ldquo;Stop complaining—you are making 16x the median salary in this country. Just do the boring job with the toxic team.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Let’s stop and think about this for a second. The original poster (OP) is making $800K annually due to the appreciation of Spotify stock. An obscene amount of money? Maybe, maybe not. I do not have the typical hang-ups about the wealthy or ultra-wealthy. I don’t see this world as a zero-sum game, and I think the richest people out there have usually done some amazing things, especially in countries like the US where most wealth is not old wealth.</p>
<p>But there is a huge difference in the two main routes to creating becoming very wealthy:</p>
<ol>
<li>Founding a company or practice, or joining one early, out of passion - which then goes on to become incredibly valuable</li>
<li>Working for someone else doing a job you think is boring in order to join the 1%.</li>
</ol>
<p>In this article, I’m talking about the latter.</p>
<p>I propose this core question for this type of person engaging in number 2: Is this large income worth doing a job you find boring, or working with people you feel are toxic? I would say no. Absolutely not. OP is clearly regretting how he’s spending his time at work. He should look for something to do that he values, even if it pays a quarter as much as he gets now. Or less!</p>
<h2 id="the-hedonic-treadmill">The Hedonic Treadmill</h2>
<p>There’s an often misquoted study from ~2010 that personal income beyond about $75K (presumed to cover basic necessities with a comfortable overhead) does not equate to further happiness. This number is actually about right when it comes to simple reported happiness, which has more to do with the hedonic treadmill than anything else. But the study in question was also measuring reported “life satisfaction” as surveyed, which did not stop increasing with income. Of course, “life satisfaction” is a fraught survey metric as well, as it might actually measure a perceived comparative number with one’s neighbors (we’ll get to this later).</p>
<p>But whatever the proper measure of happiness or satisfaction is, there is a great deal of logic to thinking its relationship with income looks like this:</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="happiness income curve"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/treadmill-graph.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 720px; width: 100%"   >


    
</div>

<p>As in: there are diminishing returns to incremental income. Not a revolutionary idea. It’s obvious. But it also means that somewhere along this curve is the often-quoted $75K, and somewhere far to the right is OP’s $800K. And the curve between those points is probably pretty flat.</p>
<p>What could OP get in return for moving to the left along this flat section of the curve? Eight hours of time per workday, at least, that he finds incrementally more valuable. How much do you think those 8 hours could improve his life satisfaction on their own happiness/hours curve?</p>
<p>This is where the real paradox comes in. Gaining wealth is supposed to make your time more valuable. You choose to get more services, have a housekeeper, maybe even a private chef. But if those things actually indicate a person values their time more highly than someone poorer, how come they would even consider sacrificing most of that time doing something they find boring, or with people they find annoying? Just to maintain their position along the flat section of the curve?</p>
<p>Maybe they aren’t prioritizing happiness at all.</p>
<h2 id="keeping-up-with-the-joneses">Keeping up with the Joneses</h2>
<p>My argument so far would be absolute blasphemy to most of the $500K+ salary people who don’t have much fun at work. Let’s talk about their two most common counterarguments:</p>







<div class="paige-quote">
<blockquote class="blockquote"><ol>
<li><em>&ldquo;Work should be a sacrifice, and more money means more security for my family.&rdquo;</em></li>
</ol>
</blockquote>


</div>

<p>This is noble. It’s also way too self-sacrificial for the extremely wealthy first-world people we’re talking about. You’re making $800K. There is not a salary sacrifice in the world that will make your family “insecure.”</p>
<p>And what pattern does this even establish? You’re going to choose to be unhappy for most of your waking hours so that you can guarantee your children will be able to do the same? What are you actually working for if not you or anyone else being able to actually enjoy themselves?</p>







<div class="paige-quote">
<blockquote class="blockquote"><ol start="2">
<li><em>&ldquo;But I could make this crazy money and then retire in 5 years.&rdquo;</em></li>
</ol>
</blockquote>


</div>

<p>Now this is a good argument! You could indeed retire in 5 years after making $800K per year and then spend your time with family or pursue passion projects! The problems here are twofold:</p>
<p><strong>First</strong>, nobody does this. Instead, they spend more money. Of course, some of it will be saved, but the main thing that happens when people find themselves with far more money than needed for their family’s security is that they spend it. Bigger houses, more trips, elite schools for the kids. These make you feel well-off compared to your neighbors but don’t push you much higher on that flat curve.</p>
<p><strong>Second</strong>, people find value in being useful. There’s a reason why so many struggle in retirement. Even with a rigid FIRE plan, you’ll still want to work afterward on something interesting. So why not find that now?</p>
<p>What’s actually happening? Lifestyle creep. I think this is 90% of why people feel they could never work on something more fun or meaningful for less money. They’ve already started to spend their new money, and now losing those things would hurt more than gaining them felt good. That damn hedonic treadmill.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-enough">What is &ldquo;Enough&rdquo;?</h2>
<p>While writing this essay I came across another recent one from Adam Singer, who is more blunt about this:</p>
<p><a href="https://www.hottakes.space/p/250k-per-year-is-plenty-of-income">https://www.hottakes.space/p/250k-per-year-is-plenty-of-income</a></p>
<p>Of course I agree, but what I found really funny while reading it is that I see two reactions to this 250K threshold: That it&rsquo;s extremely high, and that it&rsquo;s extremely low. These diverse reactions are only possible in a society where, for many, money has become largely about comparison to others vs something needed to live a satisfied life. I think those who see this and think its an extremely low to be &ldquo;plenty&rdquo; is living in comparison land.</p>
<p>So, think deeply about what you value. Money itself is a means to an end. It&rsquo;s the way you spend your time, and that includes working too, that has true value. Value your own time as much as your spending habits would suggest you do. This is the right logic for your long-term well-being.</p>
<p>We might be approaching a technological singularity. It’s a healthy time to step back, reflect on the fundamental values driving our behavior, and make changes. Wouldn’t it feel silly to spend most of your waking hours working miserably on meaningless things, only to arrive in the second half of your life in a world of true abundance?</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2025-07-21:/the-treadmill/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/the-treadmill/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>The Treadmill</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I have long been of the mind that LLMs and their evolutions are truly thinking, and that they are on their way to solving all of the intellectual tasks that humans can solve today.</p>
<p>To me, it is just too uncanny that the technology that seems to have made the final jump to some degree of competence in tasks that require what is commonly understood as &ldquo;thinking&rdquo; or &ldquo;understanding&rdquo;, after a long string of attempts and architectures that fail these tasks, is a type of neural network. It would be much easier to argue away transformer models as non-thinking stochastic parrots if we had happened to have had success with any other architecture than the one that was designed to mimic our own brains and the neurons firing off to one another within them. It&rsquo;s just too weird. They are shaped like us, they sound like us in a lot of ways, and it&rsquo;s obvious they are thinking something like us too.</p>
<p>I am not saying they are as good as us yet, though, for a few small reasons and one big one.</p>
<h2 id="the-limitations">The Limitations</h2>
<p>Current frontier &ldquo;thinking&rdquo; models are not AGI in the modern definition. They can&rsquo;t do every task humans can do intellectually (IE without a body, which I will get to) for several reasons:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p>Looping/Recursive reasoning:
This was a huge problem for early transformers that had to output in one shot, and the examples were obvious. This one has been essentially solved via thinking models like o1, and now o3, gemini and grok thinking models, and many more. That was a huge unlock and a huge boon for applications like programming where there is lots of nested recursion of logic that has to occur to find a reasonable solution.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Memory and context:
Context windows get larger all the time, but this limitation still is not solved. Just adding a bunch of tokens into a context window doesn&rsquo;t get you much when 2 million token models lose coherence after about the first 40,000 - which they do, and which every programmer working with anything but a tiny codebase intuitively understands. But this one too will largely be solved soon, if not through architectures that actually update their weights, it&rsquo;ll be solved through nuanced memory systems that people are actively developing on top of thinking models.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Size:
This is basic, but most of the models we can interact with today are still working with an order of magnitude fewer neural synapses than human brains. It could very easily be that, even with the other problems solved, we just need bigger electronic brains to match the size of our meat ones. It certainly <em>feels</em> like some of the ways LLMs fail today sort of come down to &ldquo;not enough horsepower&rdquo; types of issues.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Vision</strong>:
And this one might sound funny to someone that is paying attention to AI in particular, because GPT-4 with vision launched something like 2 years ago now. And it has been impressive for a long time, able to do things like identify what objects are in an image, where an image is from, etc: things most humans can&rsquo;t do glancing at an image, that seem super-human.</p>
<p>But the vision itself is not “good” vision. It cannot really pick out small important details, and it still behaves in many ways like vision recognition models have for years now. Now that we have a model that has both thinking and image input and editing at every step, the o3 and o4-mini series that recently released, we can really start to see the limitations in vision. Let me take you through 2 examples that represent the 2 types of failure modes that result from these not having true image understanding, yet.</p>
<p>My thesis today is that this is the key limitation that is not going to be overcome &ldquo;by default,&rdquo; but that it will be overcome.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="proof-the-vision-is-not-there-yet">Proof the Vision is Not There Yet</h2>
<p>Each release from the major providers steadily knocks away my intelligence tests, which I admit are mostly programming oriented, but the ones that they can never really dent are the spatial reasoning ones - where a model really has to think about images in its head or use an image provided for detailed work.</p>
<h3 id="simple-3d-modeling-with-frontier-ai-models">Simple 3D Modeling with Frontier AI Models</h3>
<p>Every major model release, <a href="/3d-modeling-with-ai">I test what models can do with OpenSCAD</a>. I won’t get technical about it here, but OpenSCAD is a CAD program (Computer Aided Design - think 3D modeling for engineers, not the artistic kind) that is defined entirely through a programming language vs the typical mouse strokes and key presses that software like SolidWorks or AutoCAD depend on.</p>
<p>This makes OpenSCAD the perfect test platform for a model that inputs and outputs text primarily. I can describe a 3D model I want, and the model can output text that renders into a 3D model.</p>
<p>As amazing as LLMs are at scripting in normal programming languages, they have never been good at OpenSCAD. See my link above for GPT-3.5 and GPT-4 trying to model an incredibly simple object. That acorn was about as complex as GPT-4 could get without really falling down.</p>
<p>Here is OpenAI&rsquo;s o3’s attempt to make a standard 2x4 Lego Brick:</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="an OpenSCAD render"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/o3-lego.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 720px; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">o3&#39;s model left, real Lego brick right</span>
    
</div>

<p>This was the easiest object I tested, and o3 does a decently good job. It grabbed the correct dimensions online and, using its inherent training data of what a 2x4 Lego block is, applied those dimensions into a mostly coherent object. It has one major flaw, which you can see on the underside as I have the image rotated - it drew two lines through two of the cylinders. My guess is that this is its interpretation of the supports in the middle of the actual Lego brick, that connect but don&rsquo;t run through the center cylinder.</p>
<p>Now for a harder test: a simple engineering part that&rsquo;s definitely not in its training data, because it is my own design. I printed this for a robotics project more than a decade ago, and had it sitting around in my 3D printer storage drawer.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s a bit of a weird part - a pinion with a smooth section and an 11-tooth gear of equal diameter, and a hole in the center with a slightly raised wall. This is the kind of part that an engineer well versed in AutoCAD or SolidWorks can produce in just a few minutes, but which requires attention to detail and a conceptual model of how parts fit together.</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="an OpenSCAD render"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/o3-pinion.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 720px; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">o3&#39;s model left, real part right</span>
    
</div>

<p>This is where you can see how these models fall apart. o3 immediately gets that it&rsquo;s a pinion, that it has a hole in the middle, and that it has a smooth section on the bottom and a gear on top. But the execution is nowhere close to workable, from most major to least (in my opinion):</p>
<ul>
<li>There are two gears (unknown as to why or if this is intentional, o3 explained one as a &ldquo;grooved ring&rdquo; - whatever that means)</li>
<li>The gear teeth are concave - whereas the rounded sharp tooth shape is clear in the image</li>
<li>There are 10 teeth, not eleven - which seems trivial, but it&rsquo;s indicative of a real flaw that messes up all complex models I throw at AI - where LLMs make an assumption like what number of teeth is &ldquo;likely,&rdquo; rather than looking at the image in detail and counting them.</li>
<li>There is clearly an attempt at the raised wall around the top hole, but it&rsquo;s far too big.</li>
<li>The height of the smooth base section and gear sections are equal in the real part, but o3 makes the gear more than 3x thicker than the base.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="map-reading">Map Reading</h3>
<p>Here&rsquo;s another great example of what I mean when I say that frontier models have bad vision.</p>
<p>I recently gave this question to the latest thinking image model, o3: &ldquo;Here&rsquo;s an image from Google Maps of the block I live on between the avenues of Burbank, Hazeltine, Oxnard, and Van Nuys. What is the longest continuous loop I can walk within the neighborhood without crossing my path or touching one of the avenues? This square is 1/2 mi on each side&rdquo;</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="the uploaded map"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/o3-struggle-map-new.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 400px; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">The image uploaded with this query</span>
    
</div>

<p>O3 thinks for 4 minutes about this question, zooming in to various parts of the map countless times to form the route. And then it fails on the first step, suggesting starting at Tiara and Stansbury, which do not intersect on the map. Any person looking at this image could tell that is true in just a few seconds.</p>
<p>This is what I mean when I say these things have bad vision - and this is the best model from the lab I think has the best vision. Vision is not about being able to identify millions of different objects, <a href="https://www.image-net.org/">ImageNet-style</a>. It&rsquo;s about seeing the detail and paying attention to the right thing. Here in this map, that means looking roughly at the lines representing Stansbury and Tiara, looking at where they would intersect, and seeing they do not.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Though getting AI models to read maps and create 3D models from code may not be on everyone&rsquo;s rubric, any UX developer that has worked with a frontier AI knows what I&rsquo;m saying intuitively. This is likely just as true for any role heavily leaning on visual information. There is a difference between generating some Tailwind code that spits out a standard UI and getting to the level of complexity that the AI starts to need to look at screenshots in detail and know the relative position and orientation of components, or see small details. They just.. don&rsquo;t do that yet.</p>
<h3 id="non-frontier-ai-models">Non-Frontier AI Models</h3>
<p>A common retort to this argument might be &ldquo;Well Brian, you&rsquo;re using the wrong type of model.&rdquo;</p>
<p>But believe me, I try essentially everything I can get my hands on, and like non-LLM AI models in other domains, other than being incredibly limited in application, these models are simply not good at vision, either. Here&rsquo;s an image of a 3D model generated by Zoo CAD, a company doing text and image to 3D, which was, when I printed it back in January at least, state of the art in this domain:</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="My Flipper Zero and 3D Printed Clone"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/flipper-3d.jpg"   style="height: auto; max-width: 720px; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">My Flipper Zero (left) and its 3d-printed clone (right)</span>
    
</div>

<p>The input to the model was a picture I took of my <a href="https://flipperzero.one/">Flipper Zero hacking toy</a>. The 3D print on the right is of the 3D model it produced, with the only modification on my part being to scale it.</p>
<p>I have long awaited an easy way to &ldquo;3D scan&rdquo; parts from the real world into software. This would make so many of my DIY printing jobs around the house much easier - and it gets us one step closer to the dream of teleportation.</p>
<p>And I was impressed when I first saw this output - it was one of the best of my attempts with this AI tool. Feature-wise, it did a pretty good job of capturing the main facets of my Flipper Zero. But it&rsquo;s just too obviously not good enough: dimensions are all wrong, there is hallucinated symmetry all over the place, and small details are missed everywhere. One of the reasons I printed this model was just to get a real feel for how similar it is to the Flipper when scaled correctly, and it just becomes obvious that this is not a useful technology yet when you hold both of them in your hands.</p>
<p>My prediction is that frontier models will get there before purpose-trained models like the one that cloned my Flipper Zero. This has been the reality across most other domains of AI. Now that we have general-purpose AI models that have started to encapsulate a working, if not complete, conceptual model of the world, they are starting to outperform all of the smaller purpose-built models of the last decade.</p>
<p>And this will be good for the general capability of the AI industry: It&rsquo;s a much better outcome to have a few general-purpose models that can do fine visual work, that can be prompted and orchestrated by people working in different domains, than it is to need an AI lab or startup to train a specific model for every task. It&rsquo;s the same reason I believe humanoid robots are going to win over purpose-built ones in the long run: We can&rsquo;t predict what users will want their robots to do, and our world is built for humans to operate in it - therefore the most capable robots will be shaped generally like humans.</p>
<p>So how will frontier models get good at visual tasks, if they have such bad vision right now? I think the answer to that question also involves humanoids.</p>
<h2 id="the-humanoids">The Humanoids</h2>
<p>What I think is going on in these examples of frontier model vision failures is that we have a limitation in training data (duh!) - but that isn&rsquo;t because there aren&rsquo;t a lot of images and videos on the internet, it&rsquo;s because there is so much more information in the average image than there is in the average chunk of text, and a lot more of that information is irrelevant to any given question.</p>
<p>When I say that we have a limitation on training data, I&rsquo;m not in the typical camp of &ldquo;well, then transformer neural nets are obviously stupid because I was able to understand this thing without training on terabytes of data from the internet&rdquo;. This has always been a bad take because the average human trains on petabytes, not terabytes of data, and that data is streamed into their brains mostly in the form of images. I am also not in the camp of thinking that this means that the data &ldquo;just doesn&rsquo;t exist&rdquo; to get these models to AGI in the visual dimension. It so clearly does exist, and it exists so abundantly that a unique image stream can be sent to each of the billions of human brains, and they all learn the same principles that let them immediately identify the mistake that the cutting-edge thinking vision model made after 4 minutes of rigor.</p>
<p>Not only does the data exist: We never actually had a data problem in AI in the first place. We have an instruction problem. That doesn&rsquo;t mean model architecture or data massaging really, it means that we need to plug our models into the real world where all the data streams exist. I believe this will come first in the form of robots with cameras on them, the first of which is happening en masse via Tesla full self-driving AI, and I&rsquo;m sure those vision neural nets are quite insanely capable compared to what we see in the consumer transformer vision models. But the real leap probably comes when we get to humanoid robots walking around collecting and learning from vision data every day - and learning from actions they take in the real world.</p>
<p>If you’ve ever tried to get concrete actions to take based on a vision-transformer’s outputs, you will know it’s hard. I never posted about it, but I did a small project with a friend a year or two ago, trying to get automated QA working on web software, and we failed in a lot of different ways. I am very impressed that the big labs are starting to crack <a href="https://docs.anthropic.com/en/docs/agents-and-tools/computer-use">computer use</a> - because getting an LLM to give specific coordinates or elements to click on is the same type of challenge I was testing above. But it&rsquo;s no wonder these computer use applications are still very inaccurate.</p>
<p>Letting transformer-based agents control robots will be a much harder problem of a similar type. Not only does it require attention to detail, but now the images are in 3D, they come at you many times per second, and actions need to be produced as quickly. But my prediction is that we will brute force this, and it will work &ldquo;well enough&rdquo; for enthusiasts and niche industrial use cases to benefit from humanoid robots. And that&rsquo;s the takeoff point for true vision, as we all intuitively understand it. Releasing humanoids at scale (and cars, to some extent) are when we really unleash the datastream that&rsquo;s needed to get models that can see as well as you or I can. This is probably one reason why many AI companies and labs are pushing them so hard - they also understand the data they collect will be more valuable than the money paid for the first units.</p>
<p>Once we have a few hundred thousand humanoids roaming around early adopters&rsquo; houses, we will start to see AI models that can use OpenSCAD and Google Maps. And, conveniently, that&rsquo;s also the missing capability that will make the humanoids really useful. We have interesting years ahead of us.</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2025-06-16:/vision-is-the-last-hurdle-before-agi/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/vision-is-the-last-hurdle-before-agi/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Vision is the last hurdle before AGI</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m <a href="/about-me">Brian Hockenmaier</a>, and this site is full of things I build and write about. I love making games and things with VR and AI. And I love DIY projects, especially ones involving programming, engineering and 3D modeling. Some of this has been cross or back-posted from my <a href="https://www.thingiverse.com/hockenmaier/designs">thingiverse</a>, <a href="https://github.com/hockenmaier">github</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/hockenmaier/">linkedin</a>, and other places, but it all lives here permanently.</p>
<p>This is an evolution of <a href="old-site/index.html">my previous site last updated in 2022, which I still keep inside this one</a> for posterity and for the AIs of the future to know more about me. I like it not because of the content as much as because it was a fully custom js and html site with no framework&hellip; and I think it&rsquo;s sort of fun and funny that it was like this.</p>
<p>All work and opinions here are my own, not my employer&rsquo;s.</p>
<h1 id="why-im-making-it">Why I&rsquo;m making it</h1>
<p>I&rsquo;m creating this website in 2025 after starting a family as well as my first full-time role in AI. It&rsquo;s an effort to clean up my website&rsquo;s focus, move several disparate collections into one place, and emphasize what I truly care about. I wanted it to be easier to add content, CMS style, and I wanted a space to occasionally post written content, too.</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="the hockenworks homepage"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/hockenworks.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 720px; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">This webpage, if you hadn&#39;t noticed</span>
    
</div>

<p>A big reason I&rsquo;m doing this now is that, after listening to the Dwarkesh podcast with Gwern, I was convinced I really should have more of a record for future AIs to learn about me. I really don’t have a social media presence, nor do I want one, and over the years I have had a lot of projects and writing that I have unnecessarily kept private. AGI or not, there are non-artificial intelligences that may be interested one day. Talking to you, Alice :) When I started this website, your cousin Lily kept asking where you were and didn&rsquo;t seem to get the concept that you currently occupied the same space as Kaitlin.</p>
<p>I love some of the 2010s era blogs, and though mine is not going to be nearly as longform, nearly as focused on prose, or nearly as articulate, two of the sites I&rsquo;m trying to take inspiration from are <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/about/">Slate Star Codex</a> and <a href="https://gwern.net/about">Gwern&rsquo;s website</a> which are definitely advising on style here. Other than the fact that mine is also a game.</p>
<hr>
<h1 id="etymology-of-hockenworks">Etymology of &ldquo;hockenworks&rdquo;</h1>
<p><strong>Hockenmaier</strong> is a great name. I&rsquo;ve always loved it. Not just because it’s unique and has my favorite number of letters, but because of its meaning, at least my family’s “folk-etymology” for it.</p>
<p>You have:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Hocken</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Which can roughly translate to “sitting down, squatting, settling, idling”.</p>
<p>And then you have:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>Maier</strong></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Which has many different spellings, and ours has southern German roots, but all &ldquo;Meyer&rdquo; names come from the latin root &ldquo;maior&rdquo; meaning steward, administrator, or more generally &ldquo;worker&rdquo;</p>
<p>My family often puts these two ideas together as &ldquo;Lazy Worker,&rdquo; which is very on-brand for our sense of humor, but I think it&rsquo;s not just funny, but true.</p>
<p>“Lazy Worker” is perfect for someone who wants to get a lot done, especially in software engineering. We only have so many hours, and the best lives are lived restricting the number of hours spent on work that isn&rsquo;t done with people you love. So you better be efficient about it. You better be lazy. There are <a href="https://blog.codinghorror.com/how-to-be-lazy-dumb-and-successful/?utm_source=chatgpt.com">many</a> <a href="https://xkcd.com/1205/?utm_source=chatgpt.com">correct</a> <a href="https://thethreevirtues.com/">takes</a> out there on the value of being lazy when programming.</p>
<p>Now that we are starting to have AI, it&rsquo;s even better. A lazy worker like myself will not only avoid unnecessary work, but will delegate all that can be delegated to the new AI workers that are multiplying in our computers. That makes the &ldquo;steward&rdquo; connotation of &ldquo;Maier&rdquo; all the more fitting.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m proud to be the lazy worker, and this site is all about sharing my lazy works. My <em>hockenworks</em>.</p>
<hr>
<h1 id="ball-machine---the-game">Ball Machine - The Game</h1>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="A ball machine"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/bubble4.gif"   style="height: auto; max-width: 720px; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">The Ball Machine</span>
    
</div>

<p>Most blogs and personal websites are a bit boring. I think that is because most professionals consider what they do &ldquo;for work&rdquo; a bit boring by its nature, and don&rsquo;t necessarily make a concerted effort to have fun with it.</p>
<p>I have always tried to be the opposite, and with kids coming I am trying to make a bigger effort than ever to have fun whatever I&rsquo;m doing. Which is often working, in some way or another.</p>
<p>So for my website, I wanted it to be intentionally fun. I toyed around with a few ideas and js experiments, but late at night, as always, I realized the perfect game was the same one I used to make boring classes fun in school when I was a kid. That game consisted of the book of graph paper I always kept with me, plus a pencil, a ruler, and a protractor. I was a bit obsessed with physics simulation at the time. My favorite game in church growing up, where I was often daydreaming and looking at the huge arched ceiling, was to imagine a laser coming out of my line of sight and bouncing off of every surface in the room, to see where it would end up. This graph paper game I played was similar.</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="balls everywhere"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/this-website-ball-machine-1.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 720px; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">Some of my early playtests got pretty chaotic</span>
    
</div>

<p>I would start by making a &ldquo;spawn point&rdquo; usually near the top left of the page, where balls would start falling. I would draw out the path of these balls a few inches from each other along their path with &ldquo;speed lines&rdquo; to denote which way they were going, and how fast. Then I would add platforms, trampolines, loops, curves, &ldquo;booster&rdquo; acceleration zones, jumps, machines that would disassemble and reassemble balls, and so many other things - usually something new each sheet of paper - and I would end up with a Rube Goldberg machine of balls flying all around the sheet. The only goal was to fill the sheet with more ridiculous paths.</p>
<p>I started calling the sheets my &ldquo;ball machines&rdquo;. I wish I still had some of these drawings. I remember them being quite intricate.. I must have reserved English class for them.</p>
<p>So, to honor kid Brian, I am making my website a permanent ball machine. I hope you have fun with it and see all there is to unlock!</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="balls everywhere"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/waves2.gif"   style="height: auto; max-width: 300px; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">Even on the limited phone version, you can create some productive chaos</span>
    
</div>

<h2 id="how-its-made">How it&rsquo;s made</h2>
<p>I don&rsquo;t typically make complicated things like this with JavaScript. So when I found the perfect physics engine for the game - <a href="https://brm.io/matter-js/">matter.js</a> - I knew I would need help from our new little assistants. And though this game is a bit too structured to call it &ldquo;vibe coded&rdquo; - at times, it was close.</p>
<p>I ended up making my own tool called <a href="/context-caddy">Context Caddy</a> to help me with it. Part of the reason I leaned so hard into this is because I&rsquo;m always trying to push the limits of current AI, and I hadn&rsquo;t built a game since the GPT-4 days (I&rsquo;ll post about that soon). The new thinking models are truly a step above GPT-4 (this was mostly done with o3 and its minis) but they&rsquo;re still way too eager to write duplicate code, and they still don&rsquo;t &ldquo;get&rdquo; the structure of your project a lot of the time, especially with visual and physical things like this. Still, they were a great help here.</p>
<p>This game is made extra complicated by the fact that it runs on top of <a href="https://gohugo.io/">Hugo</a>, which is the static site generator behind the &ldquo;content&rdquo; part of this site. This probably doubled or tripled the effort of making this game. But, the balls in the &ldquo;ball machines&rdquo; of my youth would interact with my text notes and drawings, so this ball machine needed to do so as well.</p>
<p>There is quite a bit going on under the hood to make these two very distinct types of development projects work in tandem, and for both of them to work well. The Ball Machine would love to eat up all of the resources and make the site content unresponsive, and the content was quite a lot to dynamically build physical bodies and colliders around. I like the end result. But I like it a lot better on desktop, where the two can really interact, so I think you should play it on a real computer with a mouse.</p>
<h2 id="how-to-play">How to Play</h2>
<span
  style="
    float: left;
    width: 150px;
    margin: 0 1rem 1rem 0;
    display: inline-block;
  "
>
  





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="ball chute"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/ball-chute-hatch-1.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 200px; width: 100%"   >

 
  <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem">
    This tube creates balls every time you click it
  </span>
  
</span>

<p>The ball machine on this site is a gamified version of my graph paper drawings as a kid. Each time you load a page, you&rsquo;ll see a little pneumatic delivery tube on the top right of the screen.</p>
<p>When you spawn your first ball, you&rsquo;ll see a few things appear. First - you&rsquo;ll find a goal     <span
  style="
    display: inline-block;
    width: 40px;
    margin: 0 1rem 0 0;
    vertical-align: middle;
    text-align: left;
  "
>
  





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="the goal"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/goal.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 40px; width: 100%"   >

 
</span>
 somewhere randomly on the page. Find a way to get the balls you spawn into that goal. But there is a bit of a trick - balls start out being worth 1 coin and accumulate another coin in value every two seconds. So, the longer you can keep balls around, the more they will be worth when going into the goals, and this might get more and more challenging as your drawings take up more of the screen and balls start bouncing off of each other.</p>
<p><strong>Keep Clicking!</strong></p>
<p>It&rsquo;s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Incremental_game">a clicker game</a> - start by manually clicking the pneumatic delivery tube to spawn balls, but as you accumulate coins you&rsquo;ll be able to unlock different drawables and things that will let you accumulate more coins faster. If it feels like it&rsquo;s taking a while to make coins and unlock things, try playing around more with how the balls interact with the content, and use all of the tools you can draw. The site also works across multiple pages. And if all else fails&hellip; just give it time. This is a clicker game after all, so waiting is always a strategy! There is plenty to read while you wait.</p>
<p>It works best when you&rsquo;re on desktop, working on one tab at a time.</p>
<p> </p>
<blockquote>
<p>Quick Disclaimer: This game is designed for big screens, ideally desktop computers. If you must play on a phone, try landscape mode!</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 id="controls">Controls</h3>
<p><span
  style="
    display: inline-block;
    width: 100px;
    margin: 0 1rem 0 0;
    vertical-align: middle;
    text-align: left;
  "
>
  





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="line toggle"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/line-mode.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 200px; width: 100%"   >

 
</span>

<span
  style="
    display: inline-block;
    width: 100px;
    margin: 0 1rem 0 0;
    vertical-align: middle;
    text-align: left;
  "
>
  





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="curved line toggle"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/curve-mode.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 200px; width: 100%"   >

 
</span>

<span
  style="
    display: inline-block;
    width: 100px;
    margin: 0 1rem 0 0;
    vertical-align: middle;
    text-align: left;
  "
>
  





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="compactor toggle"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/compactor-mode.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 200px; width: 100%"   >

 
</span>
</p>
<p>To start drawing your ball machine, you need to <kbd>Left Click</kbd> or <kbd>Tap</kbd> one of these drawable toggles in the main UI (top left of the screen)</p>
<p>When you have a drawable tool toggled on, you won&rsquo;t be able to click other links on the site. You&rsquo;ll see this visually indicated when you choose them. Unselect the currently selected tool in order to see it</p>
<p>Every drawable item (lines, launchers, and more) uses the following mechanics:</p>
<p> </p>
<h4 id="drawing-on-desktop">Drawing on Desktop</h4>
<p><strong>Spawn Balls:</strong> <kbd>Left Click</kbd> on the pneumatic spawner tube</p>
<p><strong>Draw Objects:</strong> <kbd>Left Click</kbd> and drag to see a preview, then <kbd>Left Click </kbd> to place</p>
<ul>
<li>Some drawables have a second action, like curved lines, that is previewed after the second click and confirmed with a third click</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Cancel Drawing</strong> After you&rsquo;ve started a line or other drawing but before you&rsquo;ve clicked again to confirm, <kbd>Right Click</kbd> to cancel it.</p>
<p><strong>Delete Objects:</strong> Hover over a drawn item and <kbd>Right Click</kbd> to delete it, getting 50% of your money back</p>
<p> </p>
<h4 id="drawing-on-mobile">Drawing on Mobile</h4>
<p><span
  style="
    color: #ff0040;
    font-family: 'Arial Black', Arial, sans-serif;
    font-size: 20px;
  "
>
   Mobile Scroll Lock Warning:
</span>
 On Mobile, scrolling the page is blocked while you&rsquo;re drawing to allow you to draw lines in any direction.</p>
<p>You will need to untoggle your selected tool before you can scroll or click links.</p>
<p>If your phone has gesture controls to reload, go back or forward, or other browser things, you should disable them if you really want to play on your phone. Or, just play on desktop!</p>
<p><strong>Spawn Balls:</strong> <kbd>Tap</kbd> on the pneumatic spawner tube</p>
<p><strong>Draw Objects:</strong> <kbd>Touch and Drag</kbd> to see a preview, then <kbd>Release</kbd> to place</p>
<ul>
<li>Some drawables have a second action, like curved lines, that is previewed and confirmed on the next touch-and-drag.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Cancel Drawing</strong> After you&rsquo;ve started a line or other drawing but before you&rsquo;ve released to confirm, go back to where you started and release around there to cancel it. The threshold to cancel is within 25 pixels of where you started.</p>
<p><strong>Delete Objects:</strong> <kbd>Tap and hold</kbd> an object to delete it, getting 50% of your money back. You will see it pulse before it deletes.</p>
<p> </p>
<h4 id="the-auto-clicker">The Auto-Clicker</h4>
<span
  style="
    display: inline-block;
    width: 100px;
    margin: 0 1rem 0 0;
    vertical-align: middle;
    text-align: left;
  "
>
  





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="auto clicker"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/auto-clicker.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 200px; width: 100%"   >

 
</span>

<p>This is the autoclicker button that lets you pay to auto-spawn balls.</p>
<p><kbd>Left Click</kbd> or <kbd>Tap</kbd> to buy the first auto-clicker, or upgrade it.</p>
<p><kbd>Right Click</kbd> on desktop or <kbd>Tap and hold</kbd> on mobile to refund and downgrade it to the previous click frequency.</p>
<p> </p>
<h3 id="money--other-hints">Money &amp; Other Hints</h3>
<p>You&rsquo;ll quickly find ways to lengthen your Rube-Goldberg Machines and build up value before you send balls into the goal. Your money is displayed on the coin counter next to the ball spawner.</p>
<p> </p>
<p><span
  style="
    display: inline-block;
    width: 100px;
    margin: 0 1rem 0 0;
    vertical-align: middle;
    text-align: left;
  "
>
  





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="dotted line toggle"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/everything-has-a-price.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 200px; width: 100%"   >

 
</span>
<strong>Everything has a price!</strong></p>
<p>If you can&rsquo;t draw an item, you probably can&rsquo;t afford it. You&rsquo;ll see your coin counter flash red in the UI when this happens.</p>
<p><span
  style="
    display: inline-block;
    width: 100px;
    margin: 0 1rem 0 0;
    vertical-align: middle;
    text-align: left;
  "
>
  





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="dotted line toggle"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/dotted-line-mode.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 200px; width: 100%"   >

 
</span>
<strong>You get what you pay for&hellip;</strong></p>
<p>If you ever find yourself out of money, these dotted lines are free. They are not saved permanently like other lines and they go away after 50 balls hit them.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>❌ A couple of things to watch out for when building ball machines:</p>
<ul>
<li>Balls have to be moving at all times. If they sit still for too long, they are considered dead and will poof out of existence.</li>
<li>This applies to balls hitting the goal, too. If your balls aren&rsquo;t moving much when they hit the target, they won&rsquo;t go in.
So keep your balls moving!</li>
</ul>
<p>😵 If you have a good run going, but it descends into chaos, it can be hard to recover. That&rsquo;s what the <kbd>Erase Balls</kbd> button above the draw tools is for!</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Each post on this site will be a slightly different randomized game! Try making ball machines on multiple pages at once. Your work will be saved in realtime, and you can make money even on pages you&rsquo;re not currently playing on.</p>
<p><span
  style="
    display: inline-block;
    width: 100px;
    margin: 0 1rem 0 0;
    vertical-align: middle;
    text-align: left;
  "
>
  





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="dotted line toggle"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/page-revenue.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 200px; width: 100%"   >

 
</span>
 These counters display how much <strong>sustainable</strong> coin revenue per second you&rsquo;re making on this page, and how much other pages you&rsquo;re not currently working on are contributing. Any balls that are spawned automatically and continuously travel through your contraption to hit the goal will be averaged into the top amount. When you visit other pages, you will keep making this money - that&rsquo;s what the &ldquo;Other Pages&rdquo; revenue displays.</p>
<p>Your progress is saved to your device because your contraptions will be highly dependent on the screen size the site renders to.</p>
<p>The game works a bit differently on desktop and mobile, and the best experience is really on desktop - so try on a computer if you can! If on mobile, flip to landscape.</p>
<h3 id="the-end-of-the-game">The End of the Game</h3>
<p>Right now, the Ball Machine doesn&rsquo;t end, but you will be surprised the amount of money you can make across the whole site! Eventually, there will be other ways to spend coins on this site and potentially &ldquo;beat&rdquo; the ball machine. The late game items change the game in very interesting ways! I hope you make some fun machines on my website.</p>
<p>You&rsquo;ll know you&rsquo;ve done about all there is to do by tracking the achievements below!</p>
<h4 id="achievements">Achievements</h4>
<div id="achievements-list"></div>
<script>
document.addEventListener('DOMContentLoaded', function(){
  var container = document.getElementById('achievements-list');
  if(!container){ console.error('Achievements container missing'); return; }
  try {
    var defs = (window.App && App.Achievements && App.Achievements.defs) || [];
    var unlocked = JSON.parse(localStorage.getItem('game.achievementsUnlocked') || '{}');
    var yes = 'http:\/\/localhost:1313\/images\/achievement-yes.png';
    var no = 'http:\/\/localhost:1313\/images\/achievement-no.png';
    if(!defs.length){
      console.warn('No achievements definitions found');
    }
    defs.forEach(function(a){
      var row = document.createElement('div');
      var img = document.createElement('img');
      var got = unlocked[a.id];
      img.src = got ? yes : no;
      img.alt = got ? 'Unlocked' : 'Locked';
      img.style.width = '16px';
      img.style.height = '16px';
      img.style.marginRight = '4px';
      row.appendChild(img);
      var b = document.createElement('b');
      b.textContent = a.name;
      row.appendChild(b);
      if(got){
        row.appendChild(document.createTextNode(' – ' + a.desc));
      }
      container.appendChild(row);
    });
    if (location.hash && location.hash.includes('achievements')) {
      var anchor = document.getElementById('achievements');
      if (anchor) {
        setTimeout(function(){ anchor.scrollIntoView(); }, 50);
      }
    }
  } catch(e){
    console.error('Failed to render achievements', e);
    container.textContent = 'Error loading achievements.';
  }
});
</script>

<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<h3 id="resetting-the-game">Resetting the Game</h3>
<span
  style="
    color: #ff0040;
    font-family: 'Arial Black', Arial, sans-serif;
    font-size: 20px;
  "
>
   WARNING! Don't navigate to the below page unless you're sure you want to reset the ball machine game
</span>

<p>Resetting will erase all of your drawings on all pages and reset your goal locations, unlocks, coins and everything else.</p>
<p>If you are thinking about doing this because you want to try on another device, you don&rsquo;t need to, because progress is already saved to your device. The only reason to do this is to have a fresh start on this device.</p>
<p>Navigate <a href="/reset-ball-machine">here</a> and click reset to do that.</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2025-05-28:/this-website/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/this-website/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>This Website</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="this is a robot"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/ai-software-dev.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 720px; width: 100%"   >


    
</div>

<p>Lots of chatter right now about AI replacing software developers.</p>
<p>I agree - AI will take over software development. The question is: what work will be left when this happens?</p>
<p>Some considerations:</p>
<ul>
<li>Benchmarks for the best LLMs still put them solidly in the &ldquo;bad at programming&rdquo; category, scoring in the 5th percentile of human programmers on common tests. Meanwhile, LLMs score in the 80th-95th percentile for law exams and 85th–100th for psychology, statistics, and many other less technical fields. More scores available in the &ldquo;simulated exams&rdquo; section of <a href="https://openai.com/research/gpt-4">https://openai.com/research/gpt-4</a>.</li>
<li>Engineers have been using language models like tabnine and copilot as &ldquo;super-stackoverflow&rdquo; style code assistance years before chatGPT released. This means much of the velocity increase we might expect from current LLMs&rsquo; ability to write code has already been &ldquo;priced in&rdquo; to the market.</li>
<li>Many of the trends making software development more costly are growing, not shrinking: Systems are becoming more distributed. The cloud lowered infrastructure costs but made applications more complex. We&rsquo;re making more and deeper integrations among disparate systems. Auth is becoming more secure and thus complex (managed identity, MFA, etc).</li>
</ul>
<p>Github copilot chat and other LLM dev tools are speeding up the rote stuff. I’ve seen it in my own work.</p>
<p>And I really do believe new AI models will do more than just the basics, maybe in the next couple of years. Even precluding &ldquo;AGI&rdquo;, the trend we are on is that more and more work is automatable, and engineers, especially more junior ones - are going to have to shift focus away from algorithmic work that AI can do.</p>
<p>But by the time our neural nets are &ldquo;good enough&rdquo; at building software to make it significantly cheaper to build, I doubt this trend will make the news. Everything else gets automated too.</p>
<p>These are my thoughts at what seems to be the beginning of the next AI revolution in early 2024. I plan to revisit this topic and see if I&rsquo;m right in future posts.</p>]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2024-01-24:/on-ai-software-development/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/on-ai-software-development/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2024 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>On AI Software Development</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
