













    
        
    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    







    

    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"  xml:lang="en-us"  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            

            
                
            

            
                <link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/crossplay/" rel="self" type="text/html"/>
            
        
            

            

            
                <link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/crossplay/rss.xml" rel="alternate" type="application/rss+xml"/>
            
        

        

        

        <description>Recent content</description>

        
            <language>en-us</language>
        

        
            <lastBuildDate>2023-01-01 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</lastBuildDate>
        

        <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/crossplay/</link>

        

        <title>Crossplay · Tags · Home</title>

        

        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>The Flapper</p>
<p>The Flapper is a project that spawned out of a simple movement mechanic test that turned out to be surprisingly fun! The idea is to flap your arms to fly - and have it be a multiplayer battle to really get people moving.</p>
<p>Most of the start of this game was just tuning the movement mechanic, which borrowed from some physics realities and some elements I made up to make flapping feel good.</p>
<p>Here&rsquo;s a video of one of the later states of the game, where I have it fully networked and am testing with friends, though it still has a few bugs here:</p>

    <div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
      <iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" loading="eager" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Vxn8rDOZ7dU?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video"></iframe>
    </div>

]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2023-01-01:/the-flapper/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/the-flapper/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>The Flapper</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    




























    



    



    





    







    



    






















<img  alt="The Treekeepers Puddle Jumper"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/treekeepers_moonlight.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">The Treekeepers Puddle Jumper</span>
    
</div>

<p>Treekeepers VR is a networked VR game where up to 4 players can cooperate to navigate an oversized world and save a giant tree.</p>
<p>Treekeepers is in production on both Quest (standalone VR) and Steam (PC VR) with full cross-play functionality. See the <a href="https://togetheragainstudios.com/treekeepersvr/">Treekeepers VR Website</a> for links to all storefronts and more detail about the game.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="development">Development</h2>
<p>I began working on Treekeepers in June 2021, and my primary goal was to go significantly deeper into Unity and make a fully networked game. Very few co-op games existed in VR at the time (the area is still lacking), and my intention was to answer this need and create a game that 4 players could cooperate in within a static frame of reference (players move within a ship, and the ship moves through the world) while having to solve coordination challenges together.</p>
<p>I initially designed the project for SteamVR only using the SteamVR SDK but quickly realized that a VR game released only on PC would miss the majority of the userbase, as the (then Oculus) Quest 2 was quickly dominating the market. Treekeepers was a good fit for a mobile platform with its simple low-poly cel-shaded design, so I pivoted to using OpenXR about two months into the project to support VR interactions on both PC and mobile (Android) devices like the Quest 2.</p>
<p>By summer 2022, I had a releasable product, albeit only with one “world” available. I decided to push the game to early access to gather rapid feedback from real players, and after getting approved for both storefronts, Treekeepers released to early access on September 30, 2022.</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2022-10-01:/treekeepers-vr/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/treekeepers-vr/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Treekeepers VR</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<h2 id="with-together-again-studios-and-treekeepers-vr-were-setting-out-to-solve-an-insidious-problem-we-see-all-around-us">With Together Again Studios and Treekeepers VR, we&rsquo;re setting out to solve an insidious problem we see all around us:</h2>
<h3 id="social-media-is-anti-social">Social Media Is Anti-Social</h3>
<p>Though Facebook, Instagram, Twitter, and Tiktok all let us share more with each other than ever before, what we are sharing is surprisingly hostile and dismissive of opinions other than our own.</p>
<p>Though Zoom, Hangouts and Teams let us finally see each other from a distance, we still can&rsquo;t speak naturally. We depend on tools like &ldquo;mute&rdquo;. We create meeting upon meeting with different sets of the same group of people. And we don&rsquo;t form the depth of relationships we could in-person.</p>
<p>We as humans are all-too-capable of forming us-versus-them &ldquo;tribes&rdquo; and dehumanizing those who appear too different, and this problem is becoming ever more apparent behind the curtain of the graphical user interface.</p>
<h3 id="virtual-and-augmented-reality-are-a-way-out">Virtual and augmented reality are a way out</h3>
<p>In 2016, thanks to pioneers like Palmer Luckey, Michael Abrash, and John Carmack, we suddenly gained access to a technology that removes the curtain and forces us to see eachother. And in 2020, an event that has permanently limited our in-person interaction arose and gave new meaning to this technology.</p>
<p>In VR/AR, voices are no longer text on a screen, taken out of context by our social media bubbles. They&rsquo;re voices again.</p>
<p>In VR/AR, people are no longer user profiles with one image and a tag-line. They&rsquo;re really people, with bodies, faces, and hands that can point and gesture.</p>
<p>In VR/AR, messages are not just &ldquo;public&rdquo;, or &ldquo;direct&rdquo;. Conversations are dynamic, with people physically approaching one another to talk, with people moving in and out of physical groups, and with people attending public conversations together again while still able to have &ldquo;sidebar&rdquo; conversations.</p>
<p>All these abilities we used to have in-person, we have gained again in virtual reality.</p>
<p>Soon, we&rsquo;ll go even further with this technology. We&rsquo;ll be able to make real eye contact with eachother in VR. We&rsquo;ll use AR to invite distant friends and family over to our homes.</p>
<p>And at Together Again, we plan on using these new tools to let people like eachother again.</p>
<h2 id="treekeepers-only-possible-in-vr">Treekeepers: Only Possible in VR</h2>
<p>Why is Treekeepers a VR Game?</p>
<h3 id="multiplayer-of-this-depth-only-works-in-vr">Multiplayer of this depth only works in VR</h3>
<p>The challenges in Treekeepers VR hinge on player coordination and quick group decisions - Which weapon should we upgrade? Who&rsquo;s doing which job? Where are we going?</p>
<p>In VR, you gain the ability to gesture and point to enemies and obstacles naturally.</p>
<p>No more &ldquo;Who is the green player?&rdquo; - spend zero mental energy figuring out who you are talking to. Just turn towards them and speak.</p>
<h3 id="scale-is-the-most-fun-when-youre-in-the-world">Scale is the most fun when you&rsquo;re in the world</h3>
<p>We&rsquo;re going to be exploring oversized objects around a gigantic tree. Only VR can get the full benefit of this experience.</p>
<h3 id="vr-can-be-uncomfortable">VR can be uncomfortable</h3>
<p>BUT, experiencing it via a static vehicle which acts as a persistent frame of reference reduces motion sickness.</p>
<p>No need to rotate - gameplay is based on the hot air balloon always facing one direction, and players navigating within it.</p>
<hr>
<p>Check out Treekeepers VR <a href="/treekeepers-vr">here</a></p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2022-08-01:/social-media-is-antisocial/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/social-media-is-antisocial/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Social Media Is Anti-Social</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
