













    
        
    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    







    

    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"  xml:lang="en-us"  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            

            
                
            

            
                <link href="http://localhost:1313/personal/y/" rel="self" type="text/html"/>
            
        
            

            

            
                <link href="http://localhost:1313/personal/y/rss.xml" rel="alternate" type="application/rss+xml"/>
            
        

        

        

        <description>Recent content</description>

        
            <language>en-us</language>
        

        
            <lastBuildDate>2024-02-01 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</lastBuildDate>
        

        <link>http://localhost:1313/personal/y/</link>

        

        <title>Y · Personal · Home</title>

        

        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>I came across this tweet today that was surprisingly contentious. Maybe not so surprising given the state of Twitter, but still:</p>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/AdamRackis/status/1762321041899012307">https://twitter.com/AdamRackis/status/1762321041899012307</a></p>
<p>On the face of it, “people get twisted in their relationship with work” seems like a reasonable take. Stop complaining—you are making 16x the median salary in this country. Just do the boring job with the toxic team.</p>
<p>Let’s stop and think about this for a second. The original poster (OP from now on) is making $800K annually due to the appreciation of Spotify stock. An obscene amount of money? Maybe, maybe not. I do not have the typical hang-ups about the wealthy or ultra-wealthy. I don’t see this world as a zero-sum game, and I think the richest people out there have usually done some amazing things, especially in countries like the US where most wealth is not old wealth.</p>
<p>But there is a difference between founding a company you’re passionate about, which goes on to become incredibly valuable, and working for someone else doing a job you think is boring in order to join the 1%. In this article, I’m talking about the latter.</p>
<p>I propose this core question for this type of person: Is this large income worth doing a job you find boring, or working with people you feel are toxic? I would say no. Absolutely not. OP is clearly regretting how he’s spending his time at work. He should look for something to do that he values, even if it pays a quarter as much as he gets now. Or less!</p>
<h3 id="the-hedonic-treadmill">The Hedonic Treadmill</h3>
<p>There’s an often misquoted study from ~2010 that personal income beyond about $75K (presumed to cover basic necessities with a comfortable overhead) does not equate to further happiness. This number is actually about right when it comes to simple reported happiness, which has more to do with the hedonic treadmill than anything else. But the study in question was also measuring reported “life satisfaction” as surveyed, which did not stop increasing with income. Of course, “life satisfaction” is a fraught survey metric as well, as it might actually measure a perceived comparative number with one’s neighbors (we’ll get to this later).</p>
<p>But whatever the proper measure of happiness or satisfaction is, there is a great deal of logic to thinking its relationship with income looks like this:</p>



















<div class="paige-image">
    




























    



    

    
        

        

        
    
        

        

        
    
        

        
            

    



    







    





    



    






















<img  alt="Alt text"   class="img-fluid "  crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/treadmill-graph.png"   style="display:block; height: auto; margin:0 auto; width: 50%"   >


</div>

<p>As in: there are diminishing returns to incremental income. Not a revolutionary idea. It’s obvious. But it also means that somewhere along this curve is the often-quoted $75K, and somewhere far to the right is OP’s $800K. And the curve between those points is probably pretty flat.</p>
<p>What could OP get in return for moving to the left along this flat section of the curve? Eight hours of time per workday, at least, that he finds incrementally more valuable. How much do you think those 8 hours could improve his life satisfaction on their own happiness/hours curve?</p>
<p>This is where the real paradox comes in. Gaining wealth is supposed to make your time more valuable. You choose to get more services, have a housekeeper, maybe even a private chef. But if those things actually indicate a person values their time more highly than someone poorer, how come they would even consider sacrificing most of that time doing something they find boring, or with people they find annoying? Just to maintain their position along the flat section of the curve?</p>
<p>Maybe they aren’t prioritizing happiness at all.</p>
<h3 id="keeping-up-with-the-joneses">Keeping up with the Joneses</h3>
<p>My argument so far would be absolute blasphemy to most of the $500K+ salary people who don’t have much fun at work. Let’s talk about their two most common counterarguments:</p>







<div class="paige-quote">
<blockquote class="blockquote"><ol>
<li><em>&ldquo;Work should be a sacrifice, and more money means more security for my family.&rdquo;</em></li>
</ol>
</blockquote>


</div>

<p>This is noble. It’s also way too self-sacrificial for the extremely wealthy first-world people we’re talking about. You’re making $800K. There is not a salary sacrifice in the world that will make your family “insecure.”</p>
<p>And what pattern does this even establish? You’re going to choose to be unhappy for most of your waking hours so that you can guarantee your children will be able to do the same? What are you actually working for if not you or anyone else being able to actually enjoy themselves?</p>







<div class="paige-quote">
<blockquote class="blockquote"><ol start="2">
<li><em>&ldquo;But I could make this crazy money and then retire in 5 years.&rdquo;</em></li>
</ol>
</blockquote>


</div>

<p>Now this is a good argument! You could indeed retire in 5 years after making $800K per year and then spend your time with family or pursue passion projects! The problems here are twofold:</p>
<p><strong>First</strong>, nobody does this. Instead, they spend more money. Of course, some of it will be saved, but the main thing that happens when people find themselves with far more money than needed for their family’s security is that they spend it. Bigger houses, more trips, elite schools for the kids. These make you feel well-off compared to your neighbors but don’t push you much higher on that flat curve.</p>
<p><strong>Second</strong>, people find value in being useful. There’s a reason why so many struggle in retirement. Even with a rigid FIRE plan, you’ll still want to work afterward on something interesting. So why not find that now?</p>
<p>What’s actually happening? Lifestyle creep. I think this is 90% of why people feel they could never work on something more fun or meaningful for less money. They’ve already started to spend their new money, and now losing those things would hurt more than gaining them felt good. That damn hedonic treadmill.</p>
<h3 id="where-we-go-from-here">Where we go from here</h3>
<p>What am I saying? I’m asking you to think deeply about what you value. Money isn’t a core value. Value your own time as much as your spending habits suggest you do. This is the right logic for your well-being, even if the world stays as it is. Now for my last thought:</p>
<p>I’m obsessed with AI and the technological singularity. It’s a healthy time to step back, reflect on the fundamental values driving our behavior, and make changes. Wouldn’t it be silly to spend most of our waking hours working miserably on meaningless things, only to arrive in a second half of life in a world of abundance?</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2024-02-01:/hedonic-treadmill/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/hedonic-treadmill/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2024 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>The Treadmill</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/treekeepers_moonlight.png" alt="The Treekeepers Puddle Jumper"></p>
<p>Treekeepers VR is a networked VR game where up to 4 players can cooperate to navigate an oversized world and save a giant tree.</p>
<p>Treekeepers is in production on both Quest (standalone VR) and Steam (PC VR) with full cross-play functionality. See the <a href="https://togetheragainstudios.com/treekeepersvr/">Treekeepers VR Website</a> for links to all storefronts and more detail about the game.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="development">Development</h2>
<p>I began working on Treekeepers in June 2021, and my primary goal was to go significantly deeper into Unity and make a fully networked game. Very few co-op games existed in VR at the time (the area is still lacking), and my intention was to answer this need and create a game that 4 players could cooperate in within a static frame of reference (players move within a ship, and the ship moves through the world) while having to solve coordination challenges together.</p>
<p>I initially designed the project for SteamVR only using the SteamVR SDK but quickly realized that a VR game released only on PC would miss the majority of the userbase, as the (then Oculus) Quest 2 was quickly dominating the market. Treekeepers was a good fit for a mobile platform with its simple low-poly cel-shaded design, so I pivoted to using OpenXR about two months into the project to support VR interactions on both PC and mobile (Android) devices like the Quest 2.</p>
<p>By summer 2022, I had a releasable product, albeit only with one “world” available. I decided to push the game to early access to gather rapid feedback from real players, and after getting approved for both storefronts, Treekeepers released to early access on September 30, 2022.</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2022-10-01:/treekeepers-vr/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/treekeepers-vr/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Treekeepers VR</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[
    <div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
      <iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" loading="eager" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/q_1itpdiPb4?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video"></iframe>
    </div>

<p>The &ldquo;Human Joystick&rdquo; is an experimental VR movement system in which the player moves through the virtual environment by changing their physical location within their VR &ldquo;playspace&rdquo;.</p>
<p>A demo of the human joystick movement system, showing how the system can work on flat surfaces or terrain.</p>
<p>This was my first barebones VR project. Though I knew Unity going in, VR and 3D games in general have a lot of unique aspects that I wanted to learn about while trying to solve an actual problem, rather than following tutorials or demos online.</p>
<p>VR has some adoption problems in its current state. We all know of some of the main problems- the clunky headset, the nausea issues, and of course the pricetag. But one major problem that you don&rsquo;t really notice until you get into it, is the lack of a good solution for virtual movement.</p>
<p>I had been wondering about &ldquo;the human joystick&rdquo; as a potential a solution to this particular problem ever since getting into consumer VR in 2016.</p>
<p>In most modern VR systems, the player can move physically around the room if they choose. Some applications and games depend on this - they put you in a small space and rely on your physical movement in order to reach different areas and interact with things. But games that provide a more traditional sense of scale and allow players to move through large worlds cannot rely on physical motion, because their users are constrained by physical space. Because of this, you see all kinds of &ldquo;artificial&rdquo; locomotion systems in order to let people move around - some just like traditional 2D games that let users &ldquo;slide&rdquo; their playspaces around the world using a joystick, and others that adopt teleportation mechanics. Neither feel very natural as compared to actually walking, and some can be downright sickening.</p>
<p>My goal with this project was to solve this problem with a mixture of physical and artificial movement.</p>
<p>It works like this: When the player is standing near the center of their playspace, physical VR movement applies. The player can move around and interact with things with their actual bodies. But once the player moves further from the center, the plaspace starts to move with them in the same direction as the vector from the center of the player&rsquo;s space to their current position. This allows for some of the benefits that physical movement experiences have, while allowing the players to more naturally move through an infinite amount of space.</p>
<p>I experimented with several speeds, both static and scaling with the distance between the center and the player. I also experimented with the size of the physical movement &ldquo;deadzone&rdquo; and with vertical and constrained movement across hills, valleys, and buildings.</p>
<hr>
<table>
  <thead>
      <tr>
          <th style="text-align: center">


















<div class="paige-image">
    




























    



    

    
        

        

        
    
        

        

        
    
        

        
            

    



    







    





    



    






















<img   class="img-fluid "  crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/human_joystick_centered.jpg"   style="display:block; height: auto; margin:0 auto; width: 60%"   >


</div>
</th>
          <th style="text-align: left"><em>View from the player&rsquo;s perspective looking at the guides at his feet. With the white dot in the red deadzone, the player isn&rsquo;t moving.</em></th>
      </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
      <tr>
          <td style="text-align: center">


















<div class="paige-image">
    




























    



    

    
        

        

        
    
        

        

        
    
        

        
            

    



    







    





    



    






















<img   class="img-fluid "  crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/human_joystick_moving.jpg"   style="display:block; height: auto; margin:0 auto; width: 60%"   >


</div>
</td>
          <td style="text-align: left"><strong><em>When the white dot is in the green area, the player moves in that direction. Here I am moving forward and left at about half of max speed.</em></strong></td>
      </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<hr>
<p>Eventually I found some good default values and the system worked, but there were some unforeseen problems: First, it was more difficult to center yourself within the playspace without looking at the visible guides I put at the player&rsquo;s feet than I expected. Second and more importantly, when you were already moving in one direction, it was not as simple as I thought to start moving in another direction accurately without fully returning to center, which was an immersion breaker.</p>
<p>Ultimately I put the project up for others to view but have not expanded it into a full experience or released it on any marketplaces. Feel free to download the Unity project and try it on your own VR setup if you&rsquo;re curious.</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2020-01-01:/human-joystick/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/human-joystick/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Human Joystick VR</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Note from 2025: The Answering Machine is a proof-of-concept system that I built using pre-LLM natural language processing (NLP), specifically NLTK, to produce answers to questions asked about data in plain English.</p>
<p>Looking back, this project was a great insight into what LLMs immediately allowed that was incredibly difficult before.  This project was several months of work that the openAI sdk would probably have allowed in a few weeks - and that few weeks would have been mostly frontend design and a bit of prompting.</p>
<p><strong>Try it here:</strong> <a href="http://voicequery-dev.s3-website-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/">http://voicequery-dev.s3-website-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/</a>
<strong>Github:</strong> <a href="https://github.com/hockenmaier/voicequery">https://github.com/hockenmaier/voicequery</a></p>
<p><img src="/images/answering_machine_uploads.png" alt="Answering Machine homepage"></p>
<p>This proof-of-concept system uses natural language processing (NLP) to produce answers to questions asked about data in plain english.</p>
<p>It is designed with simplicity in mind - upload any columnar dataset and start asking questions and getting answers. It uses some advanced NLP algorithms to make assumptions about what data you&rsquo;re asking about, and will let you correct those assumptions for follow-up questions if they&rsquo;re wrong.</p>
<p>It is built entirely out of serverless components, which means there is no cost to maintain or run it other than the traffic the system receives.</p>
<hr>
<h3 id="how-to">How-to</h3>
<p>On a desktop or tablet, click the link in the header to navigate to the answering machine. For now it isn&rsquo;t optimized for smartphone-sized screens.</p>
<p>In order to use the answering machine, you can either select one of the existing data sets such as &ldquo;HR Activity Sample&rdquo; or upload one of your own using the homepage of the site:</p>
<p><img src="/images/answering_machine_uploads.png" alt="Answering Machine homepage"></p>
<p>To upload your own, click in the upload area or just drag a file straight from your desktop. For now, use csv data files. Excel and other spreadsheet programs can easily save data in the csv format using the &ldquo;File &gt; Save As&rdquo; or similar option in the menu. Each file needs a unique name.</p>
<p>When you hit the upload button, the site may not appear to change until the file is uploaded, at which point you&rsquo;ll see it appear in the box labeled &ldquo;Ask Your Data Anything&rdquo; below. Click on your file to start using it with the answering machine, or click the red trash can icon to delete it.</p>
<p>There are no user accounts in this system yet, so the data you upload might be seen by other users using the system. Try not to use sensitive data for now.</p>
<p>When you enter a dataset, you&rsquo;ll see a view that presents you with a quite a bit of information:</p>
<p><img src="/images/answering_machine_hr.png" alt="Main view of Answering Machine"></p>
<p>The only part you need to focus on right now is the information panel. This panel lists out all of the fields (columns), data types of those fields, and some sample data from a few records in your data set:</p>
<p><img src="/images/answering_machine_info.png" alt="Answering Machine info panel"></p>
<p>You can use this panel to start to formulate questions you might have about the data. If you see number values, you might ask about averages, maximums, or other math that might otherwise take some time to calculate. If you see a date, you can ask questions about the data in certain time periods.</p>
<p>Many datasets also contain fields that only have a few specific allowed values. When the answering machine sees less than 15 unique values in any field, the data type will be a &ldquo;List&rdquo; and it lists them right out under the sample values table. You can use this type of value to ask questions about records containing those specific values. For example in the HR data set, you might only be interested in data where the &ldquo;Education&rdquo; field&rsquo;s value is &ldquo;High School&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Now look to the query bar to start asking your data questions:</p>
<p><img src="/images/answering_machine_query.png" alt="Answering Machine query bar"></p>
<p>The types of questions that will currently be automatically detected and answered are:</p>
<ul>
<li>Counts of records where certain conditions are true</li>
<li>Math questions such as averages, medians, maximums, and minimums</li>
</ul>
<p>These types of questions can be made specific by using qualifying statements with prepositional phrases like &ldquo;in 2019&rdquo; or adjective phrases like &ldquo;male&rdquo; or &ldquo;entry-level.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Combining these two ideas, you can ask specific questions with any number of qualifiers, such as: &ldquo;What was the median salary of male employees in the engineering department 5 years ago?&rdquo;</p>
<p>Upon hitting the &ldquo;ask&rdquo; button (or hitting Enter), the answering machine will do its best to answer your question, and will show you all of its work in this format:</p>
<p><img src="/images/answering_machine_answer.png" alt="Answering Machine response"></p>
<hr>
<h3 id="architecture">Architecture</h3>
<p>The Answering Machine is a purely &ldquo;serverless&rdquo; application, meaning that there is no server hosting the various components of the application until those components are needed by a user. This is true for the database, the file storage, the static website, the backend compute, and the API orchestration.</p>
<p>For the cloud nerds out there, <a href="https://martinfowler.com/articles/serverless.html">here is a great article</a> by Martin Fowler on what exactly &ldquo;serverless&rdquo; means, especially in terms of the backend compute portion which is arguably the most valuable part of the application to be serverless. For reference, I am using Martin&rsquo;s 2nd definition of &ldquo;serverless&rdquo; here.</p>
<p>This is a high-level map of all of the components that make the answering machine work in its current (June 2020) state. The API gateways, cloudwatch events, and some triggers &ldquo;given for free&rdquo; by AWS are left out of this for readability:</p>
<p><img src="/images/answering_machine_architecture.png" alt="Serverless Architecture of the Answering Machine app"></p>
<p>The full suite of lambdas and persistent storage services that make up the answering machine.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="features">Features</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Upload any dataset</strong>: Users can upload columnar datasets (CSV format) and start querying.</li>
<li><strong>Real-time responses</strong>: Questions are answered instantly, with NLP driving the interpretation and response generation.</li>
<li><strong>Serverless architecture</strong>: The system incurs no hosting costs apart from traffic-based expenses.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 id="how-to-1">How-to</h2>
<p>On a desktop or tablet, click the link above to navigate to <strong>The Answering Machine</strong>. Currently, it is not optimized for smartphones.</p>
<p>To use the system:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p><strong>Upload a dataset</strong>: Drag and drop a CSV file or use the upload button.</p>
<ul>
<li>Example files like &ldquo;HR Activity Sample&rdquo; are available for testing.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Start querying</strong>: Select a dataset and type your question in the query bar.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p><img src="/images/answering_machine_hr.png" alt="HR dataset view"></p>
<ol start="3">
<li>Use the <strong>information panel</strong> to understand dataset fields, data types, and sample values. This helps formulate more specific questions.</li>
</ol>
<p><img src="/images/answering_machine_info.png" alt="Info panel"></p>
<hr>
<h2 id="query-types">Query Types</h2>
<p>The system currently supports:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Counts</strong>: “How many employees joined in 2020?”</li>
<li><strong>Mathematical questions</strong>: Averages, medians, maximums, and minimums.</li>
<li><strong>Filters</strong>: Combine conditions like “What’s the average salary of engineers in 2019?”</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 id="concept-matching">Concept Matching</h2>
<p>If the NLP system misinterprets a query, users can create <strong>concepts</strong> to align query terms with dataset fields.</p>
<p><img src="/images/answering_machine_query.png" alt="Answering Machine query bar"></p>
<p>Concepts override the system’s auto-matching logic, ensuring accurate data interpretation.</p>
<p><img src="/images/answering_machine_concept.png" alt="Concept creation"></p>
<hr>
<h2 id="architecture-1">Architecture</h2>
<p><strong>The Answering Machine</strong> is a purely serverless application. Its backend consists of AWS Lambda functions, API Gateway, and other serverless components.</p>
<p><img src="/images/answering_machine_architecture.png" alt="Serverless architecture"></p>
<p>For more details, check out <a href="https://martinfowler.com/articles/serverless.html">Martin Fowler&rsquo;s article on serverless computing</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p>Feel free to explore the tool and test various datasets. Remember, this is a proof-of-concept system with no user accounts, so avoid uploading sensitive data.</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2019-07-03:/answering-machine/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/answering-machine/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2019 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>The Answering Machine</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<hr>
<p>Land War is an 8-player strategy game I developed as a solo project and released to Steam in March of 2019.<br>
This game was intended to have low art requirements and simple interaction rules that result in deep strategic gameplay.</p>
<p>The core concept is that of an ultra-simplified real-time-strategy game. Each player is represented by a color and can grow their territory by moving in any direction. The strategic elements occur when players encounter other players and have to make choices about which side of their land to defend or give up. Players can use the structure of the map and the coordinated action of other players to gain defensible footholds in order to take more area and eventually be the last player on the board.</p>

    <div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
      <iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" loading="eager" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/5Q8PAuWcmQc?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video"></iframe>
    </div>

<p>A full game of the final product released on Steam played on a Windows computer.</p>
<h3 id="development">Development</h3>
<p>I built Land War over the course of 7 months and 400 hours of work using Unity with C#. Though art requirements were intentionally low for a video game, I still had to produce several hundred static graphics and GIFs, and commissioned custom music for the menu and gameplay.</p>
<p>This project is one of my favorite examples of what can be done in relatively little time with a focused vision and a constant eye on scope creep. From the very start, I knew that a key to making compelling software was to flesh out the core concept before all else. This is why I started on the most fundamental strategic interaction of the players and built an MVP version of the game without a menu, sound, art, or even a win condition.</p>
<p>I started the project on a Memorial Day Monday, and by Friday had a rudimentary prototype playable with 8 players on Nintendo Joy-Con controllers paired to a Windows machine via Bluetooth.<br>
This is what the project looked like for my first play-test with other people 5 days in:</p>



















<div class="paige-image">
    




























    



    

    
        

        

        
    
        

        

        
    
        

        
            

    



    







    





    



    






















<img  alt="Land War 4-day MVP"   class="img-fluid "  crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/land_war_mvp.gif"   style="display:block; height: auto; margin:0 auto; width: 50%"   >


</div>

<p><em>4-player game played with Nintendo Joy-Cons on a build of the game from 5 days into development.</em></p>
<p>From there, I continued to work on depth and full feature functionality including menus, a tutorial, a map generator, a dynamic scoring and round system, better sound and sprite graphics, different play modes and settings, and support for many controllers. I released the game with very little marketing aside from some Reddit posts and a physical handout at E3 but was happy to receive positive reviews and several hundred purchases of the game.</p>



















<div class="paige-image">
    




























    



    

    
        

        

        
    
        

        

        
    
        

        
            

    



    







    





    



    






















<img  alt="Player Select screen"   class="img-fluid "  crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/land_war_player_select.png"   style="display:block; height: auto; margin:0 auto; width: 50%"   >


</div>

<p><em>Player Select screen. Supporting menu and player controls across hundreds of controller types was one of the largest unforeseen challenges in developing Land War.</em></p>



















<div class="paige-image">
    




























    



    

    
        

        

        
    
        

        

        
    
        

        
            

    



    







    





    



    






















<img  alt="Settings menu"   class="img-fluid "  crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/land_war_settings.png"   style="display:block; height: auto; margin:0 auto; width: 50%"   >


</div>

<p><em>Settings menu. Most interesting mechanics I found while developing the game were added as options to keep the game interesting here.</em></p>



















<div class="paige-image">
    




























    



    

    
        

        

        
    
        

        

        
    
        

        
            

    



    







    





    



    






















<img  alt="E3 marketing material"   class="img-fluid "  crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="http://localhost:1313/images/land_war_e3.png"   style="display:block; height: auto; margin:0 auto; width: 50%"   >


</div>

<p><em>The only physical marketing material developed for Land War. Several hundred Steam keys (copies of the game) were handed out during the E3 convention in 2019.</em></p>

    <div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
      <iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" loading="eager" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/BylKEPF4EeU?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video"></iframe>
    </div>

<p><em>Land War&rsquo;s Steam release announcement trailer.</em></p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2019-03-01:/land-war/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/land-war/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Land War</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>First Ten is an educational app containing information about the U.S. Bill of Rights, accessible on Google devices and smart speakers. It uses a VUI (voice user interface) only, meaning there is no visual way to interact with the app.</p>
<p><strong>Try it here:</strong> <a href="https://assistant.google.com/services/a/uid/00000036f6a580ed">https://assistant.google.com/services/a/uid/00000036f6a580ed</a>
<strong>Github:</strong> <a href="https://github.com/hockenmaier/billofrights">https://github.com/hockenmaier/billofrights</a></p>
<p>Like Alexa skills, Google actions can be accessed through search or by simply asking for their names in Google Home smart speakers. Ask your Google Home or Android device, &ldquo;Can I speak to First Ten?&rdquo; in order to try it.</p>
<h3 id="architecture">Architecture</h3>
<p>First Ten&rsquo;s backend is built in the serverless AWS services Lambda and DynamoDB, and its frontend—the engine that parses your voice into different &ldquo;intents&rdquo; and parameters—is built on Google&rsquo;s Dialogflow.</p>
<p><img src="/images/first_ten_architecture.png" alt="Serverless Architecture of the First Ten app"></p>
<hr>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2018-05-19:/first-ten/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/first-ten/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Sat, 19 May 2018 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>First Ten</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p><strong>Raspberry Pi Control Panel</strong> is a hardware project I designed in 2016 to manage home automation systems. The project involved designing a custom 3D-printed case for a Raspberry Pi microcomputer with a touchscreen interface.</p>
<p>Links:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/hockenmaier/RaspberryPiControlPanel">GitHub</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:2524560">Thingiverse</a></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>I created this panel display in 2026 to control much of the home automation I used in my Studio City apartment. Mainly a hardware project, I designed and 3D-printed a case and frame for the touchscreen and raspberry pi microcomputer in order to mount them to the wall. The software running the control panel is SaaS, but I did write a custom html wrapper to control the orientation and settings of the site, which is available on the github linked above.</p>
<p>Update in 2025: This panel is still my main view into my home automation in my new house in Sherman Oaks, almost 10 years in with no modification!</p>
<p>Here&rsquo;s a video to see the panel in action:</p>
<h2 id="hahahugoshortcode2s0hbhb">
    <div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
      <iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" loading="eager" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/iFGmm-ijJvE?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video"></iframe>
    </div>
</h2>
<p>Feel free to explore the linked repositories for schematics and source code.</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2016-01-01:/raspberry-pi-panel/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/raspberry-pi-panel/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Raspberry Pi Control Panel</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
