













    
        
    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    

    

    
        
    







    

    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"  xml:lang="en-us"  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            

            
                
            

            
                <link href="https://hockenworks.com/tags/system-design/" rel="self" type="text/html"/>
            
        
            

            

            
                <link href="https://hockenworks.com/tags/system-design/rss.xml" rel="alternate" type="application/rss+xml"/>
            
        

        

        

        <description>Recent content</description>

        
            <language>en-us</language>
        

        
            <lastBuildDate>2025-12-10 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</lastBuildDate>
        

        <link>https://hockenworks.com/tags/system-design/</link>

        

        <title>System Design · Tags · hockenworks</title>

        

        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>My <a href="/raspberry-pi-panel">home automation dashboard</a> broke down in two ways this year. Hardware, then software. My wife and I really liked this dashboard. It saved us from pulling out our phones and getting sucked into emails or social media while we were supposed to be living our lives.</p>
<p>Both breakdowns ended up in rebuilds. The hardware obviously solved by 3D modeling and printing and the software part became another problem I would vibe code - no - vibe engineer - my way out of.</p>
<p>After rebuilding, it is totally different. But cooler perhaps? And everything it uses should last many decades this time, instead of just one decade.</p>
<p>Let me break it down for you:</p>
<hr>
<h1 id="the-build">The Build</h1>
<h2 id="hardware">Hardware</h2>
<p><strong>First breakdown:</strong> the screen finally died with one of the LED rows failing. It was a trooper. This meant updating to a <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B07P8P3X6M">new version of the screen</a></p>
<p>And the slight physical difference of the board components meant I had to redesign how I mounted it to the wall, from a complete enclosure that attached via mounting tape to a new slim set of custom brackets I made taking advantage of the standard screw mounts on the screen’s PCB:</p>
<div class="paige-row-wide">
  <div style="display:grid; grid-template-columns:repeat(2, minmax(0,1fr)); gap:15px;">
      































    













    



    























<img   class="rounded-3 w-100"  crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/old-enclosure.webp"    >


      































    













    



    























<img   class="rounded-3 w-100"  crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/new-mount.webp"    >

</div>
</div>

<p>Old enclosure left, new mounts right (almost invisible in white like the wall). It&rsquo;s much more secure, much less plastic and a good general purpose mount for raw PCB 7-inch displays. Printed in <a href="https://us.store.bambulab.com/products/abs-filament?srsltid=AfmBOopWZrOOFNoQS26lx71-xycEFqOJ3GG7-FllK-4zYhuttsgHJYb5&id=40475105493128">glossy white ABS</a> to last forever and match the walls.</p>
<p>I posted them on Thingiverse here: <a href="https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:7226385">https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:7226385</a></p>
<h2 id="software">Software</h2>
<p><strong>Second breakdown:</strong> And the timing here was perfectly ironic - about a month after I got this new screen and made the slim mount, the software I was using to display the dashboard just gave up. That software was called <a href="http://actiontiles.com/">ActionTiles</a> and yes, that domain is gone because everything about the product disappeared about 20 days before I am posting this. <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/SmartThings/comments/1p2ya18/action_tiles/">The subreddit</a> didn’t know what was happening but as best I can tell, it sounds like the solo developer unfortunately passed away several years ago.</p>
<p>Unfortunately ActionTiles was not open source for me to host it myself, nor does it seem worth the effort to integrate with the SmartThings API myself (I am considering moving to an open source home hub after lackluster support for SmartThings anyway), so my next course of action was to vibe code myself another dashboard. This one is less focused on home automation but equally useful to us.</p>
<p>Over the course of some prompting and <a href="https://openai.com/codex/">Codex</a> PRs, the final result shows:</p>
<ul>
<li>The weather now and for the next week</li>
<li>Upcoming birthdays on my wife&rsquo;s and my shared birthday Google sheet</li>
<li>How many months old baby Alice is</li>
<li>Upcoming SpaceX launches visible from my house, with pulsing backgrounds an hour before each launch</li>
<li>The time and date in a nice format</li>
<li>Other astronomical events like meteor showers and eclipses</li>
<li>Plus holidays and solstices</li>
</ul>
<p>Here is the end result:</p>
<p><style>
  .home-list-wrapper {
    width: 800px;
    height: 480px;
    position: relative;
    left: 50%;
    transform: translateX(-50%);
    margin: 1em 0;
  }

  .home-list-wrapper iframe {
    position: absolute;
    top: 0;
    left: 0;
    width: 800px;
    height: 480px;
    border: 0;
  }
</style>

<div class="home-list-wrapper">
  <iframe
    class="lazy-iframe"
    data-src="/html/home-list.html"
    src="about:blank"
    loading="lazy"
  ></iframe>
</div>

<div class="home-list-caption" style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
  
</div>

<div style="text-align:center;">
  <a href="/html/home-list.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"
     style="display:inline-block;padding:.5rem 1rem;border:1px solid #ccc;border-radius:.5rem;text-decoration:none">
    Open In Standalone Tab
  </a>
</div>

Apologies to readers on phone.. this dashboard is hardcoded for fixed size a 16/9 layout.</p>
<p>I was aiming for clean, simple, readable, and things Kaitlin and I were always looking at our phones to find out. It doesn&rsquo;t do the same things as the previous dashboard but it reduces the number of times my phone has to come out even more than the previous one. We&rsquo;ve been really enjoying it!</p>
<p>I learned some interesting things throughout this process:</p>
<ul>
<li>There are surprisingly good APIs out there for weather and forecasts despite the absolutely <strong>abysmal</strong> mobile weather app market</li>
<li>Meteor showers don&rsquo;t need an API because they happen the same time every year</li>
<li>Eclipses basically don&rsquo;t either cause you can just hard code out all the eclipse data with a few kilobytes of data for decades into the future</li>
<li>The SpaceX upcoming launches list, despite being fully open and probably the simplest of all the data sets here to work with, was by far the most challenging for my AI assistant to read from. This is where the hosted AI coders fall down a lot: their environments simply are different than the ones we are using and they have a hard time accessing stuff that should be open. When they finally figure out how to do that, they have such short memories that they forget things like “only show launches from Vandenberg&quot;.</li>
</ul>
<p>As with almost everything on this site, it&rsquo;s totally open source and this one&rsquo;s contained in a single ~1000-line html file. If you want, you can throw this into your favorite AI model and ask it to change it to events you care about and weather in your location.</p>
<p> 
 </p>
<h1 id="vibe-coding-or-vibe-engineering">Vibe Coding? Or Vibe Engineering?</h1>
<p>Here is where I launch into another breakdown of AI software development. I feel the need to write about it every time I wrap another project, because it&rsquo;s changing so quickly.</p>
<p>I used <a href="https://openai.com/codex/">Codex</a>, mostly, to build this dashboard. I like Codex <a href="/on-ai-software-development-2/#autonomous-coding-agents">because it makes more sense to me to have AI models make discrete code changes and pull-request them into my project rather than trying to work in the same IDE as the AI</a>.</p>
<p>Every time I &ldquo;vibe code&rdquo; something new, I find new ways to be amazed and disappointed by these thinking machines. The main takeaway I had this time is, despite the amazing speed of development, I just can&rsquo;t see anyone other than an engineer getting a workable software product out of these models in 2025.</p>
<p>This is why the term “vibe engineering” is growing on me. Now that the basic code writes itself, what I see engineers doing all day are things <em>around</em> the code like making sure environments work and making sure features don&rsquo;t conflict. And, most key of all: determining the actual specific logic of the product. Check out the detail in my original prompt for this dashboard:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Please create a new dashboard at <a href="https://hockenworks.com/html/home-calendar.html">https://hockenworks.com/html/home-calendar.html</a>.</p>
<p>It will function as a standalone servable page like <a href="https://hockenworks.com/html/agent-mode-solar-system-self-contained.html">https://hockenworks.com/html/agent-mode-solar-system-self-contained.html</a>.</p>
<p>This is going to be permanently displayed on a small 16/9 touchscreen in our kitchen running on chromium on Raspberry Pi.</p>
<p>On the right part of the screen (a full square aligned with the left side of the 16 by 9 screen) will be a calendar. That calendar should display the current week and next 7 weeks on a 7 by seven grid, using your stylistic preferences to denote the dates and days of the week. Draw a bold line horizontally and vertically through month breaks with a clear delineation between the two.</p>
<p>This calendar should use public data which does not require any sign-in to fetch:</p>
<ul>
<li>All US Holidays</li>
<li>First day of each season, dates when the time changes</li>
<li>Special astronomical events like eclipses or visible meteor showers etc (list time of day for these ones, for example &ldquo;Solar Eclipse at 2:11 PM&rdquo; listed on its date</li>
<li>SpaceX launches from Vandenberg ONLY</li>
<li>Anything else you see fit to list here (let me know if you&rsquo;ve added anything when you finish)</li>
</ul>
<p>Come up with theme colors and icons for each foreseeable event (such as a clock for time change days, spaceship for launches, egg for Easter, etc, and fall back to just text for unknown events.</p>
<p>On the left half of the screen, full remaining width (to the left of the square calendar on the right) should be in this order:</p>
<p>Time in the format: 12:42 PM
Date in the format: Nov 23rd</p>
<p>Both of these should have fun, randomized animated transitions. Use whatever html and css tricks you want to do this, just make sure it&rsquo;s all self-contained code and libraries you can include in hockenworks so this thing never breaks.</p>
<p>Then have a few lines which list any upcoming holidays or events in the next 4 weeks verbally in the format: Solar Eclipse coming up next Tuesday, February 17th at 2:11 PM or Solar Eclipse coming up February 17th at 2:11 PM</p>
<p>You should use &ldquo;this&rdquo; and &ldquo;next&rdquo; for upcoming days of the week, or leave part that out if it&rsquo;s further than 2 weeks out.</p>
<p>Do this on a black background with primarily white and light pastel colorings.
New data such as holidays should be fetch hourly, if you need to decide on a frequency.
Remember, this will be permanently displayed and always be up to date so account for any edge cases.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The combination of <a href="/vision-is-the-last-hurdle-before-agi">AIs really not being able to see yet</a> and also being unable to test on the physical Raspberry Pi device which had some unique properties, Codex simply failed at the visual calendar. So I pivoted to a text-only dashboard.</p>
<p>But here is where I think the term vibe coding should become &ldquo;vibe engineering.&rdquo; Look at that prompt, which was still not nearly detailed enough to produce what I wanted. There were at least ten more prompts, several as long as that, after pivoting to a text-only dashboard to get it working well. This wasn&rsquo;t to correct AI mistakes, but to get to the level of precision in <em>what I actually wanted out of the dashboard</em>. You have to be <strong>SO</strong> precise in your prompting to get what you want. Precise like an engineer, not an idea guy.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s much faster to have AI code for you than to write it yourself. But if you are spending this much time designing detailed logic and building up the knowledge of what is feasible and what isn&rsquo;t, in my opinion, you&rsquo;re an engineer.</p>
<p>The AI also lacks any touchpoints with the real world - in this case, my old chromium running on Raspberry Pi was not testable for the AI, and so I had to run back and forth from my office to the dashboard to see if things scaled correctly. This is not just a problem for niche projects like this. I have seen AI code not work on certain devices and browsers in “normal” web projects at work too, and fixing these things is what <em>engineers</em> do.</p>
<p>And then, potentially the most egregious consistent failure mode (and this really needs to be fixed): AI still loves to mock up fake data. This happened multiple times in this project where AI just started ignoring API calls and making up dates and times for things to happen. This tendency feels like the labs are trying to game benchmarks by making their software agents make plausible-looking successes that a human evaluator might miss and accidentally rate highly - but made up data is far, far worse for real world use, especially for non-engineers who are less likely to catch it.</p>
<p>Even with all of these problems preventing these models from “democratizing engineering” - they are still amazing tools. I would not have known where to start on many of these features without the AI simply knowing things I didn’t, like the open weather API and the method of accessing Google sheets as a CSV export. Even as an engineer, there&rsquo;s no chance I would have whipped up a custom dashboard to do all this and solve my dashboardlessness before the era of AI.</p>
<p>These models are liars and cheats that are also blind, but somehow they’re still greatly expanding what it’s possible to build, and how fast we can build it. Just recognize that once you are building and running real software that actually fits your intentions, you are, effectively, an engineer.</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:hockenworks.com,2025-12-10:/raspberry-pi-panel-2/</guid>

                
                    <link>https://hockenworks.com/raspberry-pi-panel-2/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Dashboard Breakdowns</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>The Answering Machine is a proof-of-concept system that I built using <strong>pre-LLM</strong> natural language processing (NLP), specifically NLTK, to produce answers to questions asked about data in plain English.</p>
<p>Looking back, this project was a great insight into what LLMs immediately allowed that was incredibly difficult before. This project was several months of work that the openAI sdk would probably have allowed in a few weeks - and that few weeks would have been mostly frontend design and a bit of prompting.</p>
<p><strong>Try it here:</strong> <a href="http://voicequery-dev.s3-website-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/">http://voicequery-dev.s3-website-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/</a>
<strong>Github:</strong> <a href="https://github.com/hockenmaier/voicequery">https://github.com/hockenmaier/voicequery</a></p>
<p>The system uses natural language processing to produce answers to questions asked about data in plain English.</p>
<p>It is designed with simplicity in mind—upload any columnar dataset and start asking questions and getting answers. It uses advanced NLP algorithms to make assumptions about what data you&rsquo;re asking about and lets you correct those assumptions for follow-up questions if they&rsquo;re wrong.</p>
<p>It is built entirely out of serverless components, which means there is no cost to maintain or run it other than the traffic the system receives.</p>
<h2 id="how-to">How-to</h2>
<p>On a desktop or tablet, click the link in the header to navigate to the Answering Machine. For now, it isn&rsquo;t optimized for smartphone-sized screens.</p>
<p>In order to use the Answering Machine, you can either select one of the existing datasets, such as &ldquo;HR Activity Sample,&rdquo; or upload one of your own using the homepage of the site:</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="Answering Machine homepage"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/answering_machine_uploads.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 720px; width: 100%"   >


    
</div>

<p>To upload your own, click in the upload area or just drag a file straight from your desktop. For now, use CSV data files. Excel and other spreadsheet programs can easily save data in the CSV format using the &ldquo;File &gt; Save As&rdquo; or similar option in the menu. Each file needs a unique name.</p>
<p>When you hit the upload button, the site may not appear to change until the file is uploaded, at which point you&rsquo;ll see it appear in the box labeled &ldquo;Ask Your Data Anything&rdquo; below. Click on your file to start using it with the Answering Machine, or click the red trash can icon to delete it.</p>
<p>There are no user accounts in this system yet, so the data you upload might be seen by other users using the system. Try not to use sensitive data for now.</p>
<h3 id="asking-questions">Asking questions</h3>
<p>When you enter a dataset, you&rsquo;ll see a view that presents you with quite a bit of information:</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    







    





    



    























<img  alt="Answering Machine main view"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/answering_machine_hr.png"   style="height: auto; width: 100%"   >


    
</div>

<p>The only part you need to focus on right now is the information panel. This panel lists out all the fields (columns), data types of those fields, and some sample data from a few records in your dataset:</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="Answering Machine info panel"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/answering_machine_info.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 720px; width: 100%"   >


    
</div>

<p>You can use this panel to start to formulate questions you might have about the data. If you see number values, you might ask about averages, maximums, or other math that might otherwise take some time to calculate. If you see a date, you can ask questions about the data in certain time periods.</p>
<p>Many datasets also contain fields that only have a few specific allowed values. When the Answering Machine sees fewer than 15 unique values in any field, the data type will be a &ldquo;List&rdquo; and it lists them right out under the sample values table. You can use this type of value to ask questions about records containing those specific values. For example, in the HR dataset, you might only be interested in data where the &ldquo;Education&rdquo; field&rsquo;s value is &ldquo;High School.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Now look to the query bar to start asking your data questions:</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="Answering Machine query bar"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/answering_machine_query.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 720px; width: 100%"   >


    
</div>

<p>The types of questions that will currently be automatically detected and answered are:</p>
<ul>
<li>Counts of records where certain conditions are true</li>
<li>Math questions such as averages, medians, maximums, and minimums</li>
</ul>
<p>These types of questions can be made specific by using qualifying statements with prepositional phrases like &ldquo;in 2019&rdquo; or adjective phrases like &ldquo;male&rdquo; or &ldquo;entry-level.&rdquo;</p>
<p>Combining these two ideas, you can ask specific questions with any number of qualifiers, such as:<br>
<em>&ldquo;What was the median salary of male employees in the engineering department 5 years ago?&rdquo;</em></p>
<p>Upon hitting the &ldquo;Ask&rdquo; button (or hitting Enter), the Answering Machine will do its best to answer your question and will show you all of its work in this format:</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="Answering Machine response"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/answering_machine_answer.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 720px; width: 100%"   >


    
</div>

<p>The last line in the response is the Answering Machine&rsquo;s answer. In this case, it is telling you the metric you asked for with all your stipulations is <strong>6871.6 dollars.</strong></p>
<p>Moving up, you see a series of assessments that the Answering Machine has made in order to filter and identify the data you are asking about. Statements like &ldquo;Best auto-detected Numeric Subject Found: salary with column: Compensation (Monthly)&rdquo; provide a glimpse into one of the Answering Machine&rsquo;s most advanced features, which uses a selection of NLP techniques to compare words and phrases that are similar in meaning, ultimately matching things you are asking about to fields and values that actually exist in your database.</p>
<p>At the very top of the response is how the Answering Machine&rsquo;s nested grammar parsing logic actually parsed your question, with some specific pieces color-coded:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Green</strong> chunks indicate &ldquo;subjects&rdquo; that were detected. Subjects are what the Answering Machine thinks you&rsquo;re asking &ldquo;about.&rdquo; These should represent both the main subject and other supporting subjects in your question.</li>
<li><strong>Purple</strong> chunks are conditions. These are the things that the Answering Machine thinks you are trying to use to &ldquo;specify&rdquo; or filter data.</li>
</ul>
<p>Now that your question is answered, you might notice that some new green and purple colored bubbles have appeared in the sections of your screen labeled &ldquo;New Subjects&rdquo; and &ldquo;New Conditions.&rdquo; We&rsquo;ll call these &ldquo;lexicon&rdquo;:</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="Answering Machine subjects and conditions"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/answering_machine_lexicon.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 400px; width: 100%"   >


    
</div>

<h3 id="forming-concepts">Forming Concepts</h3>
<p>If the Answering Machine already understood what you were asking and successfully matched it to fields and values in your data, you don&rsquo;t have to do anything with these. But often you will be using domain-specific lexicon, or the auto-matching algorithm simply won&rsquo;t pick the correct value. These situations are what concepts are for.</p>
<p>To create a concept, click and drag on the green or purple &ldquo;lexicon&rdquo; bubble and move it out into the blank middle area of the screen. Then click and drag the field or field value from the info-panel at the top of the screen and drop it right on top of that bubble. You&rsquo;ll see both the data bubble and the lexicon bubble included in a larger gray bubble, which represents the concept:</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="Answering Machine concept"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/answering_machine_concept.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 200px; width: 100%"   >


    
</div>

<p>You can add more lexicon bubbles to this concept if they mean the same thing, but you can only use one data bubble.</p>
<p>Concepts override the Answering Machine&rsquo;s auto-matching logic. If you ask another question containing a subject or condition that is now matched by a user to a data value, that data value will be used instead of the auto-match. If the concept isn&rsquo;t working well, you can delete it by dragging all of the nested bubbles out of it either into the blank middle area or into the colored panel they originally came from.</p>
<p>Feel free to play around with new datasets and questions, and use the contact section of this site if you have comments or questions. When you ask questions or create/modify concepts, that data will automatically be saved to the server in real-time. You can close the page anytime and come back to your dataset to keep asking questions.</p>
<p>Remember that there are no user accounts, meaning you can share your dataset and work in tandem with others! But again, please do not upload sensitive data to this proof-of-concept tool as it will be available for other users to see and query.</p>
<h2 id="architecture">Architecture</h2>
<p>The Answering Machine is a purely &ldquo;serverless&rdquo; application, meaning that there is no server hosting the various components of the application until those components are needed by a user. This is true for the database, the file storage, the static website, the backend compute, and the API orchestration.</p>
<p>For the cloud nerds out there, <a href="https://martinfowler.com/articles/serverless.html">here is a great article</a> by Martin Fowler on what exactly &ldquo;serverless&rdquo; means, especially in terms of the backend compute portion, which is arguably the most valuable part of the application to be serverless. For reference, I am using Martin&rsquo;s 2nd definition of &ldquo;serverless&rdquo; here.</p>
<p>This is a high-level map of all of the components that make the Answering Machine work in its current (June 2020) state. The API gateways, CloudWatch events, and some triggers &ldquo;given for free&rdquo; by AWS are left out of this for readability:</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="Serverless Architecture of the Answering Machine app"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/answering_machine_architecture.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 720px; width: 100%"   >


    
</div>

<p>The full suite of lambdas and persistent storage services that make up the Answering Machine.</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:hockenworks.com,2019-07-03:/answering-machine/</guid>

                
                    <link>https://hockenworks.com/answering-machine/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2019 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>The Answering Machine</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p>Land War is an 8-player strategy game I developed as a solo project and released to Steam in March of 2019.<br>
This game was intended to have low art requirements and simple interaction rules that result in deep strategic gameplay.</p>
<p>The core concept is that of an ultra-simplified real-time-strategy game. Each player is represented by a color and can grow their territory by moving in any direction. The strategic elements occur when players encounter other players and have to make choices about which side of their land to defend or give up. Players can use the structure of the map and the coordinated action of other players to gain defensible footholds in order to take more area and eventually be the last player on the board.</p>

    <div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
      <iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" loading="eager" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/5Q8PAuWcmQc?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video"></iframe>
    </div>

<p>A full game of the final product released on Steam played on a Windows computer.</p>
<h3 id="development">Development</h3>
<p>I built Land War over the course of 7 months and 400 hours of work using Unity with C#. Though art requirements were intentionally low for a video game, I still had to produce several hundred static graphics and GIFs, and commissioned custom music for the menu and gameplay.</p>
<p>This project is one of my favorite examples of what can be done in relatively little time with a focused vision and a constant eye on scope creep. From the very start, I knew that a key to making compelling software was to flesh out the core concept before all else. This is why I started on the most fundamental strategic interaction of the players and built an MVP version of the game without a menu, sound, art, or even a win condition.</p>
<p>I started the project on a Memorial Day Monday, and by Friday had a rudimentary prototype playable with 8 players on Nintendo Joy-Con controllers paired to a Windows machine via Bluetooth.<br>
This is what the project looked like for my first play-test with other people 5 days in:</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    







    





    



    























<img  alt="Land War 4-day MVP"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/land_war_mvp.gif"   style="height: auto; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">4-player game played with Nintendo Joy-Cons on a build of the game from 5 days into development.</span>
    
</div>

<p>From there, I continued to work on depth and full feature functionality including menus, a tutorial, a map generator, a dynamic scoring and round system, better sound and sprite graphics, different play modes and settings, and support for many controllers. I released the game with very little marketing aside from some Reddit posts and a physical handout at E3 but was happy to receive positive reviews and several hundred purchases of the game.</p>
<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    







    





    



    























<img  alt="Player Select screen"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/land_war_player_select.png"   style="height: auto; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">Player Select screen. Supporting menu and player controls across hundreds of controller types was one of the largest unforeseen challenges in developing Land War.</span>
    
</div>

<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    







    





    



    























<img  alt="Settings menu"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/land_war_settings.png"   style="height: auto; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">Settings menu. Most interesting mechanics I found while developing the game were added as options to keep the game interesting here.</span>
    
</div>

<div style="text-align: center; margin-bottom: 1rem;">
    





























    



    



    





    



    





    



    























<img  alt="E3 marketing material"   crossorigin="anonymous"    referrerpolicy="no-referrer"  src="https://hockenworks.com/images/land_war_e3.png"   style="height: auto; max-width: 400px; width: 100%"   >


    
        <span style="display: block; font-style: italic; margin-top: 0.5rem;">The only physical marketing material developed for Land War. Several hundred Steam keys (copies of the game) were handed out during the E3 convention in 2019.</span>
    
</div>


    <div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
      <iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" loading="eager" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/BylKEPF4EeU?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video"></iframe>
    </div>

<p><em>Land War&rsquo;s Steam release announcement trailer.</em></p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:hockenworks.com,2019-03-01:/land-war/</guid>

                
                    <link>https://hockenworks.com/land-war/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Land War</title>
                
            </item>
        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p><strong>Raspberry Pi Control Panel</strong> is a hardware project I designed in 2016 to manage home automation systems. The project involved designing a custom 3D-printed case for a Raspberry Pi microcomputer with a touchscreen interface.</p>
<p>Links:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/hockenmaier/RaspberryPiControlPanel">GitHub</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:2524560">Thingiverse</a></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>I created this panel display in 2016 to control much of the home automation I used in my Studio City apartment. Mainly a hardware project, I designed and 3D-printed a case and frame for the touchscreen and raspberry pi microcomputer in order to mount them to the wall. The software running the control panel is SaaS, but I did write a custom html wrapper to control the orientation and settings of the site, which is available on the github linked above.</p>
<p>Update in 2025: This panel is still my main view into my home automation in my new house in Sherman Oaks, almost 10 years in with no modification to the software or Pi itself! However, the LED behind the screen died this year and I had to replace it (link below)</p>
<p>Here&rsquo;s a video to see the panel in action:</p>
<h2 id="hahahugoshortcode29s0hbhb">
    <div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
      <iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" loading="eager" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/iFGmm-ijJvE?autoplay=0&amp;controls=1&amp;end=0&amp;loop=0&amp;mute=0&amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video"></iframe>
    </div>
</h2>
<p>Feel free to explore the linked repositories for schematics and source code.</p>
<h2 id="instructions">Instructions</h2>
<p>If you want to make this, all you need to do is set up a raspberry pi, download chromium (or your preferred web browser), and navigate to your action tiles panel.</p>
<p>If you want to mount the screen vertically like mine, then I have made an easier solution than going through the trouble of actually rotating the raspberry&rsquo;s display and touch device. Just use the html below and edit it to use your own panel&rsquo;s URL in the &ldquo;iframe&rdquo; element instead of mine. This will launch the panel rotated in your browser.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#fff;background-color:#111;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-html" data-lang="html"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#ff0007;background-color:#0f140f;font-weight:bold;font-style:italic">&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>&lt;<span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">html</span>&gt;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  &lt;<span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">head</span>&gt;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    &lt;<span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">title</span>&gt;Rotated Raspberry Panel&lt;/<span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">title</span>&gt;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    &lt;<span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">style</span> <span style="color:#ff0086;font-weight:bold">type</span>=<span style="color:#0086d2">&#34;text/css&#34;</span>&gt;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      <span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">body</span> {
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#fb660a">-webkit-</span><span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">transform</span>: rotate(<span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">90</span><span style="color:#cdcaa9;font-weight:bold">deg</span>);
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#fb660a">-webkit-</span><span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">transform-origin</span>: <span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">bottom</span> <span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">left</span>;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">position</span>: <span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">absolute</span>;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">top</span>: <span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">-100</span><span style="color:#cdcaa9;font-weight:bold">vw</span>;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">height</span>: <span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">100</span><span style="color:#cdcaa9;font-weight:bold">vw</span>;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">width</span>: <span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">100</span><span style="color:#cdcaa9;font-weight:bold">vh</span>;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">background-color</span>: <span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">#000</span>;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">color</span>: <span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">#fff</span>;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>         <span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">overflow</span>: <span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">hidden</span>;&#34;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      }
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>        <span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">iframe</span>{
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      	<span style="color:#fb660a">-ms-</span><span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">transform</span>: scale(<span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">0.97</span>);
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      	<span style="color:#fb660a">-moz-</span><span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">transform</span>: scale(<span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">0.97</span>);
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      	<span style="color:#fb660a">-o-</span><span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">transform</span>: scale(<span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">0.97</span>);
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      	<span style="color:#fb660a">-webkit-</span><span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">transform</span>: scale(<span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">0.97</span>);
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      	<span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">transform</span>: scale(<span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">0.97</span>);
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      	<span style="color:#fb660a">-ms-</span><span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">transform-origin</span>: <span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">0</span> <span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">0</span>;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      	<span style="color:#fb660a">-moz-</span><span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">transform-origin</span>: <span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">0</span> <span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">0</span>;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      	<span style="color:#fb660a">-o-</span><span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">transform-origin</span>: <span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">0</span> <span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">0</span>;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      	<span style="color:#fb660a">-webkit-</span><span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">transform-origin</span>: <span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">0</span> <span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">0</span>;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      	<span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">transform-origin</span>: <span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">0</span> <span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">0</span>;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      }
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    &lt;/<span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">style</span>&gt;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  &lt;/<span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">head</span>&gt;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  &lt;<span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">body</span>&gt;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    &lt;<span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">iframe</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      <span style="color:#ff0086;font-weight:bold">src</span>=<span style="color:#0086d2">&#34;https://app.actiontiles.com/panel/f7a7118c-236b-4144-b5b9-ccb35abeef21&#34;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      <span style="color:#ff0086;font-weight:bold">height</span>=<span style="color:#0086d2">&#34;300%&#34;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      <span style="color:#ff0086;font-weight:bold">width</span>=<span style="color:#0086d2">&#34;300%&#34;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>      <span style="color:#ff0086;font-weight:bold">frameborder</span>=<span style="color:#0086d2">&#34;0&#34;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    &gt;&lt;/<span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">iframe</span>&gt;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>  &lt;/<span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">body</span>&gt;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>&lt;/<span style="color:#fb660a;font-weight:bold">html</span>&gt;
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Link to buy the screen:
Modern:
<a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B07P8P3X6M">https://www.amazon.com/dp/B07P8P3X6M</a>
Original:
<a href="https://smile.amazon.com/gp/product/B01ID5BQTC/">https://smile.amazon.com/gp/product/B01ID5BQTC/</a></p>
<p>Link to the Action Tiles web application this is running:
<a href="https://www.actiontiles.com/">https://www.actiontiles.com/</a></p>
<p>If you have issues getting your pi to use the full touchscreen width, try adding these setting to the /boot/config.txt file and reboot:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#fff;background-color:#111;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#fb660a">max_usb_current</span>=<span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">1</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#fb660a">hdmi_group</span>=<span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">2</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#fb660a">hdmi_mode</span>=<span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">1</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#fb660a">hdmi_mode</span>=<span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">87</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>hdmi_cvt <span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">800</span> <span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">480</span> <span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">60</span> <span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">6</span> <span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">0</span> <span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">0</span> <span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">0</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>If you want to make sure your screen doesn&rsquo;t go to sleep:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#fff;background-color:#111;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>sudo nano /etc/lightdm/lightdm.conf
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Add the following lines to the [SeatDefaults] section:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#fff;background-color:#111;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"><span style="display:flex;"><span>xserver-command=X -s <span style="color:#0086f7;font-weight:bold">0</span> dpms
</span></span></code></pre></div>]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:hockenworks.com,2016-01-01:/raspberry-pi-panel/</guid>

                
                    <link>https://hockenworks.com/raspberry-pi-panel/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jan 2016 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Raspberry Pi Control Panel</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
