













    
        
    

    
        
    







    

    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"  xml:lang="en-us"  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            

            
                
            

            
                <link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/data-analytics/" rel="self" type="text/html"/>
            
        
            

            

            
                <link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/data-analytics/rss.xml" rel="alternate" type="application/rss+xml"/>
            
        

        

        

        <description>Recent content</description>

        
            <language>en-us</language>
        

        
            <lastBuildDate>2019-07-03 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</lastBuildDate>
        

        <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/data-analytics/</link>

        

        <title>Data Analytics · Tags · Home</title>

        

        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<p><strong>The Answering Machine</strong> is a proof-of-concept system that uses natural language processing (NLP) to produce answers to questions asked about data in plain English.</p>
<p><strong>Try it here:</strong> <a href="http://voicequery-dev.s3-website-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/">http://voicequery-dev.s3-website-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/</a>
<strong>Github:</strong> <a href="https://github.com/hockenmaier/voicequery">https://github.com/hockenmaier/voicequery</a></p>
<p><img src="/images/answering_machine_uploads.png" alt="Answering Machine homepage"></p>
<p>It is designed with simplicity in mind — upload any columnar dataset and start asking questions. Advanced NLP algorithms interpret your queries and assumptions, providing answers. You can even correct these assumptions for better follow-up queries.</p>
<hr>
<h2 id="features">Features</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Upload any dataset</strong>: Users can upload columnar datasets (CSV format) and start querying.</li>
<li><strong>Real-time responses</strong>: Questions are answered instantly, with NLP driving the interpretation and response generation.</li>
<li><strong>Serverless architecture</strong>: The system incurs no hosting costs apart from traffic-based expenses.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 id="how-to">How-to</h2>
<p>On a desktop or tablet, click the link above to navigate to <strong>The Answering Machine</strong>. Currently, it is not optimized for smartphones.</p>
<p>To use the system:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p><strong>Upload a dataset</strong>: Drag and drop a CSV file or use the upload button.</p>
<ul>
<li>Example files like &ldquo;HR Activity Sample&rdquo; are available for testing.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Start querying</strong>: Select a dataset and type your question in the query bar.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p><img src="/images/answering_machine_hr.png" alt="HR dataset view"></p>
<ol start="3">
<li>Use the <strong>information panel</strong> to understand dataset fields, data types, and sample values. This helps formulate more specific questions.</li>
</ol>
<p><img src="/images/answering_machine_info.png" alt="Info panel"></p>
<hr>
<h2 id="query-types">Query Types</h2>
<p>The system currently supports:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Counts</strong>: “How many employees joined in 2020?”</li>
<li><strong>Mathematical questions</strong>: Averages, medians, maximums, and minimums.</li>
<li><strong>Filters</strong>: Combine conditions like “What’s the average salary of engineers in 2019?”</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 id="concept-matching">Concept Matching</h2>
<p>If the NLP system misinterprets a query, users can create <strong>concepts</strong> to align query terms with dataset fields.</p>
<p><img src="/images/answering_machine_query.png" alt="Answering Machine query bar"></p>
<p>Concepts override the system’s auto-matching logic, ensuring accurate data interpretation.</p>
<p><img src="/images/answering_machine_concept.png" alt="Concept creation"></p>
<hr>
<h2 id="architecture">Architecture</h2>
<p><strong>The Answering Machine</strong> is a purely serverless application. Its backend consists of AWS Lambda functions, API Gateway, and other serverless components.</p>
<p><img src="/images/answering_machine_architecture.png" alt="Serverless architecture"></p>
<p>For more details, check out <a href="https://martinfowler.com/articles/serverless.html">Martin Fowler&rsquo;s article on serverless computing</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p>Feel free to explore the tool and test various datasets. Remember, this is a proof-of-concept system with no user accounts, so avoid uploading sensitive data.</p>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2019-07-03:/answering-machine/</guid>

                
                    <link>http://localhost:1313/answering-machine/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2019 00:00:00 UTC</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>The Answering Machine</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
